please be advised that this hearing is
being recorded this motion hearing of
the federal court heard by video
conference is now open presiding The
Honorable Justice gleon and before the
court the federal court file number
t1295 D20 between Ronco Inc versus Her
Majesty the Queen the council for the
plaintiffs and the responding party
Colin Baxter David Taylor and
Christopher
tra Sono and the council for the
defendant moving party Peter Nos backin
and Charles M
Maher and uh good morning to all can uh
let me start by first making sure we can
all hear each other so uh just go around
starting with you Mr Baxter yes thank
you we can both hear you okay great and
um I don't know who's taking the lead on
the uh on the respondant side or the uh
movie party side Mr nobin are you uh yes
I will start us off and and and we can
hear you fine thank you your all
right okay with that then um just very
quickly before we uh before we begin let
me have a uh let me quickly walk through
what I have in front of me and uh to
allow you to to flag anything more that
uh that that should be available to me
so I've got a copy of the uh
the uh fresh amended statement of claim
in front of me I have a copy of the
defendant's motion
record I've got a copy of the
plaintiff's uh responding motion
record I have a copy of the statement of
defense and there's also a reply that
was filed to that defense I assume it's
been overtaken by the
amendment I have a copy of the moving
part
books of authorities volumes one and
two I have a copy of and then I have a
couple of
additional uh cases that have been
provided to the court I've got
Sketchers decision of ponary
milinski I've got a copy of Supreme
Court Canada decision in city of
Nelson and I have a copy of uh decision
of Mr Justice grmo in Telecommunications
uh tell us Communications excuse me uh
and then finally I have a
copy
of the um the responding parties or the
plst book of
authorities is there anything else that
I should have in front of me before we
uh before we
begin there was one other uh material
file Justice gleon and and it was a
November 1st email uh attaching a
proposed amended statement of
claim I I don't know on what date uh
precisely it was filed do you have that
I do have that yes I do have that I
don't have it up electronically but I do
I out a hard copy of that I do not thank
you it's a essentially it's a short
email explaining the rationale for an
amend a proposed amendment as well as
paragraph 1A you will have noticed uh is
is revised uh so that anything else Mr
travisano no that's it thank
you and anything on the respondent side
over and above what I've just canvased
no you have everything Justice gon okay
great okay with that then um just before
we begin I I also have received a copy
of uh from on uh submissions from uh the
plaintiff and from the respondent on on
cost thrown away with respect to the
prior adjournment that's that I might uh
not might I will ask you to speak to
each of you to speak to briefly uh but I
think we'll save that till the end of uh
of the argument today uh and uh give you
a few minutes if there's something you
want to prepare with respect to that
issue but I I haven't I do have some
questions on cost rone away especially
given the fact that uh we're now hearing
this matter within a relatively short
window uh we're back we're back in front
of the court in three weeks and uh so I
definitely have some questions with
respect of the quantum that's being
sought and whether or not there actually
is uh uh thrown away costs here given
given the short passage of time or at
least costs thrown away to the extent
that have been uh been indicated in the
in the plain of submissions so so again
I'd like to hear from you on that and uh
and I'm I'll also be curious as to
whether not engaged in any further
discussions given given where we are
right now on that
issue um so that's my one preliminary
matter that I want to flag for you and
as I say I want to hear from uh from
both of you at the end of uh of the
matter today um
so before we begin first let me ask if
there's any preliminary matters uh Mr
nobin on on your side no PR preliminary
matters on our side and Mr Bax or
anything preliminary on your
side no sir no justice Leon okay okay
with that then I think I'm prepared to
start uh to to hear oral submissions in
on this matter I I've read the material
I'm generally familiar with the
circumstances uh and the the issues that
have been raised in the uh in the claim
and uh and the general positions of the
parties um and uh so so I'm going to
turn things over to uh to the
respondent thank you justice
gleon uh uh both Mr Mayor and myself
will be making submissions today on
behalf of the defendant uh on this
motion to strike portions of the plain
fresh as amended statement of claim um
essentially we seek to strike the
portions of the claim that seek to quash
the cbsa decision that imposed Customs
act duties and interest on the
plaintiff and the portions claiming
damages equivalent to the Customs act
duties and interest General damages and
damages for professional fees incurred
and that includes the ca the claims
based on negligence and on a breach of
public law
duties uh specifically we seek to strike
subparagraphs 1 a to d which are the
portions of the prayer for Relief
seeking these items paragraphs 46 to
60 claiming the various sets of damages
on the basis of parody
honey paragraphs
61-66 claiming the sets of damages on
the basis of a breach of Duty of care in
negligence and paragraph 67 which again
sets out the damages that the plaintiff
seeks the plaintiff brings this action
under Section 135 of the Customs act but
the relief it seeks Falls outside the
limits of that section a claim under 135
is limited to challenging a ministerial
finding that the Customs Act was
breached such that a penalty may be
imposed but aside from falling outside
the limits of a 135 action the claims we
seek struck out are also otherwise
outside this Court's Jurisdiction
disclose no reasonable cause of action
or or constitute an abusive Pro process
and should be struck on that
basis what can remain of the claim if
the defendant is fully successful on
this motion is the essence of the 135
action itself so the challenge to the
ministerial decision upholding the
penalty assessed against the
plaintiff finally we seek an order
providing an extension of time to file
an amended defense in response to uh
whatever remains of the statement of
claim uh I'll give a brief overview of
our submissions before we uh go further
in
depth the essential character the focus
of this claim and the relief sought is a
challenge to the validity of the July
2020 detailed adjustments
statement issued by the
cbsa this is a decision that required
the pain plaintiff to pay duties on
import importations of goods between
2015 and 2018
the parts of the claim that seek to
overturn the the detailed adjustment
statement referred generally as a
Das and seek damages equivalent to the
duties it imposes should be struck out
because first the court cannot quash the
cbsa decision on an action the court can
only quash a decision by way of judicial
review but second the federal court does
not have jurisdiction to deal with that
request even on judicial review here
given a statutory appeal scheme set up
by the Customs act which requires such a
challenge to go to the
CIT the courts have consistently found
the scheme ousts the jurisdiction of the
federal court to deal with such
matters and finally Artful pleading
cannot transform Customs act duties
essentially
taxes into damages be it a negligence or
under a breach of public law
duties the plaintiffs claims a those
headings would have the same effect of
nullifying the cbsa
decision we submit the plan if must
pursue the appeal scheme provided in the
Customs act to challenge the obligation
to pay the duties at
issue the portions of the claim seeking
General damages and damages for
professional fees incurred should also
be struck as disclosing no reasonable
cause of
action first no duty of care is owed to
the plaintiff to ground a claim
negligence in this claim
overall the pleadings of causation and
loss are
deficient and the pl if cannot be
awarded its costs incurred pursuing
various other appeal proceedings as
damages in this
action that's the outline of our
argument in a nutshell in terms of
structure today my submissions will
focus on uh the background and context
to the plaintiff's claim to the ENT that
it is helpful to you uh justice gleon
including the operation of the Customs
Act and the relevant facts as set out in
the claim and the documents it
references uh I will then make
submissions on why the claims related to
duties imposed by the cbsa should be
struck as outside this Court's
Jurisdiction including the request that
the dask be quashed and the damages
claims as it relates to the amount of
Duties and
interests finally will briefly address
some of the plaintiff's arguments
related to the potential for a
multiplicity of
proceedings and the assertion that the
issue of Reason to Believe would be
Central to all of
them my colleague Mr Mayor will then
present our submissions on the remainder
of the claims that should be struck the
claims for General damages professional
fees incurred and the general duty of
care issue as it pertains to the claim
as a
whole he will also address the
plaintiff's EST stopple
argument as you can see there are
several steps to our submissions we
submit that this reflects the fact that
the claim takes something relatively
simple and attempts to make it
complex we submit that we in the court
shouldn't be dissuaded by the apparent
complexity on this motion to
strike uh as a preliminary context this
action arises out of Customs act duties
and penalties imposed on the plaintiff
by the cbsa on import if I could just
stop you there mrb and and just who are
you going to take a few minutes and just
uh make some submissions on the motion
to strike standard what what what
standard I'm applying in law here I will
I can do that I can I can do that first
if you prefer you can do it where
wherever you're going to do it but I
would like to hear you on that issue
with respect to particular the ne claims
and the public law Duty claims I I would
like to clearly understand what your
position is with respect to the general
law that applies before we get into the
merits of of those okay well why don't I
go there now since since you're raising
the question
um uh the law on motion to strike is is
generally well known the court can
strike out a pleading in whole or in
part if it discloses no reasonable cause
of action and the test for that is
whether it is plain and obvious that the
claim has no chance of success assuming
the facts set out in the claim to be
true and proven
uh under rule
221 sub1 Suba it is appropriate for the
federal court to strike a statement of
claim for want of
jurisdiction uh This was done for
example in the verico case uh which just
for your references volume two tab 53 we
don't have to go there but that's where
it is uh of the defendants
book the plaintiff in that case was
unhappy with a tax assessment and
essenti sought to have his claim to a
tax credit adjudicated in the federal
court through a statement of claim
seeking
damages the Federal Court held that the
essential purpose of the statement of
claim related to a matter in the
exclusive jurisdiction of the tax court
and struck the claim on the basis that
it lacked
jurisdiction that's analogous roughly to
to what we're dealing with here
today uh rule 2211 F also allows the
court to strike parts of a claim that
constitute an abusive
process um we submit that the claim for
an order quashing the Das and the claims
for damages based on the duties and
interest which would effectively nullify
the Das are outside this Court's
Jurisdiction do disclose no reasonable
cause of action and and or an abusive
process so those are submissions on the
general tests applicable I'm not sure if
you wanted go further at this point
that's fine thank
you so in terms of just a preliminary
context of of what this case is about uh
this action arises out of Customs act
duties and penalties imposed on the plff
by the cbsa on importations of certain
Railway
Wheels following an audit the cbsa
required the plff to correct its tariff
classification on Goods imported between
2015 and
2018 which had been incorrectly declared
under a dutyfree tariff item and to pay
the Rel the related duties and interest
um the plaintiff was also required to
pay a penalty for not having made
corrections to its declarations earlier
when the cbsa says it had a re an
earlier reason to believe that its
declarations were
incorrect uh now J G I was going to take
you the Customs Act
is relatively complex I suppose and and
I was going to it's helpful take you
through the various Provisions but if
it's not helpful I don't want to take up
too much time doing that so I I I ask
what would be most I'm generally
familiar with the the Act and the
workings of the ACT um but but I think
it might be helpful for you to uh to
walk me through to make sure that uh
that the provisions and the way your the
position you take with respect to their
operation uh is understood by me okay
fair enough I'll do that then uh uh so
the Customs Act and the Rel
legislation seeks to oversee regulate
and control the crossb movement of
importations of goods it provides for a
voluntary self-reporting scheme to be
followed by
importers uh they it's it's the
responsibility is on importers to
declare their goods honestly and and
correctly uh the relevant portions of
the Customs act are at volume one tab
two of the defendants book of authority
um and maybe I'll just refer you to them
rather than take you directly to them if
that's the best way to not to take too
much time on this um so under Section
32 for goods to be released in Canada
importers are required to account for
the goods and to pay any related duties
this accounting includes declaring the
Tariff classification of the goods it
also includes declaring the goods origin
and value for Duty it's important to
understand that the ACT treats those
things for certain purposes in the same
way so some of the cases we'll be
looking to later will be dealing with
value for Duty as opposed to tariff
classification but in terms of
redeterminations and appeals they're
treated the exact
same uh section
571b sets out that tariff
classifications be determined in in
accordance with the Customs
tariff and whether duties must be paid
on imported goods depends in part on the
Tariff classification as well as other
factors a cbsa officer May determine the
Tariff classification of goods under
Section 58 sub
one if an officer does not make the
determination subsection 582 says that
the Tariff classification is deemed to
be as declared by the
Importer so an officer can check it and
make the determination or leave it as as
declared by the Importer
that tariff classification can change
after importation in certain
circumstances number one if the Importer
has reason to believe it declared its
declared tariff classification was
incorrect and it files a correction
under Section
32.2 or if the cbsa itself redetermined
the Tariff classification under Section
59 sub
one so first I'll take a look at section
32.2 subsection 2 states that the
Importer shall within 90 days after the
Importer has reason to believe that
their Declaration of tariff
classification is incorrect correct that
declaration and pay any amount owing as
duties and interests as a
result section 32.2
sub4 says that the obligation to do that
to self-correct ends four years after
the goods were originally accounted for
so when they originally
imported in other words for a period of
four years after the goods are imported
the Importer is required to self-correct
declarations tariff
classification pay any additional duties
within 90 days of having reason to
believe its original Declaration was
incorrect and it's not required to do
that after the four-year
period uh section subsection three says
that these importer correction s are to
be treated as redeterminations made by a
cbsa officer under 59 so once that
happens they both go down the same
stream in terms of further
redeterminations and
appeals um section 59 is the other way
of Declaration of tariff classification
may change and that's simply when a cbsa
officer directly makes that
redetermination
um subsection 592 says that an important
that an importer is entitled to a notice
of any determination under these
Provisions uh and the form of that
notice is a detailed adjustment
statement otherwise known as a
Das if the determination under 508 or
redetermination changes the amount of
the duties payable the Importer must pay
the deficiency or is entitled to a
refund as the case may be as indicated
on the Das
um the fritz case also lays this out uh
at paragraph 8 uh for your
reference uh once a Das is issued the
custom act provides a multi-level appeal
scheme set out in sections 59 to
68 under 59 as as I indicated uh the
cvsa May redetermined the Tariff
classification of goods within four
years of the date it was first
determined under
58 under Section 60 an importer can
request a further redetermination by the
president of the
cbsa in respect of anything that's
already been redetermined essentially an
appeal under Section 67 an importer May
appeal a section 60 decision to the
CIT and finally section 68 says that a
decision of the CIT may be appealed to
the federal court of appeal on a
question of
law now let me let me stop you there and
and cl ask you to clarify for me what
precisely is a SE section 67 or 60
decision composed of is it simply the
Tariff determination or is it also the
the uh retroactive payment of of of
Duties and and interests that arises out
of that decision as well and how how
that
amount has been arrived at or determined
what exactly is captured in this
decision is it the whole decision or is
it simply the Tariff portion of the
decision that's
reflected uh um typic typically it's the
Tariff portion but what's the important
thing to remember is that under 67 when
the appeal goes to
CIT the case law of both this court the
court of appeal and the CIT makes it
clear that it is not limited it to that
and that even if some an issue raised by
the Importer is not dealt with on a
section 60 appeal if if the if the
president says I'm not dealing with uh
um anything outside of the Tariff
classification it's that issue is still
to be brought to the
CIT so I will go through the case law
that that states that okay thank
you uh and as as I will come to the
courts have consistently found that this
scheme CS the jurisdiction of the
federal court on the matter subject to
it in the fritz case for
example
um now a self-correction by the Importer
or redetermination by the
cbsa uh can in certain
circumstances what be prompted by a a
trade compliance verification carried
out by the cbsa these are random
compliance verifications that the cbsa
conducts from time to time
in order to ensure compliance with the
Customs act these are carried out
pursuant to section
4201 uh and and they and and they review
declarations made by importers during a
particular verification
period so that's that's the the act the
relevant portions of the ACT uh as we
see it that pertain to tariff class
classification and the imposition of
Duties uh I'll I'll now move on to the
provisions regarding penalties I'll try
to move pretty quickly through this part
um subsection
109.2 um says that every person who
fails to comply with any designated
provision in the ACT is liable to a
penalty of not more than $25,000 as the
minister may
direct the designated Provisions Customs
regulate
include section 32.2 of the Customs act
as a designated provision we've included
those at tab three of our book
reference so since that's 32.2 is
designated if an importer fails to
correct declaration within 90 days of
having reason to believe its declaration
is incorrect it is a contravention of
the act that attracts a
penalty section uh 109.3 says that an
office May assess and issue a penalty to
a person liable under
1091 and serve on the person a written
notice of penalty
assessment so when that is
issued uh the the ACT sets out a
separate appeal scheme that relates to
the
Penalty under
d a person served with a notice of
penalty assessment may request a
decision of the minister of Public
Safety and preparedness under under
Section
131 1311 C says that where such a
request is made the minister shall
consider the case and decide whether the
person indeed failed to comply with the
act so that's what that's the decision
the minister is looking
at and
1321b says that if the minister finds
there was no contravention and a penalty
was not
justified the only result provided is
that the minister will cancel the
assessment of penalty and off authorize
the return of the money and interest
paid on account of the
penalty section 135 provides that a 131
decision of the
minister may be appealed by way of an
action in the federal court with the
minister as a defendant that's what
ostensively we're dealing with here
today and and again specifically what is
the subject of that 135
the right the the 135 is an appeal of
the decision under 131 by the minister
and that
decision is exclusively dealing with
whether the the Importer indeed failed
to comply with the ACT such that a
penalty may be imposed and the results
of that as I say is is is limited to
what's in section
1321b so if that appeal to the minister
is successful the only consequence is
canceling the penalty and returning
it
um the federal court so on a 135 appeal
I'll add that it states that the federal
courts Act and the rules on an ordinary
action is applicable on an action
brought under Section 135 and that's
according to subsection two of that
provision uh so it's important to see
that the scheme set out in the act um
number one out as we'll see out the
federal Court's Jurisdiction as it
pertains to uh tariff classification and
the duties resulting
um and and sets out a scheme for that
and it sets out a separate scheme for
the
penalties let me sorry I may be getting
ahead of you and if I am just say so but
so the the one 129 process allows a an
individual to or or Corporation to uh
seek a decision from the minister on the
issue of
compliance and and or the issue of the
nature of the penalty imposed am I
correct in understanding that's the
scope of
129 uh there are there there are two
Roots within that so it it it's
um in terms of the compliance that you
just spoke of it's only as it pertains
to the Penalty so it's not about whether
they got the Tariff classifed ific right
understood so it's an appeal of the
notice penalty assessment essentially
but there are two different Provisions
uh that apply so if it if in terms of
the uh whether or not the Act was
actually contravened by the
Importer is a decision under 131 yes and
there can be a separate decision about
the amount of the penalty which would be
issued under
133 the 135 uh
um appeal which goes to to the federal
court on an action is limited to whether
or not the 131 decision which is whether
or not there was a
contravention if the Importer wishes to
challenge uh
the
amount in a in in a in a somewhat odd
formulation of this act it it has to
pursue a judicial
review on that issue and I and I will I
will touch on that in a moment uh and
give a reference and factually um just
just to help me out in this particular
Circumstance the
contravention uh is there's there's a
determination that there was a
contravention of the act and a penalty
was
imposed and helped me understand exactly
what that penalty there appears to have
been two two items or two tariffs that
were an issue here uh as I understand
the record there was a $500 penalty
imposed with respect to one set of items
and a second $500 penalty imposed with
respect to the wheels issue that are
that's that's form the subject matter of
this particular action am I
correct uh yeah we we can go to that if
you want wish which is at the um I don't
need to go I I go if it's helpful but I
but I really just want to make sure that
I'm factually understanding the nature
of the penalty and what what portion of
the penalty
if it is at all in dispute here what
portion of the penalty is is an issue
okay well I guess I would answer that
with two points number one yes the
verification in this case did deal with
two different items that were imported
so one is the is the ruff boore wheels
uh and and that's what we're dealing
with today and that's the subject of
this action the other item is not the
subject of this AC and the penalty
imposed for the rough four wheels was a
$500 penalty am I correct uh I believe
it says $500 the plane ifs indicate a
thousand I
think that's my question okay they
appear to capture the whole of the
penalty for the two items uh my question
is are we engaged with both items here
today or we engaged with only one uh
well we would be engaged only with one
but even as far as that goes that's not
really the the core of what brings us
here on this motion to strike today
understood okay does that answer your
question it does perhaps Mr Baxter will
be able to clarify exactly what's the
issue it I understand it's not not the
core issue here but factually this seems
to all work together with a a series of
decisions that have been undertaken and
challenged through different routs and
that seems to be part of the uh the
underline basis for the for the uh for
the claims that are being advanced in
the actual I'd like to make sure I
understand what's what the basis of
those those PLS are right the the the
the the challenge to the notice of
penalty assessment and therefore the
subsequent ministerial decision is
related to the Penalty imposed on the
rough Bo
Wheels thank
you
um I'll now briefly go through uh
briefly as I can uh through the central
facts of this case as as as the
defendant sees it as set out in the
fresh as amended statement of claim and
the documents at
references uh as noted the plff is a
manufacturer and supplier of Railway
Wheels
uh and Wheel
sets um it Imports rough boore Wheels
into Canada from
2005 it declared the rough boore Wheels
it imported under a tariff item
1921 I'll just refer to it as the one
ending in point 21 uh which is
dutyfree so items under that
classification don't incur any
Duty in July of 2017 this cbsa commenced
a trade compliance verification audit
under Section
4201 for goods imported by the plaintiff
including the rough Bo Wheels as noted
they also looked at another
item with respect to the wheels it
looked at five sample importations that
occurred in
2015 the verification process
resulted in the cbsa final verification
report which was issued in July
2018 and that is at a tab
3A of the defendants book of
authorities um I can take you there
unless you're familiar enough with the
facts that you that that wouldn't be
helpful um but I'll just briefly go
through that as as it pertains to
[Music]
uh do you you have okay I do
have good um in the first
paragraph on the first page it indicates
that the verification period is from
July 1st 2015 to December 31st
2015 so that means that the sample trans
transactions it's going to look at come
from that period that the cbsa will
looked
at the fourth
paragraph indicates that some of the
goods in this verification were found to
be classified
incorrectly and that dases would be
issued to correct the tarff
classification of the specific sample
importations that were looked
at at the paragraph of the bottom of the
page it says under Section 32.2 of the
Customs Act importers have an obligation
to make a correction to a declaration of
tariff classification within 90 days
after the Importer has reason to believe
the original declaration is
incorrect um the findings specifically
with respect to the rough boore wheels
are on page three of the verification
report which I'm not sure if you're
looking electronically it's page 33 of
the
PDF I have it yes
uh the cbsa so starting starting with
the heading at the in the middle of the
page the cbsa finds the verified samples
were properly classified you see
classification declared and
classification
determined cbsa finds they were properly
classified under a tariff item ending in
29 which carries a 99.5%
duty rather than the item ending in a 21
as declared by the pl of
which incurs no
duties on the following
page uh it indicates the finding that
the plane have had specific
information so in the middle of the
page after the two uh links it says that
uh the plaintiff had a specific
information available to it so a reason
to believe regarding the Tariff
classification of the
goods and that was that the uh that the
Tariff was clear
essentially at the bottom of the page
the plaintive is required to correct
within 90 days of the date of the
report all of other transactions of the
same Goods that were verified back to a
maximum of four years
go to the following
page near the bottom of the page where
it says samples 4 five6
Etc uh this section deals with the
administrative monetary
penalty uh and and the samples 4 five6 6
Etc deals with the rough Bo
Wheels uh it states that by failing
failing to earlier correct its tariff
classification within 90 days of having
a reason to believe the plaint of
contravene section 32.2 of the Customs
act and that an MPA would be
assessed so that's the verification
report
um in August of
2018 the cbsa issued
redeterminations as it indicated it
would of the Tariff classification for
the five samples that it looked at in
the verification process so those are
redeterminations issued under Section
591 and these redetermination imposed
redeterminations impose duties on those
importations to reflect the N9 .5% Duty
rate under the proper clar
classification uh and for your reference
those are located at tab 3C the
defendants
record they did not involve
self-corrections they were just straight
redeterminations under
9 uh the plane have followed the appeal
scheme in the Customs act with respect
to those dases and brought an appeal on
the on on these five redetermined
samples to the president of the
cbsa under Section
60 it appealed the
section and and it was denied that
appeal and it appealed the section 60
decision further to the
CIT the C decision is at uh
tab
3D the CIT dismissed the appeal in March
of 2020 and confirmed the cbsa
determination that the rough Bo wheels
are properly classified with a duty of
99.5% and that the plainf had improperly
classified them under a duty-free
item the plff did not seek review of the
cit's
decision accordingly there's no dispute
that the plain if had been incorrectly
declaring the goods for years since 2005
under the wrong tariff
classification benefiting from the
duty-free
classification the only issue the plan
of disputes is which years it had to
self-correct for under Section
32.2 and pay duties
on now at the same time it was pursuing
those challenges of the five samples the
plan have also filed corrections as
instructed covering the rest of its
importations of the wheels for the years
2015 to
2018 these were filed in January
2019 and consists of of of blanket
adjustments for each year for your
reference those are at tab
3E in May of 2019 tab 3E did you say
that's
correct um
in May of that year of 2019 the cbsa
issued dases for those importations
pursuant to the plaintiff's Corrections
and imposed the related duties
owing so those it through that process
the corrections were were deemed to be
redeterminations under 591a of the
Customs act and those dases are at tab
3F
the plf again pursued the statutory
appeal route with respect to those
importations appealing the Das as
related to the corrections under Section
60 of the Customs act and on July 30th
2020 the president of the cbsa issued
his decision
upholding the determination under 59 in
the form of a Das and that is the July
Das which the plaintiff seeks to
overturn and that is found at tab
3G it is that July 2020 dask that
ultimately requires the plaintiff to pay
the retroactive duties and interest the
plaintiff
disputes the pl of commenced a judicial
review application and a CIT appeal both
seeking to overturn July 2020 Das both
proceedings were put in AB bance on
consent pending the result of the pus
action under Section 135 of the Customs
act which relates to the
Penalty I would just say as a side note
that when the defendant agreed to put
those those proceedings in advance it
was not we were not aware that the plan
would be seeking relief beyond the
limits of section
135 uh on this
action the judicial review notice of
application is at tab 3H for your
reference and the CIT appeal is at tab
3i the plan of states that it commenced
this multitude of proceedings based on
various pieces of advice it received
from the
cbsa and based on case law that I
provided indicating that the federal
court does not have jurisdiction over
these matters on a judicial
review if we go to tab
3i and it's page uh 139 of the PDF
that's of
assistance it's the second last page of
the notice of appeal to to the
CIT yes and it's the second last
paragraph we see that the plane of CIT
appeal raises front and center the issue
of the reassessment period
it argues that the July 2020 Das should
be reversed and that it should not have
to pay duties on itself Corrections for
the period that it did as it did not
have reason to
believe uh shifting now to the process
that got us here on the section 135
action
go ahead okay uh the cbsa issued a
notice of penalty assessment requiring
the plff to pay an administrative
monetary penalty for Contra reading the
Customs act on October 3rd
2019 and for your reference that's at 3K
the plan have contested the notice it
argued it had not had prior reason to
believe that its tariff classifications
were Incorrect and asked for a
ministerial review of the assessment
under section 129 of the
ACT a ministerial decision upholding the
finding that the plff had contravened
the act was issued in September of 2020
and is contained at tab 3L
of note the ministerial decision did not
deal with the July 2020 Das or duties
owed by the plaintive which makes sense
because that was that is not what is
dealt with on that appeal
route the plan if continued to pursue
the appeal scheme for challenging
penalties under the Customs act and
issued a statement of claim under
Section
135 issued in October of
2020 however instead of asking that the
ministerial decision upholding the
penalty be overturned the plff asked
that the July 2020 Das be quashed that
duties and interests pursuant to that
Das be reimbursed and that press
professional fees incurred be
reimbursed after the defendant indicated
an intention to file a motion to strike
the plff filed a fresh as amended
statement of claim to include pleadings
of
negligence and breach of public law
duties as discussed in parody honey and
to add a claim for General
damages nowhere in its statement of
claim or its fresh amended statement of
claim does the plantiff explicitly
request an over an order overturning the
September 2020 ministerial decision that
upheld the penalty assess assessment
which is the main focus of a 135
action so those cover the and this may
be a semantics issue but so I'm
clear that that ministerial decision
does two things it finds one a
contravention and
two uh upholds the penalty assessment uh
it upholds is that fair articul what's
happening there yes it upholds the fact
that a penalty was imposed it doesn't
deal with the amount of the penalty
under Section 131 understood
okay so those cover the central facts
and legislation applicable to this case
in The defendant's View
as I said we will now make submissions
seeking to strike the portions of the
claim or I will now make submissions
seeking to strike portions of the
claim uh number
one uh requesting an order quashing as
unreasonable the July 2020 Das and
number two damages for Customs act
duties and interest paid retro act my
colleague will then focus on the
remainder of our
submissions uh we will both address some
of the plaintiff's arguments in their
factum as we move along
um first in address
address sorry to rise uh justice gleon
if I might just a word yes Mr back I'm
sorry Mr nosach and um I just wanted
perhaps we can shorten things uh Ronco
has proposed an amendment that is not
seeking to quash the dash Ronco
acknowledges the problems U called out
by my friend in the case Fritz and
others and paragraph 1A is no longer
sought as relief in this case so to the
extent my friend was going to take um
take time to uh to uh dispute uh the
relief sought in paragraph 1A I can
perhaps shorten proceedings today by
assuring the court that in any event if
if unless this this action is completely
uh struck in the water struck dead in
the water paragraph 1A will not be um
will not be s and quashing the Das per
se is is no longer a relief s and I hope
perhaps that's of assistance to Mr nosb
and into the court and I'm sorry to
interrupt Mr nosb and I just thought it
might
assist thank you Mr Baxter Mr
nosp um our our submission is that
removing that single paragraph from the
claim
um is merely cosmetic
removing that signpost does not change
the essential character of the claim
which is a matter that is to go to the
CIT the claim seeks to nullify the
Das which can only only be properly
challenged through the Customs act
scheme and so I do think it is important
to go through the to go through the
law as it relates to jurisdiction on
these matters uh and so uh
if it pleases you justice gleon I I will
proceed to do so go ahead
okay first in addressing the claim it
should be understood that the section
135 of the Customs act does not justify
or authorize what the plaintiff is
seeking uh in this
action section 135 actions restricted to
an appeal of The Minister's decision
under
131 and the ACT clearly sets out that
the only consequences flowing from the
decision relate to the Penalty
assessment this is seen uh in the fact
that as we briefly discussed an importer
must separately bring an application for
judicial review to challenge a decision
on the penalty
amount rather than including it in a 135
action we see this discussed for example
in the starway case which just for your
referen is at tab 49 in paragraph 23
where the court said says the action is
limited to whether or not there was an
infraction to appeal the decision with
respect to the amount of a penalty Mr
starway was required to apply for
judicial review a completely distinct
procedure um the plaintiff's Fresh's
amended statement of claim goes well
beyond these limits of a section 135
appeal so I'll refer the court now to
the hos young versus Canada decision
which uh at the trial level you presided
over Justice gleon um in the federal
court of appeal decision the court of
appeal confirmed that a section 135
appeal per se concerns no genuine issue
other than whether there was indeed a
contravention of the Customs
act at paragraph 57 it states and this
is for reference at tab
25 yes having correctly concluded that
there was a contravention to sections 12
of the C act the federal court had the
power pursuant to Rule 25 to dismiss all
the allegations related to the appeal
pursuant to section 135 of the Customs
act as involves no other genuine
issue however the federal court of
appeal found that the rules of severance
and Joiner also apply to a section 135
action and on that basis it declined to
dismiss other causes of action brought
by the plaintiff such as allegations of
threats of violence solely on the basis
that they fell outside of
135 so the court said we can't get rid
of those just because they're outside of
135 given the rules of
Joiner notably the defendant in that
case had not challenged the individual
claims on any basis other than they fell
outside the limits of a section 135
action in this case we
do not only do we submit that the plain
if's claim Falls outside the scope of a
135 Act
and cannot be justified by that section
but also that they disclose no
reasonable cause of action in their own
right and are outside of this Court's
Jurisdiction and should therefore be
struck now I'm glad so the first the
first issue of course is is whether is
the first item requested in the claim
which is uh that the July 2020
D be struck be quashed I should say be
quashed as unreasonable and my friend
has indicated that there no longer
pursuing that um so I won't belabor the
point but suffice it to say that
subsection 183 of the federal courts act
provides that uh extraordinary remedies
such as cerai may be attained by the
federal court from the federal court
only by way of judicial
review uh so the the pl of can't get
there on an action that's well
established but what is still
significant and
important uh to understand is that here
we are dealing with a d redetermining
tariff classification and imposing
duties under the Customs act and in
these circumstances Parliament has set
up a scheme that must be followed and
which ousts the federal Court's
Jurisdiction even on judicial
review that is the appeal scheme that we
went through through uh contained in
sections 59 to 68 of the Customs
act this court and the federal court of
appeal have consistently found with this
process Parliament has outed the
jurisdiction of the federal court to
quash a Das for any
reason the federal court of appeal has
held that the CIT has the authority on
an appeal under Section 67 of the
Customs act to determine not only the
correctness of a decision on the merits
for example whether the cvsa arrived at
the correct tariff
classification but also on the das's
validity uh and I will take you to the
fritz decision of the federal court of
appeal which is at volume one tab
20 uh uh in this case the court of
appeal determined it did not have
jurisdiction to hear a Jr on the
validity of a Das because it fell within
the Customs act appeal
scheme the case concerns uh value for
Duty declarations rather than tariff
classifications but as I noted the same
appeal scheme applies in the same way to
both briefly the cbsa investigator was
granted a search warrant seized
documents of the
applicant and these form the base for
criminal
charges a court later set aside the
search warrant as violating the charter
and the documents were deemed
inadmissible outside those criminal
proceedings the cbsa issued a Das under
Section 59 based on the information
obtained as a result of the
unconstitutional search
warrant the applicant asked the cbsa to
cancel the Das because they were based
on unlawfully obtained
evidence when the cbsa refused to resend
the dases the applicant brought a Jr to
set
aside those decisions because they were
issued on the basis of information
obtained in breach of the charter the
federal court granted the application
but the federal court of appeal allowed
Canada's Appeal on the basis that by
virtue of customs of the Customs act
scheme Parliament has has ousted
jurisdiction of the federal court to
quash Adas paragraphs 31 to 36 are the
most
helpful um 31 says the jurisdiction of
the federal court in relation to
detailed adjustment
statements was considered more recently
in Abbot in that case Justice Lemieux
concluded that by virtue of the scheme
of the Customs act that includes the
privative Clauses quoted above
Parliament has ousted the jurisdiction
of the federal court to quash a detailed
adjustment statement in the alternative
he would have declined jurisdiction on
the basis of the existing
an adequate statutory
remedy par down in paragraph 33 Court
says I agree with Justice
Lemieux that subsection 596 which is the
privative Clause of the Customs act
deprives the federal court of the
jurisdiction to set aside a detailed
adjustment statement for any
reason and then in 34 he explains I
appreciate that in the federal court
application the detailed adjustment
statements were not being challenged on
the merits but rather on the basis that
the agency should not have issued them
using information subsequently found to
have been obtained in breach of Section
8 of the
chart indeed the issue as framed by the
parties and as adopted by Justice Hughes
was a challenge to the decision of the
agency to refus to cancel the detailed
adjustment statements when asked to do
so however in my view the parties and
Justice hes mischaracterize the question
to accept their characterization would
be to accept a semantic
exercise any challenge to a detailed
adjustment statement could be
characterized as a challenge to the
decision of the agency not to cancel it
as long as the agency refuses to cancel
it when asked and in paragraph 36 it the
court references that it's the CIT that
is the tribunal that has the mandate to
determine the validity and correctness
of the detail adjustment
statements uh in
Jockey this course this this court
followed Fritz in
dismissing an application that involved
the same issues the plaintiff raises in
its challenge to the July 2020 Das in
this
case the federal court decision is at
Volume 2 tab 30 of the defendant's book
and the subsequent CIT appeal decision
is at tab
31 and the CIT decision gives a more
thorough rundown of the facts in
procedural history I'll just briefly
outline them because they are very
similar to what we're dealing with
here in 2005 the cbsa began a
verification audit and issued its report
in 2008 in that case the report
concluded the applicants methods for
calculating value for Duty were
Incorrect and it stipulated the correct
method
it also found that the applicant had
reason to believe its declarations were
incorrect since
2005 and it required the applicant to
self-correct its declarations for All
Imports going back four years in that
case 2005 to 2008 pursuant to section
32.2 of the
act the applicant asked the cbsa to
resend its requirement that it go back
four years among other things it argued
that it didn't have reason to believe at
any earlier date until it received the
2008 report and that it should at most
only be required to self correct and pay
duties on a go forward basis similar to
the plaintiffs
here cbsa refused and issued dases
redetermining the
goods the applicant filed a judicial
review seeking to quash the
decision the federal court dismissed
that application on the basis that it
did not have jurisdiction to determine
the issue relied on previous jurist
prudence and finding and found that the
case fall fell in line with
Fritz the issu the issues the applicant
raised in that case squarely concerned
whether the applicant had reason to
believe its declarations were incorrect
at the time of import and whether it
would need to correct its declarations
and pay duties going back four
years at paragraph 30 of the Jockey
decision in the federal court the court
found that this is a matter for the
Customs act appeal scheme quote I am of
the view this is a matter for the
president of the cbsa and if unresolved
for appeal to the CIT the specialized
tribunal designed by Parliament to
resolve such issues and at paragraph 31
the court concludes the federal court
does not have jurisdiction to hear this
matter in the alternative I would follow
Justice McTavish in outer space Sports
decline to entertain the application for
judicial review because the review
process in the act constitutes an
adequate alternate
remedy the federal court followed Fritz
and jockey in the recent case of
Sketchers which we uh filed with the
court subsequent to our
factum
um again it's very similar after
conducting a verification the cbsa
required Sketchers to perform
self-corrections of declarations and pay
duties going back four years from the
date of the report the date of the
report in the Sketcher case was deemed
to be the date the applicant first had
reason to believe this declarations were
incorrect so in that case it differed in
that there was no earlier reason to
believe found it was only with the
issuance of the
report the applicant had argued and even
with that I might add even with that no
earlier reason to believe it was held
that the Importer in that case had to
pay for the previous self-correct and
pay any duties for the previous four
years uh the applicant had argued that
it should only have to make Corrections
on a go forward basis into the
future and requested the cbsa cbsa grant
that request which the cbsa refused so
Sketchers brought a judicial review of
that
refusal Sketchers included
arguments that the cbsa was deviating
from its policies
and from how it treated other
importers in requiring it to
self-correct for the previous four years
very
similar the cbsa brought a motion to
strike that application which the court
granted and the court found at paragraph
23 I I'll read that portion there is no
basis however to conclude that the
federal court has jurisdiction to weigh
in as Justice Stratus in AP Morgan notes
a failure to follow policies is not by
itself an abuse of discretion policies
do not have the force of Law and
administrative decision makers can
depart from them the matters disclosed
by Sketchers concern the methodology for
determining value for Duty and Sketcher
obligations flowing there from under the
Customs
act Sketchers can put its arguments
concerning cbsa decisions policies and
discretion as the Importer in Fritz
marketing could Advance Charter
arguments to the president of the cbsa
the CIT and the federal court of
appeal the court concluded by stating
that as in Jockey the application should
be dismissed on the grounds that the
federal court did not have
jurisdiction finally on this point I
would just mention the federal court of
appeals decision in the CB Powell case
which for reference is at Tab four of
our book of
words this case stands for the fact that
an importer must complete the appeal
scheme in the Customs act before seeking
recourse to the courts and perhaps this
relates to a point we were discussing
earlier this means an importer should
pursue an appeal to the CIT on an issue
even if the cbsa refused to deal with it
on a section 60
appeal in the CB Powell
case the cbsa president refused to
address an issue on a section 60
redetermination that did not explicitly
form part of the officer's section 59
redetermination under appeal but that
the Importer had raised at the 59
stage the Importer brought a judicial
review seeking a declaration that the
cbsa negative jurisdiction decision
could lead to an appeal to the
CIT Justice Stratus States under the ACT
Parliament has established administ so
and the and the court granted that the
court granted a declaration that that
the Importer could appeal that to the
CIT uh and the federal court of appeal
differed slightly saying that under the
ACT Parliament has established an
administrative process of adjudications
and appeals in this area he references
the scheme in the Customs
act he goes on to say the courts are no
part of this allowing the courts to
become involved in this administrative
process before it is completed
would inject an alien element into
parliament's
design the federal court of appeal found
that the Importer should have pursued an
appeal to the
CIT on the issue whether certain the CIT
would find it had jurisdiction or not it
has to the Importer has to go through
the
scheme so on the other side of things
from the cit's point of view the CIT has
taken up this view of its Authority that
allows it to examine and Rule upon the
validity of AAS as a whole and not just
its
correctness it is not restricted to
looking only at a strict basis for a
section 60 decision on its merits such
as the correct tariff classification
origin or value for
Duty uh we referenced a number of
examples in uh our factum where the CIT
does this uh including uh where um the
identification identity of the Importer
is an issue or where the verification
audit process was an issue I'll just
take you to two the groden case and the
jockey CIT
case um in groden I I don't think we
have to go there but I I I'll just
outline the decision um in
groden um the case dealt with whether
the CIT
could deal with the issue of whether or
not a Das was invalid as being time
barred for being issued more than four
years after the relevant importations
contrary to the
act on the section 60 appeal the
president of the cvsa simply upheld the
findings of the Das and did not deal
with the time bar
issue the CIT held that it the CIT held
that it did have jurisdiction to
determine the issue even if not dealt
with in the section 6
decision at paragraph 29 of that case
the tribunal notes it is clear that
Parliament intended to confer on the
tribunal broad appellant jurisdiction in
the tribunal's view its Authority Under
the ACT is not limited merely to the
narrow substantive question of the
correct tariff classification origin or
value for duty of imported
goods goes on to say at 33 the tribunal
has the authority under Section 67 to
determine not only the correctness of a
decision made under Section 60 but also
its validity and it cites the britz case
for
that and at paragraph 36 the tribunal
says an appellant must first ask the
cbsa pursuant to section 60 to
reconsider the matter and the effect of
section 67 is to then escalate the
matter to the
tribunal uh clearly the case law opposes
the plain assertion in its factum that
the CIT is limited to considering the
correct
origin tariff classification or value
for duty of the
goods and indicates that that argument
is without Merit when the jockey
case was uh was was struck by the
federal court and went back to the
CIT uh the CIT did not decline to graph
with the issues at hand in this case as
the plain of suggesting their fact
rather it dealt with them at length over
the course of 38
paragraphs just for your reference again
that decision is at tab 31 of the
defendant's
book the Importer there argued that it
should not have been required to
self-correct its declarations and pay
duties going back four years because it
did not have earlier reason to believe
as found by the
cbsa essentially that the resulting gas
was invalid as a
result in its decision the CIT set out
the party's arguments and positions in
full by paragraphs 248 to
260 the CIT found that jockey's
obligation to self-correct its
declarations from 2005 to 2008 and pay
retroactive duties was not in fact
dependent on jockey having reason to
believe
in 2005 that its declarations were
incorrect the CI therefore found that it
it didn't have to determine specifically
when jockey first had reason to believe
this declarations were incorrect to
resolve the appeal and the validity of
the
Das it does find that the requirement
for the self-corrections was in
accordance with the act and it explains
at length why it makes its findings
paragraphs 264 to 284
so the CIT said that it didn't have to
determine when jockey first had reason
to believe since it made no difference
on that particular set of
facts but it does grapple with and
decide that the D is valid after
considering the
arguments now in Jockey as in the
current case the Importer is not looking
for a finding on when it first first had
reason to believe its declarations were
incorrect as a standalone issue in its
own
right uh a genuine 135 action would
would would take care of that the
Importer in that case and the plaintiff
here is seeking to invalidate the
requirement that it pay retroactive
duties that's what they're looking for
the CIT squarely dealt with that issue
in jockey
now at paragraph 57 of its factum the
plaintiff says that in its initial
appeal to the
CIT on the five sampled Goods that were
redetermined under 59 that it did not
have the power to determine how the
Tariff classification should ultimately
impact the appellant with respect to the
duties imposed so as I see that was in
the decision regarding the five import
importation sampled and didn't involve
uh
self-corrections or the requirement to
make
self-corrections and the C made that
particular statement in the context of
discussing any impact an advanced ruling
issued to a third party would have on
its
decision which was
none the CIT did not say that it did not
have the ability to determine the
validity of a Das clearly it does have
that ability based on the case law and
the jockey case in particular where the
CIT dealt with virtually the same issue
as being raised
here finally with respect to jockey I
would just I would just correct
paragraph 89 of the plff plaintiff's
factum where it says that the cbsa
argued in Jockey that it would be for
the federal court not the CIT to decide
when the Importer had reason to believe
its declarations were correct if you go
to the relevant paragraph in the CIT
decision it's paragraph
260 uh it is clear that the cbsa makes
that statement only in describing the
process of appealing a notice of penalty
assessment which culminates in a section
135 action the cbsa was not arguing the
CIT could not deal with the validity of
the
Das it did argue that the reason to
believe was not relevant to the validity
of the Das but it didn't say
that uh the CIT cannot deal with that
and I I'll read the paragraph to make it
clear to the extent here is here is what
what what it says to the extent that the
minister of Public Safety and emergency
preparedness upholds the reason to
believe finding which underpinned the
imposition of the penalty the Importer
can then appeal that decision by way of
an action of the federal court pursuant
to section 135 of the ACT in these
circumstances the cbsa argued that it
would be for the federal court not the
tribunal to decide when the Importer had
reason to believe that its declarations
were incorrect so of course in the in
the circumstances of a 135 action it is
for the federal court to deal with that
issue so just
just just to help me out a little bit
here on this issue of reason to believe
a reason to believe is a legitimate
issue uh before the federal court in a
135 action or potentially a legitimate
issue and could also be a legitimate
issue before the
CIT
correct I can I can and does that leave
open the the point that your friend will
make in his submissions that uh that
that this allows for inconsistent
decision making uh confusion for the for
in this case the plaintive etc
etc uh no I don't think it does I think
I think that they can pursue both both
roots and they deal with different
aspects and and I mean what we thought
was going to happen when we agreed to
the Advance was that they wanted to
pursue the 135 appeal first and then
would you know use to the to the extent
that is helpful use the results of that
in the other
proceeding so so again that
perhaps not relevant here um but if that
were to occur and there were a
conclusion reached in 135 action that uh
the reason to believe finding
was
incorrect what's the impact on the CIT
process if if that's if that's what
occurs in this case in this case or or
even more generally I'm just looking for
interal understanding well I do I do
think that it it very much depends on
the facts of the case so as we see in in
the jockey case and we would submit in
this case and we do in paragraphs I
believe 71 to 75 of our factum that the
reason to believe actually has no impact
on the obligation to go back now there
can be other cases where uh it it may um
make a difference so my friends refer to
the policy that cbsa has
and what is interesting about both the
jockey case and this case is that the
the timing between the um verification
period so in this case it was
2015 uh and the date that the report was
issued is four
years if we had a case where the the
time period between those two events was
two years so for example uh a
verification period was
2019 and the um verification report was
issued in
2021 and there was no uh no issue no
reason to believe at an earlier date the
policy says that the Importer is to pay
is to correct duties in the in and pay
sorry correct importations and pay
duties during the verification period
and going forward from that so from in
that case the policy would indicate it
would be the 2019 2020 21 going forward
however if there is reason to believe
they have to go back and correct under
the policy four
years up to a maximum of four years to
the date where the where the reason to
believe First existed so that could mean
in that case that they have to go back
from even before the verification period
to
2017 um so again that that case that
hypothetical case involves a
verification period of 2019 a report of
2021 four years back from the report is
2017 so I I mean I I would I would
submit that that ALS that illustration
also
um
uh undermines the plaintiff's submission
that our interpretation renders me
reason to believe in the policy
meaningless I think I've just
demonstrated that it still does hold so
in a case like that it may it may be
relevant or it may not be relevant as
determined by the
CIT which is their in their purview to
determine uh whether reason to believe
is is is significant or not but the core
issue in any case
is the validity of the Das and whether
or not uh it was a valid decision to
make the Importer pay retroactive
duties all right I'm I'm left with this
with
this lingering question
with with respect to this reason to
believe
determination
um and the possibility I I acknowledge
the submissions you make with respect to
this particular circumstance that
perhaps it's of no no uh consequence uh
given the timelines that we're dealing
with although I think your friend takes
issue with with the way the policy
itself has been been uh been interpreted
perhaps if I've understood the argument
correctly but but the issue the question
I'm I'm left with with is that the the
federal court could come to one
conclusion on the question of reason to
believe and it remains this very issue
could also be decided by the CIT in a in
in a separate proceeding that uh that
might well lead to a different
conclusion and
uh how how does that issue get resolved
is that that for the federal court
appeal to sort out is that is that your
position
or the possibility that this could even
happen C certainly there is a further
appear appeal to the federal court of
appeal from the CIT uh decision um on a
question of law and the recent case of
Best Buy uh indicates that there's also
the possibility of a judicial review
from the
CIT uh in a narrow window that's defined
in that case and so absolutely abolutely
if if the timing requires that then they
can pursue that further there and that
would Rectify that or as in as is the
case here um a uh a proceeding may be
put in
advance all right thank
you um so the case law I've taken you
through um establishes in our view that
the Customs act scheme indeed deprives
the federal court of the jurisdiction to
set aside a detailed adjustment
statement for any
reason um this is further relevant
because it means that it would not be an
appropriate remedy in this case for the
court to order that the action part of
the action be converted to a judicial
review under rule
57 or that it be considered a judicial
review converted to an action under
section 18.4 of the federal courts act
those remedies may be appropriate in
some other cases but here it is plain
and obvious that such an application
would fail as it did in jocky given the
scheme under the Customs
act accordingly the federal court does
not have jurisdiction to issue an order
quashing the 2020 Das whether on an
action or or on a Jr and that paragraph
if it remains should be struck out
but the plff but the plff cannot obtain
essentially the same relief it seeks in
quashing the 2020 Das simply by labeling
the Customs act duties and interested
those as damages in the claim as it is
attempted to
do despite this different
framing the plaintiff effectively seeks
to obtain the same remedy of having the
Das overturned essentially nullifying
its
effect the purpose of the July 2020 Das
is to directly impose duties essentially
imposing
ax on the
plaintiff having those duties reimbursed
to it as damages has the same effect as
overturning the decision that impos them
draining it of legal
effect as we've seen it's before the CIT
and onto the federal court of appeal
under the Customs act scheme that the
plff must pursue its challenge to the
Das and SE to overturn it not the
federal
court the federal court has held that it
may strike a statement of
claim if it's essential character in an
application that is an application for
judicial review with only a thin
pretense to a private
wrong and we say the same thing applies
here where it's properly an appeal to
the
CIT another Public Law remedy which
replaces the judicial review
option the court States this for example
in the in the recent Leone case and the
Stewart case those are at tabs 34 and 50
for your reference uh and those cases
cite the Supreme Court decision in
telone to that
effect in the current matter the
essential character of the claim is a
challenge to the 2020 Das which must be
taken to the CIT under the Customs act
scheme
we submit the pretense in this case is
very thin indeed the pl of seeks in
essence to undo what was done by
overturning the Das or having it effect
effectively nullified the fresh as
amended statement of claim
until its recent suggested Amendment
explicitly seeks an order quashing as
unreasonable the July 2020
D it also describes the cbsa decision as
the unreasonable imposition of ret
retroactive duties and it claims it
should not have been required to pay the
retroactive duties set
out in the 2020
death as I said uh earlier uh when the
plan of provided uh the proposed
amendment in November removing paragraph
1A of the claim um we submit that such a
proposed amendment is merely
cosmetic and it just removes a
signpost but does not change the
essential character of the claim
with its original amendments to its
original statement of
claim the plan of added allegations that
the cbsa breached a duty of care to the
pl by treating the plaintive differently
from other importers by imposing
retroactive duties following a trade
compliance
verification by imposing retroactive
duties in a manner inconsistent with the
representations of a cbsa
director and in osing and by imposing
retroactive duties in a manner
inconsistent with the cbsa policies
based on these allegations the plaintiff
claims that is entitled to damages in
the exact amount of the duties and
interest it says was errone it was
erroneously required to
pay the plaintiff simply disagrees with
the cvsa determination that it is
required to pay duties and interests on
import importations from 2015 to
2018 the Ed breaches are merely ways the
plaintiff feels the decision was
unreasonable such that it be set aside
or
nullified it is not content to let that
decision stand as plaintiffs were in
other cases that were allowed to proceed
his
actions for example this is a far cry
from the claim at issue in
telone in that case telone brought an
action against
Canada seeking compensation for
financial losses it incurred when Canada
in its view improperly refused to Grant
it a
license the action was for breach of
contract negligence and unjust
enrichment and sought compensation for
losses pisone did not seek to overturn
the decision granting licenses only to
others or seek to limit its legal effect
the case also did not involve a tax-
likee situation where the
decision itself directly required the
plaintiff to pay money which the
plaintiff then sought reimbursement for
which is the case here so if I
understand your submission if if the
plaintiff had framed or framed the
damage claim in this case in the context
of some future loss that's resulted from
this this assessment speaking very
hypothetically here I don't know if if
that's possible or not uh your objection
would disappear is that is that what
what I understand the uh the submission
to me the objection is the way the
damages have been framed damages has
been framed in a manner that clearly
indicates that they're linked at least
based on your submission to the Tariff
and the retroactive tariff uh repayment
that's required um had those damages
been been framed in some other manner
that suggested some future loss um I
take it the objection would disappear is
that is
that I would put it slightly differently
I I I would say that they are they are
accurately framed to the extent that
they are labeled as the duties and
interest because that is exactly what
this claim is trying to do um if it were
uh
um so I I don't I don't I don't know if
it's a matter of framing I mean I think
if it concerned something else
um it it's possible depending on what it
was hypothetically that that that that
that would be different but at any
rate it's not those those damages which
are the ones that I'm dealing with right
now are not like tesone damages they are
taxes that the decision directly
imposed and
uh and by seeking those damages those
amounts which I think are accurately
set out as being the duty amounts uh the
the uh the plaintiff seeks to overturn
that decision either literally by
quashing it or effectively by having
those amounts
reimbursed uh I think the language at
paragraph 79 of the of the Supreme
Court's decision in tazone is helpful um
that that's at toab 13 uh of our book
um and I'll just I'll just go through
part of it um sorry tab tab 13 did you
say that's correct and it's page 318 of
the P I've got it yes go ahead uh tazone
is not attempting to nullify or set
aside The Minister's order its case is
that the minister in deciding not to
issue a license to tazone acted in
breach of his contractual and Equitable
duties or in breach of a duty of care
telone does not say that The Minister's
decision should be
quashed on the contrary
Tone's causes of action in contract tort
and Equity are predicated on the
finality of that decision excluding tone
from
participating from participation in the
Telecommunications Market thereby
causing it Financial loss nor does
tazone seek to deprive The Minister's
decision of any legal effect it does not
challenge the licenses issued to its
competitors it does not seek to undo
what was
done the plaintive in this Case by
contrast does seek to undo what was done
whether directly under the pretense whe
whether directly or under the pretense
of a damage is claim it does seek to
deprive the decision at issue of legal
effect uh I would also say that the the
current matter is also different from
the negligence claim in parody honey
this the negligence claim in parody
honey that the federal court of appeal
refused to
strike the plainist in that case were
beekeepers who brought a class action
claim in negligence against Canada the
claim was based on a Minister's decision
to impose a blanket ban on the
importation of specific honeybee
packages despite having no lawful
authority to do so and his refusal to
consider even consider uh permit
applications uh the claim was for
resulting losses and damages to
beekeepers who relied on the B package
Imports to sustain stain their
beekeeping
businesses here again the plaintiffs did
not seek to overturn or undo the refusal
to issue importation perits and here
again the decision that issue did not
directly require the plaintiffs to pay
money that they sought reimbursement for
wasn't a tax- likee
situation in contrast to those two
cases is the Federal Court decision in
flaro that's at tab 18 te you for your
reference in that
case the plaintiffs brought an action
under Section 17 of the federal courts
act seeking a declaration that the
defendant was unlawfully detaining funds
that had been seized pursuant to the
exis
Act and the claim sought damages in the
amount of the seized
funds the court dismissed the claim it
found that the for for
of the funds should have been challenged
through the specific statutory review
mechanism set out in the exis ACT which
was app applicable in that case and that
the funds could not be recovered as
damages the court States at paragraph
76 these plaintiffs seek the same remedy
they may have received had they followed
the statutary process for review by the
minister considering that they failed to
resource under those Provisions it would
undermine parliament's intent to not now
allow the plaintiffs to wait out the
time limits and seek the same remedy in
the federal court they should have
sought before they should have sought
from the
minister they should have followed the
scheme in the ACT rather than bringing
in action for
damages if the current plti were
successful on an appeal to the
CIT it's obl obligation to pay duties
and interest on the importations would
be
removed and any duties and interest paid
reimbursed it would get the same remedy
with respect to duties and interests it
seeks
here it can't be that where an importer
disagrees it should have to pay duties
taxes imposed on it by a Das that it can
circumvent the statutory scheme put in
place by Parliament by calling the
duties damages and bringing an action
the defendant submits it's plain and
obvious that the plaintiff's framing the
claim for duties and interests as
damages does not change the fact that
the claim's essential character is a
challenge to the Das which must be
brought to
CIT it does not have the essential
character of a private
wrong accordingly the portions of the
statement of claims seeking damages for
duties and interest as a result of the
breach of Duty of care should be struck
as being outside this Court's
Jurisdiction and disclosing not
reasonable cause of
action uh I I'll now turn to the
plaintiff's claim for damages and the
amount of Duties and
interest on the basis of the parody
honey
case just before I just see we're at
we're we're at about 1105 here
um thinking of a a break how much longer
do you think you're going to be Mr
mbacham I don't think I should be uh too
much longer it's probably best to have a
break between myself and my colle okay
and that's fine
great I'll try to move as quickly as I
can
um uh the the plain if's pleading of
breach of public law
duties referencing parody honey does not
affect the essential character of the
plain's claim with respect to the duties
in interest or the fact that it
challenge must be pursued at the CIT
um as I'm sure you're familiar with the
majority in parody honey contemplated in
obiter the notion of a claim for
monetary relief in public law as an
alternative to what the courts have been
doing which is applying private law
concepts of negligence to governments
with various
adaptations uh the notion of such a
claim or cause of action has not since
been taken up by the courts in fact two
months ago the Supreme Court in the
Nelson versus marchie decision which we
uh filed after it was
issued um rejected the
concept at paragraph 41 the Supreme
Court States in reference to the
approach proposed in par
honey quote such an approach has no
basis in this Court's Juris Juris such
an approach has no basis in this Court's
jurist Prudence it also runs counter to
Crown proceedings legisl in Canada which
subjects the crown to liability as if it
were a private
person it rejects the notion of such a
cause of action as as articula and
parody honey and the federal court has
already acknowledged this disapproval of
parody honey in in telis Communications
versus Videotron which we also passed up
and just for your reference it's at
paragraph 84 that it makes that
statement we submit that this rejection
by the Supreme court is sufficient to
strike the plaintiff's claims based on
parody
honey in any event with respect to the
duties and interest damages claimed
under that
head it's our submission that the
plaintiff's claim uh does not even fit
within the framework contemplated by the
federal court of
appeal the majority in parity honey made
clear that in some cases an award of
monetary relief will be neither
necessary nor appropriate
but paragraph 143 of that
decision just as Stratus States the
compensatory objective of monetary
relief must be kept front of mind so in
some cases the quashing of decision or
the enjoining or prohibition of conduct
will suffice and monetary relief will
neither be necessary nor
appropriate the present
case as it relates to uh duties and
interest damages is such a case an award
of monetary relief is neither necessary
nor
appropriate the plan does not seek to be
compensated for economic losses that
flow Downstream when it seeks damages in
the amount of Duties and
interest it doesn't flow Downstream from
the cbsa decision to oppose duties it
seeks to have the duties themselves
effectively nullify this is the type of
case that Justice Stratus describes in
Canada versus Oshkosh
where the administrative remedies will
quote have the direct effect of
requiring that monies be paid and the
return of the monies paid or owing under
the decision is the inexorable
consequence of quashing the decision if
as I said if the plan follows the only
appropriate route to challenge the Das
and is successful on appeal to the CIT
its obligation to pay the duties in
interest would be removed and any
payments reimbursed accordingly the pl
claim for monetary relief in public law
is neither necessary nor
appropriate ultimately letting the pl of
proceed with its action for the duties
and interests imposed by the Das in
either negligence or a claim for breach
of public law duties would frustrate
parliament's intention as to how these
matters are to be
determined it's claim for duties and
interests owing as damages going from
either cause of action should be struck
um I should be fairly quick with the
rest of my submissions
um we will rely on our written
submissions with regard to our
alternative argument that claiming
Customs act duties and interest as
damages constitutes a collateral attack
on the
Das
um suffices to say the plane if if
allowed to do so would have achieve
through through what it through
collateral attack what it can only
properly seek to achieve by pursuing an
appeal to the C
it um to sum up the various parts of our
jurisdiction argument on the claim as it
relates to duties and interests imposed
by the
Das first the court cannot quash a
decision in an action but only in a
Jr second the court cannot even do that
here as the Customs act sets out an
appeal scheme that out the jurisdiction
of the court to overturn a Das for any
reason including its validity
the federal court doesn't have
jurisdiction to deal with these matters
the only way to challenge Das is through
the
CIT third the plaintiff's attempt to
characterize tax- likee duties as
damages does not change the fact that in
its Essence the claim seeks to nullify
the cbsa Das something that can only be
done by way of an appeal to the
CIT and the plff can follow that route
in this case all it has to do is take
its CIT appeal out of
abeyance I'll now briefly address two of
uh my friends arguments from their
factum which I haven't yet touched on
first the plaintiff argues that if our
position were accepted it would mean the
plaintiff would have to pursue multiple
proceedings it argues this would be
impractical inefficient overly
complicated encounter to the priority
given to access to
Justice to this argument we simply
respond that as we have seen with the
Customs act Parliament has set out two
separate appeal schemes one for
challenging penalties assessed under the
ACT which culminates in an action to the
federal court and a separate one for
challenging a Das which goes to the CIT
federal court of appeal and Os the
jurisdiction of the federal
court in answer to paragraph 102 of the
plain's factum which sets out to the
various proceedings they say our
argument would
require we say that yes the plaintiff
must pursue a section 135 action to
challenge The Minister's decision
upholding the penalty assessment that's
required by the
ACT if the plaintiff had legitimate
damages claims properly pursued by way
of an action unlike the ones here these
could be joined to the 135
action we say that yes the plaintiff
must pursue a separate Jr to challenge
the amount of the penalty as the case
law has shown in the ACT
requires and yes the plff must pursue an
appeal to the CIT to challenge the July
2020 Das in the duties it imposed as
we've argued
today plan if doesn't have to pursue
them all at the same time proceedings
can be put in advance but these are the
routes that must be
followed the plan if points to the break
case which discusses consolidating a
judicial review application and an
action in the interest of access to
Justice
however that case and that discussion
did not involve a statutory scheme set
up by Parliament to deal with the issue
which outs the jurisdiction of the
federal court Parliament has has done
that here under the Customs act so that
case is not
instructed the plaintiff cannot ask the
court to ignore parliament's intent the
Customs act the federal courts Act and
the Juris prence of this court the
courts above to reduce the number
proceedings it has to
follow this brings me to the related
assertion by the plaintiffs that all of
these proceedings would turn on the same
issue of reason to believe this is not
the case and we we did touch on this
briefly in reference to the Jo
decision uh whether the minister so to
go through the proceedings whether the
minister properly upheld the notice of
penalty assessment could hinge on reason
to believe the amount of the of the
penalty and a challenge that by way of
Jr would not hinge on reason to believe
it would hinge on the reasonableness of
the
penalty and as I as I said whether the
plff had earlier reason to believe would
also not determine the validity of the
Das and the requirement to pay
retroactive duties which is at the heart
of this claim as I referenced we set at
our arguments there at at paragraphs 71
to 75 of our written
submissions the the plaintiff May
characterize the requirement to pay the
retroactive duties as being about reason
to believe but that doesn't make it so
the applant and jockey also characterize
the validity of retroactive payments as
centering on reason to believe in that
case the CIT
disagreed the CIT has to be given the
opportunity in the scheme to make that
determination now whether reason to
believe ultimately determines the
validity of the Das is not an aspect
that the court has to determine on this
motion I just make these arguments uh to
undermine the plain of assertion that
everything ought to be dealt with in one
single
proceeding um my friend will continue
our submissions uh subject to any
questions those are our submissions on
the issues that I I'm dealing with today
just just so um
just to help me out a little bit here
based on the jurisdiction arguments that
you've just Advanced um what specific
paragraphs and sub paragraphs of the
amended state of claim uh are you
submitting should be struck on the basis
solely of those arguments I expect
there's going to be overlap but uh I'd
like to like you to identify
specifically what the jurisdiction
argument would uh would strike without
consideration of the the other
submissions that will be made right I'll
just go through the
uh so certainly paragraph 1
a
yes paragraph
1D take the clear ones first so uh in
paragraph
67 did you say paragraph 1B or 1 C uh I
I one a and One
D
DAV uh and then in 67 the parallel
portions
um so 67 uh 1 c i and double I
all right uh and then so those are the
easy ones uh then if we go to with
little
overlap
uh section V so paragraphs
46 to uh 60
all rely on parody
honey and so we submit that given the
Supreme Court's rejection of that
approach all of those should be struck
regardless of what relief they're
pertaining
to
um and so I I I think I I can maybe
double check in the break but I think
that the the remainder of the breach of
Duty of care
um there will be overlap as to what
relief it it uh it relates
to thank you if if there's anything that
you want to update on after the break
then you can certainly do that thank
you all right uh thank you for those
submissions um so with that uh before we
turn
uh to to the next set of submissions
from Mr Mayor uh we'll we'll take a
short break here 11:20 we'll come back
at 1135 15
minutes thank you Jus the court is in
recess until 11:35 thank
you the court is now
resumed all right Mr Mayor yeah good
morning uh justice gleon so of I will
address the second part of our motion
which relates uh more to the the private
law part of the statement of claim so I
want to go through address with you uh
four main points the first one being
that there's no uh they can be no
reasonable of cause of action in
negligence regarding both the duties and
the rest of the the other heads of
Damages the second point that the
professional fees cannot Grant found a
claim in Damages and this claim and
disclose no reasonable cause of action
and um amounts also to an abuse of
process and should be struck third um I
will address how in the respon the the
defendant VI the unspecified $1 million
in general damages uh is not pleaded
properly and should be struck as well
and finally I will address a few words
um I will give a response to the estole
argument that was raised by uh the
plaintiff in their written
submissions so um I invite you to uh to
uh interrupt me if you have any
questions or if you didn't hear me well
or if I'm going too fast I will be glad
to uh respond to your concern um of
course just as to give you a bit more uh
information on this road mapping I think
uh depending on your questions and how
it goes I think the bulk of my
submissions will uh concentrate on the
first point which is about the the duty
of care uh the absence of a duty of care
in this
case uh so um so moving on to my first
point that there can be no cause of
action in negligence um the most
important points that I will highlight
during my
submissions uh are that there can be no
proximity relationship between importers
and
cbsa when CB when the cbsa um conducts
verification and imposes uh duties on
importers and this is based mainly on
the very nature of the custom
scheme uh another point in that uh I
will also address that uh even if a
prima a DF care would be uh would be
identified by the court strong policy
considerations would negate it in any
event and those are uh the risk of
indefinite liability but also um the
circumvention of a specific multi-level
appeal scheme that was set out by
Parliament that my colleague Mr noban
told you in details about earlier uh so
throughout my submissions uh justice gon
I hope to demonstrate that this motion
to strike uh is indeed appropriate to
strike this claim and
negligence um early on as this court has
often done so in other cases and I will
uh discuss these cases as I go through
my
submission so uh I won't I don't want to
do a fullon
um I don't want to go into too much
details on the law of negligence I think
we all know uh the basic element of it
um you know you have to identify a duty
of care a standard of care and a breach
of that standard of care uh I think that
here we submit that here the issue is
really about uh the first element
uh the recognition or the identification
of the duty of care so um unfortunately
for this court uh I at least to my
knowledge there's no there has been no
uh Court decision that will pine on a uh
the presence or not of a duty of care
between the cbsa and
importers um so I think so on a motion
to strike I think the question that you
have to ask yourself is um
is it plain and obvious that the
plaintiff's claim uh for ident
identifying a new duty of care is bound
to
fail um so as I said it's never been
recognized before in the case law so we
have to uh revert to the test that was
uh developed by the court and refined
over a number of significant years and
decades and that test involves two
question the first one being do the
facts um as pleaded disclose a
relationship of proximity in which
failure to take reasonable care might be
foreseeably might foreseeably cause a
loss or harm to the
plaintiff and so if uh so this this is
this is this first part is interested in
the proximity relationship but also the
foreseeability uh and so if uh a praachi
duty of care is is indeed identified um
the court must ask itself are there any
residual policy considerations that
would that would negate uh the
recognition of a duty of
care so uh of course we uh our arguments
are only cover the proximity uh
relationship the proximity analysis and
so um the proximity this proximity
relationship has been or inquiry has
been referred to as um you have to look
at the quality of the relationship uh
between the parties uh and whether or
not that makes it fair and reasonable to
impose a duty of care in the
circumstances of the case uh on uh a
certain
party it has been said in other words
that uh this relationship has to be
close and direct
enough um of course here we are
uh we are uh with a an importer so a
private person against a Public
Authority uh which is the cbsa in this
case um so and the courts have said many
times that in the case of uh identifying
a duty of Care on uh and impose it on a
Public Authority such as the cbsa um the
statutes and the words of the statutes
and the purpose and objectives of the
statutes are Paramount in that um
private law analysis
uh so it has been said that a duty of
care may arise from uh the statutory
scheme itself so we have to look at that
it may also arise from specific
interactions between the Public
Authority and the plaintiff um but only
if it's not clearly negated by
Statute um and this is all set out in
the cases that we cited the seminal case
of RV Imperial tobacco and uh it was was
uh very recently uh summarized and
discussed by the Ontario Court of Appeal
in
200 uh 21 in the case of Charles Fort
developments limited V the city of
Ottawa
um so here the Ronk or the plaintiff
claims that a duty of care arises from
uh six different elements they are
listed at uh paragraph 6 1 of their
amended statement of claim okay so uh
unless you you want to go into this I
don't think we need to but I think they
uh they can be grouped into two three
categories uh the um first of all that
our duty of care flows from the regime
itself and the cbs's role in uh
administering
it uh second uh a duty of care would
flow from the treatment of other
importers such as Sumit
Tomo uh and then that duty of care would
flow also from specific representations
that are alleged uh in the state in the
amended statement of claim um
implicating a cbsa official um so in my
uh submissions in the proximity analysis
I will address those three uh sources of
alleged sources of a duty of care and I
will argue that the nature the very
nature and purpose of the custom Act and
the custom regime uh runs contrary to
the recognition of the duty of care
second that the treatment of other
importer um in their is misguided and is
Irrelevant in the and cannot ground a
duty of care and third that the
representations of the as alleged in the
statement of claim of the cbsa official
um cannot ground a duty of care in this
case because uh they are insufficient
insufficiently pleaded uh as they don't
uh the plaintiff does not plead Reliance
on those representation or nor uh
causation so starting with how uh the
nature of the regime runs contrary to uh
the recognition of a proximity
relationship uh I think that for that uh
analysis we we definitely inevitably
have to start with what is the nature of
the custom regime what what is uh what
is its purpose and objective um I think
this is key to uh the the duty of care
analysis implicating A Public Authority
so um we've we've the the the main
purpose of the Customs act and my
colleague Mr nasakin has touched on it
briefly um is to regulate oversee and
control crossb border movements of
people and goods uh for the general
welfare of the nation and you can find
those statements in the the cases we
cited in our in our factum of Martino
versus Min Ministry of national revenue
and Mitchell versus minister of national
Revenue as well those are Supreme Court
cases um in a Martino case another the
Supreme Court also um said in other
words that um the purpose of this the
scheme of the the Customs schemes is one
of Taxation and economic
regulation so I think that it's clear
that from these cases and from the
purpose of the scheme that there's a
clear uh economic and public interest um
uh purpose uh that is at the core of the
regime um now the cbs's role in
administering and enforcing that regime
um is is important it it acts as a among
other things as a duties collector uh on
imported
goods um and so one of the most
important feature of this regime is uh
self-reporting and this is very
important and I want to insist on that
because I think it's key when you're
looking at the regime in the
identification of a duty of care we have
to have that in mind um so the the
self-reporting nature of the regime is
key to its
Effectiveness um because uh the cbsa
wouldn't be able to uh verify all the
Declarations that uh that are that are
submitted to it all the goods that are
imported um so that's why it is that's
one of the reason why it is based on
self-reporting which means that uh very
bluntly it is based on the honesty of
importers when they import and declare
their goods and it also uh is based on
the accuracy um of the information uh
that is contains It's contained in those
declarations
um the I won't uh bring the court to
that specific uh portion but the case of
rid V Canada uh 2020 from this court at
tab
45 at paragraph 35 and 36 set out a good
um a good um summmer of what what I just
told you justice
gon um and so of course since it is uh
based on self uh reporting so self-
compliance there's also mechanisms that
are very important in the regime to
ensure uh compliance and so the cbsa is
Char
sorry
here can you hear me Mr Mayor oh yeah
you were uh cutting in out it was that
the case for me
too I don't know if it's my connection
or yours but
um um I can confirm that is your
connection Justice
gleon okay so I'm in my Chambers so
uh well it should be better now but I
did see that it was uh getting wor first
a little bit seems to be back now Mr yes
okay Mr back did you miss anything there
are you okay with where we are it was
cutting in and out for us as well
justice gleon but I think I seized the
general gist of where Mr Maher was going
uh but certainly we I think we got the
general GI good okay Mr mer go go ahead
I think we're I think we're back in
business here again okay so if there's
any uh issue we can just migrate to uh
the telephone and I I can still use the
camera so don't hesitate to uh to raise
any concern yeah um yeah so I was just
referring the court to the case of ridu
which gives a a relevant and helpful uh
uh statements of the purpose of the
regime and the role of the cbsa in
administering that regime I don't know
if you got that jce LE I do yes got that
okay so uh so I was about I was about to
tell you about the compliance mechanism
H and enfor and to enforce the regime
that is based on self-reporting uh so
the regime as you know is comprised of
several civil uh administrative and
penal mechanisms to ensure that uh
importers and persons comply with the
Customs Act and the regime and so this
is where verifications audits uh
administrative monetary penalties uh and
notice of penalty assessment come into
play um
so we like I told you at the from the
outset uh we know that the courts have
never opined at least to my knowledge on
the existence of a duty of care between
cbsa and importers in that context um
but they have opined many times on the
relationship between uh tax Authority so
mainly the C and
taxpayers specifically holding
in these cases that there can be no
proximity
relationship um between the tax
collector the C and taxpayers facing an
audit or a verification and this is a
this has been a constant in all Canadian
jurisdiction including this court if
you're uh I just refer you to paragraph
for um 84 and 85 of our factum which uh
references um the most uh important
cases from different jurisdiction on
that issue uh between the CRA and
taxpayers um so we sub it it is our
submission that the purpose uh and
objectives of the custom Act and the
custom regime are akin to the tax regime
and that the same rationale should apply
that there can be no relationship
between the cbsa and importers um at
least not in the kind that is fleeted by
the plaintiff before you today in the
statement of claim um and to I'd like to
spend some time into one of those cases
since we're we're actually uh asking you
to uh draw a an important comparison so
if you could go um at tab 29 of our book
of authority this is the jco versus Her
Majesty the queen in right of Canada
case
at paragraph 26 sorry I I would like you
to
go yes go ahead I have it yeah so I'll
just go through a few uh a few of those
paragraphs not too many so please bear
with me but I think they're uh important
to uh to show you uh how the comparison
is indeed um very relevant uh so at
paragraph 26 yeah um by the the court
recogn it's the onario Superior Court by
the way this is a 2021 case so pretty
recent um the court recognized that a
duty of care has been uh has been has
never been recognized and the courts
have refused to uh recognize one in the
case of tax uh in the in the tax context
it says that the claims for negligence
far no better there's emple case law
rejecting the proximity required to
formulate formulate a private law duty
of care between the C and taxpayer
facing an audit uh and then at 28
there's a bit more uh meet to why uh
there can be no uh relation no proximity
the court says the cases generally
generally agree that the relationship of
an auditor to a taxpayer while carrying
out administrative duties in an audit is
not the same as the relation the
relationship between tax investigators
who are investigating criminal offenses
the cases hold that Auditors in an audit
do not owe a private law duty of care to
the
taxpayers uh at paragraph 33 so on two
page
below let me know when you're there I am
perfect so here the Ontario Superior
Court cites with approval a case of the
Alberta uh court of appeal the granon
case which is also included in our book
of authority the court says uh citing
paragraph 25 of that case in our view it
is plain and obvious so it was a motion
to strike that an action in negligence
cannot succeed it is clear that because
of the inherently adverse relationship
between Auditors who are exercising a
statutory function in taxpayers of
finding a a sufficient proximity to
ground a private law duty of of care
does not exist and then the the final
excerpt I want to take you to are at
paragraph 34 and
35 of the jco
case uh in the middle of 34 starting
with taxpayers and H HS collectors have
resort to administrative processes in
the courts to ensure that the taxmen is
kept in check imposing negligence
liability on top of that is inconsistent
with the statutory scheme moreover it is
hard if not impossible to discern
anywhere in the relevant taxation
statutes an implicit or implied private
law duty of care owing by the C to
taxpayers and then at 35 also in the
middle of the paragraph in my view
imposing a super added private law duty
of Care on the CRA just imposes more
costs on the government and gives
taxpayers more procedural tools to defer
tax unlike police officer investigating
a crime and I take it this is a
reference to the hill case of the
Supreme Court there are already thorough
and comprehensive regulatory schemes to
ensure that the C obeys the rules so um
we think that uh the same rationale
should apply with the cbsa in this case
that was acting as a a some an auditor
someone verifying the Importer and also
as a duty collectors in assessing the
duties owing and imposing um the
duties uh one another case that I want
to take you to which uh further uh would
support that
comparison is the case from this court
uh is the case of salesman V Canada at
tab uh 46 so it's volume two of our book
of
authority and so I think it's uh this
case is also highly relevant by first
because it's one uh from this court it
was rendered by uh justice Leah who was
at the federal court at the time and uh
although the the factual issues in that
case are not really similar to um the
ones that are before you there's a
paragraph um
41 that I want to take you to
[Laughter]
and I and it it it draws a bit on how um
it explains uh I think in a wellp put
manner what what why can there be no
relationship between the C and taxpayers
so uh justice Lan States unlike
financial institutions the C is not a
commercial undertaking offering its
products and services in an open
competitive market the CRA is a creature
of stat statute was man whose mandate is
to administer an income tax system that
relies on self-reporting by taxpayers
and to that end the ACT gives the CRA
broad powers in supervising the scheme
of assessing and auditing
taxpayers in such context the CRA and
taxpayers have opposing interest their
relationship is therefore not one where
the CRA should be responsible for
protecting taxpayers from losses arising
from their assessment rather it is one
it is that of debtor creditor
governed by Statute and in a sense
adverse as a result absent absent a
breach of the powers in the act the C
has no Duty towards taxpayers other than
to act in accordance with the act for
the purposes of the act
so we submit that the same rationale
should apply in this case between the C
and the
plaintiff um and because both both
regimes are strikingly similar and if
you uh if I if I may Justice Lon I just
want to take you through some uh some uh
features of the custom act regime and
show how and show to you uh hopefully
that that it's very similar in some ways
to uh the tax regime
okay um so I think both uh regime
involve the state or an agency as a
money collector the cbsa VR duties um
and the the C via taxes or uh or
else uh both regime also rely on the
same founding principle of
self-reporting
uh and on you know accuracy and honesty
of importers or
taxpayers um and so you can find uh
traces of that core principle in the
scheme itself in the Customs act uh at
section 7.1
uh it sets out the obligation for
importers such as the plaintiff to
provide accurate complete information on
the goods they
import um section 12 of the Customs act
sets out the obligation to report the
goods they
import um also section 32 of the custom
act uh sets out uh that the importers
themselves have to account for the goods
they import they have to declare their
value for Duty uh declare their tariff
classification and pay the required
duties uh section
32.2 which is of interest in this case
today uh uh states that importers must
by themselves correct their declaration
if they have reason to believe that
their uh declarations were Incorrect and
that obligation as you know ends four
years after the goods are accounted for
so this is just uh examples where that
self-reporting
principle uh can be found practically in
the
regime um and
so both regime both the tax and the
custom regimes um involves uh gives
brand BR grants broad powers on um to
conduct Audits and conduct
verification uh section
42 and section 42
.01 in the Customs Act is this is where
you can find uh this it grants the power
to the cbsa to conduct random Audits and
verification to ensure compliance with
the
ACT um and of course both both the tax
in the custom regime uh to protect
importers and individuals and companies
from uh incorrect decisions uh both
include a multi-level
uh appeal scheme that ultimately
culminate in a special administrative
tribunal and uh potentially to uh the
federal court of
appeal so uh so there so this this is
why we say they're strikingly similar
and I and we submit that the rationale
that has been developed by the courts on
the absence of a duty of care between
the CRA and taxpayers should apply um
almost uh mutatis mutandis to the cbsa
and importers uh in this and the
plaintiff in this case
um we submit that absent a claim of bad
fate or misfeasance in in um public
office the cbsa cannot be held in
negligence by simply carrying out its
duties of uh verifying some importers
imposing duties and then collect those
duties um and so they both have they
both have at their core a relationship
of uh that is one of deor creditor
importers being uh the the deor um most
often of um of uh duties to the state in
the per in the person of the
cbsa um so in with that in mind with the
purpose of the Customs Act and the
what's been said on the tax regime we
submit that it would not be fair just
and reasonable to impose a duty of care
um on Auditors and officers of the cbsa
charged with the ad the administration
of the Customs regime and the collection
of
Duties so is it your position that that
a duty of care given the statutory
regime um you you just stated that
absent bad faith or misfeasance no Duty
would attach um are those the only two
circumstances uh I think we're going to
talk a little bit here uh about the
whole issue of representations as well
um do representations attract to duty I
know you're going to argue that it's not
properly pled but does does that fall
within your bad faith or mis deance
category or is there is is it a broader
category of circumstances where a duty
might
attach
um okay I just let me know if I don't
understand your question but um yeah so
we take that in this case in the
circumstances of this case they cannot
ground the duty of care the
representations of the
cbsa um I think the case law says that
uh in um in negligence claim involving
public authorities um interactions may
involve uh the recognition of a duty of
care so our position is not would not
would not uh be contrary to that that
well accepted principle
um but I think so I I'm reticent a bit
to to answer any hypothetical uh set of
facts that might uh where
representations and undertakings might
come into play but I I think we in the
in the case of uh and I'll speak a bit
to that more generally when I get to
that point but um I think that um you
know some representations made by a
public official or by by Public
Authority uh can cannot uh cannot
um have the effect of uh of um of uh you
know neutralizing the effect of Express
legislative Authority or uh go contrary
to uh to uh legislative Provisions so
and so so I think that does answer my
question okay your bad faith misfeasance
category might be might be broader but
it's it's it's and again I'm not asking
you to define the breadth of that
whether or not this is the only category
of circumstances yeah yeah it appears
that's not the case it appears that
you're suggesting it could be broader
without taking a position with respect
to where we are here yeah and I think
maybe I can explain a bit further my
point in raising those other uh causes
of Damages I think it's to just show
that in the case of public claw
authorities often and that's what we've
seen in the case law you will need
something more than just negligence um
to uh engage uh civil liability so
that's why I raised um bad faith or
misfeasance in public office where I
think arguably we can accept the fact
that it would be uh it would if the
facts are properly pleaded depending on
what they are it would be harder for
Public Authority to uh strike a claim at
this
stage thank
you so this was my first point on the
proximity
analysis uh then I want to address the
uh alleged treatment of other importers
in this case and specifically uh this
the Sumit Tomo and how um that cannot
ground the duty of care in this case so
uh
sorry so the the plaintiff just to sum
up I think how I I how we view the claim
of the plaintiff they claim that the
cdsa allowed and I'm quoting their uh
wording allowed other importers to
import similar Goods or identical Goods
under tariff number
21 uh and that in particular Sumit Tomo
uh they also raised uh the their they
were treated differently so they
differential treatment as to the the
other importers in the
industry um they also claimed that
um basically that cbsa targeted them by
only verifying them and not the other
importers and by only imposing duties
and retroactive duties on them and that
uh engages uh a duty of care and that
engages uh the liability of the cbsa in
negligence uh and you can find those
just for your reference at paragraph uh
38 to to 44 of their amended statement
of claim this is all set out clearly
there and also paragraph 4 49 and 52 of
their amended statement of
claim now in their amended statement of
claim there's some overlap also between
the negligence claim and the breach of
public law Duty claim so um sometimes uh
it can be a bit confusing but I think it
was set out clearly in their memorandum
how they see that that that sort how
they plead that source of Duty of care
in paragraph 40 eight of their factum
for your
reference
so this source of a duty of care as
pleaded uh we submit that it's misguided
and it shows a fundamental
misunderstanding of the Customs
regime uh and I want to address two
points on that before I move on to the
ca specific case of sumito
and do do you need a moment or go go
ahead so uh first the cvsa does not
allow uh importers to import Goods on C
under a certain tariff
item uh and as I've mentioned earlier
this is because it's based on a
self-reporting
principle so the burden actually lies on
importers to honestly and accurately uh
report and declare their goods
and not the other way around it it's not
cbsa that we look at every declarations
and that say yes you can you can import
those uh so so practically it's
inaccurate to ground a duty of Care on
the understanding that the cbsa allowed
other importers to um import similar
Goods the cbsa in this case
only only can verify a a a sub a portion
of all the importers in Canada and
verify them and imposed uh the duties uh
that the cbsa um thinks are appropriate
so the cbsa cannot be held liable for
what the other importers declared over
the
years um and again to illustrate that
how the burden uh rely the burden falls
on importers I'm just quoting from the
case of ridu at tab 45 that I uh you
don't need to go that I've uh raised uh
earlier um the court there says at
paragraph 36 the obligation to provide
full accurate and complete information
imposes a heavy burden on an individual
or an importer a burden that is not
displaced by forgetfulness or good
faith so that's my first point on that
second Point um does does the existence
of the um of the uh of the ruling that
that was being relied upon here does
that
change
so no we don't think so and I have a I
have a my not I have many submissions to
make on that but um I I will I will get
to it in a in a minute or so thank you
here I just want to make two more
General point on you know the
differential treatment an importer uh
would get by being verified and not
other importer and then I will address
the specific circumstances of this case
in Sumit Tomo
specifically
pardon well
second uh the these allegations cannot
ground a duty of care because this the
Customs act does not require the cbsa to
uh the cbsa can verify uh any importers
as it sees fit within the powers and
constraints of the statute and the
regime that's for sure uh but uh the
power the discretion to uh conduct
verification is uh is uh falls on cbsa
uh shoulder and it's part of its
statutory powers and duties uh and I've
mentioned that
uh that provision but it's found mainly
at uh
section
42.1 the power to verify and audit
importers uh so the C this Customs act
does not require the cbsa to audit every
importer in a given
industry uh out of fairness or else
towards that industry or towards those
importers uh and it certainly does not
uh imposes the duty uh on the cbsa to
impos duties on every player in a given
industry and I I think it's fair to say
that it would be
impossible uh and and and it would take
an enormous amount of resources to audit
every importer in a given
industry
um one could also argue that it would be
very uh An Inconvenient and I would say
impossible for the cbsa to try to assess
what is a given what is an
industry
um and but more importantly I think it's
impossible to ask of the
cbsa and it's not required in the regime
that they try to assess the potential
impact of
Duties on one importer and let alone
assess how auditing and collecting
duties on uh one player could affect an
industry at large because this is what
the plaintiff is arguing is at the basis
of the duty of care um that the the cbsa
knew that it would have an effect on the
competitive landscape and I'm quoting
them of the industry and so on so like I
said this the I we submit that the
Customs act does not require this but
more uh importantly or more forcefully
uh it would Rend um it runs contrary to
its fundamental principle of
self-reporting that I've uh talked to
you about um already and it would in
effect render the whole regime
unmanageable this is our
submission uh and just as a reference
for your reference the case of RV
top uh on ter superior court at tab 44
of our book of
authorities uh touches very briefly but
touches on uh the reality of the
cbsa uh uh and the fact that uh
thousands and uh hundreds of thousands
of transactions and importations occur
every day and that the cbsa uh relies on
on the honesty and accuracy of importers
it cannot be uh it cannot look at all of
the what crosses the
border so and this is found at paragraph
five just for your
reference thank you
so we submit just I want to use some
analogies here we submit that the C the
CB uh the plaintiff's position in that
regard that a duty of care would flow
from the treatment of other importers in
general
um that um it's like saying a taxpayer
that was assessed and imposed tax should
not have to pay his taxes because other
people were using the same scheme or
doing the same thing and were not cut to
use an even more simple analogy I think
their position also amounts to say that
uh someone was caught speeding on the
highway uh was imposed a fin and because
and that person would say because other
people were speeding that uh the state
shouldn't impose a fine on them
um so in this case the cbsa even if we
take we take the the pleadings and the
facts as pleaded uh the cbsa was just
doing its job select one importer for a
verification conduct a
verification um determine tariff
classification uh and then determine uh
what are the duties
owing and then collect these duties uh
in line all in line with its statutory
duties so now I want to a few words on
the Sumit
too uh circumstance of this case
so uh apart from those general for
relying on those General uh sources of
Duty treatment of importers at large the
the plaintiff relies on the specific
treatment of
Sumitomo um claiming that the cvsa
allowed Sumitomo to import uh similar or
identical Goods without uh Duty and
without imposing a penalty until the
Advent ruling of uh 20 5 was
rescinded and you can find mention of
that and that they also claim that that
grounds a duty of care in this
case pardon you can find mention of uh
that fact and that those circumstances
in the amended statement of claim at
paragraph
8 40
44 49
and
52 so
sumos different
situation uh we don't deny it at all but
it's simply the effect of legislation in
this case it is not a so-called
favorable treatment by the cbsa to
Sumitomo or a granting of a to quote the
plaintiff at the granting of an
exemption window to Sumit
Tomo uh in fact
in this case Sumit Tomo was wise enough
to Avail itself of an advance ruling and
all of its benefits that are contained
and that flow from the legislation
itself in this case the Tariff
classification Advance ruling
regulations
so what I don't know if you're uh U if
you knew about the the Advent ruling and
that regulations but in a sense a
company can ask the cbsa they can
pertain to different issues but they can
pertain to tariff
classification an importer can ask the
cbsa uh before you know before uh going
through the whole appeal scheme can ask
the cbsa to give their um what they
think of the goods would be classified
under what tarfi them and then the
Importer gets the advance ruling and it
can rely on it to import
um its
goods and so that's what sum Tomo did uh
the advance ruling of 2005 confirmed
about that the goods in issue could be
imported under tariff item 21 for a
number of years and so the cbsa uh
conducted its verification uh into um
the plaintiff's importation and it
basically at the same time or after the
verification uh the cbsa also rescinded
the uh Advance ruling uh that was issued
to Sumit Tomo so so
um yeah so and
then does the regulation have it say
anything with respect to the ability of
another uh party to come forward and ask
for an advanced ruling on the same issue
once once's an advance rul has been been
granted does the regulation deal with
that in other words could every every
competitor in this in the industry that
was importing this particular item do
the regulations allow them all to
individually come forward and obtain an
advanced ruling or once a ruling is
issued is it uh is it something that
applies to all yeah reconsider the issue
yeah and I think uh it might be useful
for us to go into the regulations but an
advance ruling only applies to between
it's only binding between the minister
and the recipient of the advance ruling
okay and this flows from the
legislation um I can if you can uh take
tab six of our book of authority I'll
walk you through the main features of
the the
regime yes I have
it um yeah hold
on I'll just find mine
open up my electronic version
sorry so in this case yeah the cbsa
rescinded Sumit Tomo Advance ruling
precisely because it was now of the view
that um tariff item 21 uh was not
applicable to the the type of goods that
are in issue today so uh if you take um
Section 8 this is where
uh it says an advance ruling applies to
Goods that are the subject of the
advance ruling and are imported on or
after the effective date of the Advan
ruling so we submit that this means that
the advance ruling only applies to the
specific Goods uh imported by the
recipient of the the Advent
ruling uh and this is further evidence
in section
10 which states that an advent ruling is
uh binding or remain in effect and shall
bind a
minister H and be the person to whom the
advance ruling was given has acted in
accordance with the
ruling um and then this section uh 13
explains the uh the so-called
differential treatment of
Sumitomo if you go to section um so
section uh 12 gives the gr gives the
power to the cbsa or an officer to uh
modify or revoke an advance ruling and
so section 30 13 deals with the effect
of that and this is what happened in the
Sumitomo case subject to subsection two
uh a modification or revocation of an
advaned rule applies to Goods that are
the subject of the Advent ruling and are
imported on or after the effective date
of the modification or
revocation so that's
why because of the legislation when the
advance ruling was changed uh or revoked
to Sumit Tomo uh the cbsa could only uh
ask from Sumit Tomo to pay the duties
from the DAT of modification and go
on and that so so my question though was
was more specific than that and that
is was do the regulations
contemplate different parties coming
forward and asking for an advanced
ruling with respect to the very same
items so in other words Sumitomo
received an advanced ruling on the
import of Wheels
yeah yeah the having having that have
and and
from the plaintiff
submissions uh the effect of that
advanced ruling or the results of that
advanced ruling are are made available
to other importers
other to access and see those Advanced
rulings and my question is is does
anything in the regulatory scheme pre
would have prevented Ronco in this
particular circumstance from seeking
Advanced ruling with respect to the very
same item yeah so I I just so I just
want to be clear uh just uh clarify some
facts that you just stated if you look
at the what's pleaded in their amended
statement of claim they they pled that
um the plaintiff pleds that uh some the
some some Advance rulings are made
available to the public so they don't
plead that this Advance ruling was made
available to the public so that's an
important uh fact that I want to make
clear and uh I think this is because it
wasn't made public in this case and uh
Ronco actually recognized that they were
aware of it through and this is at
paragraph nine of their amended
statement of claim they were aware of it
because they relied in importing the
goods under tariff 21 they relied on the
advice of their custom
Brokers without securing one for
themselves there's nothing in the the
regime that would have prevented Ronco
from securing an advance ruling actually
um the CB the cbsa also has a memorandum
on on Advance ruling and and it ain't
it importers are encouraged to seek
Advanced rulings when they want to
benefit from the certainty that it
brings and also from the you know the
benefit that you can you can impose
retroactive duties when there was an
advance ruling uh you can just go impose
the new duties or the new tarf item
going forward
so so any so any importers every
importers can get an advance ruling on
any Goods even though the goods were
already the subject of an advance ruling
uh my question so thank you yeah yeah
but and so it means that had Rono
secured an advance ruling like uh like
Sumit Tomo did and had maybe had uh Ron
CO's uh broker advice told them about
the Ben benefits of an Advan ruling uh
we wouldn't even be before you today
because there wouldn't have been any
retroactive
duties
um so the advance ruling and the
treatment of of other importers and of
sumito might be relevant in the um the
section 135 action and in this Court's
uh potential determination if Ronco had
reason to believe or not but it cannot
ground a duty of care uh in this case
that's our
submission so this concludes my
submissions on the treatment of other
importers in Sumitomo now I I want to
address specifically um the
representations made by a cbsa
official
pardon so uh in certain circumstances
like I said they can't
representations interactions
undertakings of a public official can
ground or could ground a duty of care
but not in the circumstances of this
case just as a factual little reminder
uh as you know it's the interim
verification report was issued in late
April
2018 uh the alleged uh representations
happened during a meeting uh with a cbsa
official that happened on June 26
2018 and then the final verification
report which
allegedly uh goes contrary to what was
said during the June meeting this final
verification report was uh issued in
Late July 205 so there was only a month
between the representation and the the
determination the final verification
report I just want to uh make that those
facts clear as they arep final just just
so I'm clear I thought I heard you say
the final verification report was in
July 2015 sorry 2018 2018 yes
yeah so uh our F the respon the the
fant's first point on that is that the
cbsa is required to apply the Customs
tariff and Customs legislation in the
correct matter regardless of what
representations may have been made by an
official that's my our first point but
second the second point and more
importantly uh Ronco here does does not
plead that they rely on those
representation if you uh look at the
pleadings even if you uh give it a
generous interpretation that's not what
they're saying and this this is easily
understandable because uh a little under
one month happened between the the the
meeting and the final verification
report um Ronco does not also plead
causation so they don't plead that uh
the representations and Reliance on them
cause them damages this is nowhere to be
found in the amended statement of claim
and this is why we submit that this uh
cannot ground a duty of teror and so
that uh the claim in negligence should
be struck on that basis
also
um so a proper pleaded Tor pleads all
the elements of the material facts in
support of the
elements um he so and when you plead
negligence uh through representation and
and uh you have and undertakings made by
a Public Authority you have to plead
Reliance and you have to plead causation
that Reliance on that caus you a loss or
an injury and I refer the court uh to uh
the case of Charles fer Charles fer of
the Ontario uh court of appeal which
which is found at tab 17 of our book of
authorities at uh simply just paragraph
31 and 40 uh I don't think we need to go
into them but it they clearly shows that
uh you you have to plead Reliance and
you have to plead causation when you uh
you assert damages flowing from
representations of a Public
Authority uh this was also uh this is
also confirmed in Imperial tobacco as
well at paragraph
42 so and when reading the amended
statement of claim it is clear that the
plaintiff is is not claiming that they
suffered damages because they relied on
the cbsa officials representations but
rather more simply that uh they were
they suffered damages because they were
subjected to a verification and they
were imposed the duties at issue uh uh
and the other players in the industry
were not this is the Crux of their
claiming negligence and the represent
the interactions with uh um with the
cbsa official uh are should are
inconsequential uh on the pleadings as
they are before you so and I just to
illustrate that I will refer you to
paragraph 16 and 17 of their amended
statement of claim where
what I just said is made pretty
clear um paragraph 63 to sorry 53 to
54 and also in paragraph uh 64 C 64
C so again like I said with Sumit Tomo
the representations made by do by Doug
Ben the cbsa official May well be
relevant in the section 135 action which
is focused on was there a contravention
to the act so was there reason to
believe or not that there Declaration
was incorrect uh so it might be relevant
for that inquiry but it cannot ground in
the circumstances today a duty of care
so this concludes my submissions on the
proximity analysis I want to go now
address the court to uh the second part
of the new duty of car Tesla which is
about overriding policy considerations
if that's fine with you justice vent yes
go ahead okay um so even if you would
recognize that a prima fi uh duty of
care exists or that uh you're not uh you
don't have the tools to to uh to reject
that duty of Care on this motion to
strike
um well just a point on that I in my
submission on that portion I will
address some cases where a new duty of
care was actually rejected on a motion
to strike so it has been done so it's
coming bear with me um but yeah um even
if a prima FY duty of care would be
recognized or even if you just want to
uh look at the second part of the test
strong overriding policy considerations
negate a duty of care in this
case um now so the the analysis is
different right than with the first part
of the stage uh the court will have to
look at the effect of recognizing a duty
of Care on other legal obligations on uh
the legal system or the legal regime at
play and on society in general that's
how it's been uh describe this part the
second part of the test is is the court
really in position to do that on a
motion to
strike uh yes impact uh sounds like uh
like there there might be requirements
for some evidence to ban some of these
arguments on the policy
side B we will We I will go through some
of the cases uh later on but we we our
position is that no you you can't uh
appropriately uh look at that second
stage on a motion to strike okay and I
will uh I will talk about the reasons
why uh you don't necessarily need
evidence to conclude as
such um
so the first our our one of our
submissions on that is that finding a
duty of care based on the elements uh
that are listed by Ronco at paragraph 61
of their amended statement of claim um
seriously risk opening the door to
indeterminate
liability um so and I've and I've
touched upon it this is based on um how
a duty of care based on the cbsa
verification and imposition of Duties on
one importer and not necessarily on
other importers in an industry
uh and the failure of the cbsa to assess
the financial impact of those uh
statutory duties on an importer and an
industry uh would it is our submission
that it would make render the regime
unmanageable uh I've set out it's not
required by the regime but we think that
it it would render it unmanageable and
it would open the door to indeterminate
liability and I know some sometimes
people will say well you can't just
throw that um policy in the air but this
is what this is this is what it's FedEd
in the amended statement of claim they
claimed that the cbsa targeted them
because they verified only them then
because they didn't impose or verify uh
duties on other uh on other importers
and that uh caused to uh to you know to
that interfered with uh the competitive
landscape of the Railway uh or Railway
Wheels
industry um so they claim the plaintiff
claims that uh with uh you know coupled
with the dog bin interactions and the
facts of this case uh the circumstances
are uncommon and that it wouldn't open
the door to indeterminate liability uh
we strongly disagree of course the
circumstances of this case are unique as
they will they would always be for any
cases but what the the sources of the
duty of care and what Rono or the
plaintiff claims is not unique the cbsa
uh conducts random verification on a
daily basis this is part of their
mandate and they are not required to uh
look at the effects on of their uh of
the exercise of their statutory duties
on other importers and so we submit that
recognizing a duty of care as feed by
Ronco in this case would actually open
the door for any importers that are uh
that are uh verified and imposed duties
and then if they are dissatisfied
because of the duties because other
importers uh were not verified or were
not treated the same way by uh the cbsa
in their view then it would open uh the
possibility to bring a negligence claim
and we we submit that this is a serious
consideration that you have to take into
consideration and um we submit that you
don't have you don't need uh to have
evidence to look at that issue uh
seriously
um another policy consideration is that
letting this claim in negligence go at
at for all the damage but at least for
the the duties this got as
damages uh would uh in effect circumvent
the proper appeal mechanism that Mr nosb
and told you earlier about um so I think
this is another policy consideration
that you have to keep in mind and this
is uh again a this is more of a legal
argument and it's not based on any
evidence uh that uh going letting this
claim of negligence go ahead would
actually frustrate parliament's
intention
um to uh that entrusted this the cbsa
and then to the CIT to deal with the
validity of
AAS
um so this court has struck out claims
very early on in the same context of a
motion to strike based on uh these
similar overriding
considerations and um the first one
we've we cited them in our written
materials the first one being the alasen
V Canada
case of this court U at tab eight of our
book of authority the relevant
paragraphs and I don't think we need to
go into them but for your reference are
uh 53 to
55 um in that case the court concluded
that um so so in that case an applicant
brought an action um in uh raising
different grounds of uh
action uh including negligence uh he was
a failed uh someone who got a a refu um
who got a refusal of an henc uh decision
in the immigration context and sorry I'm
using uh I'm using acronyms but hnc
meaning humanitarian and compassionate
ground
decision by an officer of immigration
Canada and in that in that case um the
again similarly like in this case the
applicant was dissatisfied with the way
the decision was made um and the court
concluded that um an agency decision
cannot be the source of uh a claim in
negligence because it would uh because
it would basically open the risk of
indeterminate liability or indeterminate
possibility for applicants to bring a
claim in negligence when they uh when
they fail in this specific immigration
um
system um and it also held that that
would circumvent the the the uh appeal
mechanism that was a that was uh
specifically designed by Parliament and
that culminate in a judicial review in
this case so uh that's for the Almon
case and again that this was on a motion
to strike on in the second case I want
to talk to you about is the swarat case
v
Canada at tab 51 of our book of
authorities again I don't think we need
to go into it but at paragraph 31 to 32
are the relevant excerpts that I want to
draw the Court's
attention um so this was a case actually
involving a bit a bit more similar to
the case that you have before you
because it involved uh you commercial
related damages uh in that case it
involved Health Canada and the whole
licensing regime of Health product by
Health
Canada um and in that case um I think
the facts are that Health Canada first
granted a license for the health product
to be marketed in Canada and then it
revoked its licensing based on various
reasons um but um and that in that case
B on a motion to strike um without
evidence the court concluded that um you
know if we would let a claim in
negligence go ahead because uh Health
Canada was just exercising its statuto
duties and revoking the license uh it
would open the door to indeterminate
liability uh and it would be impossible
for it would be impossible for uh Health
Canada to assess the economic
impact uh it's revoking or granting a
license would have on uh you know on the
Distributors of of Health Products in
Canada and and it found that it would
actually just simply run contrary to the
duties that are vested in in health
Canada so it is our submission like a
similar uh reasoning should uh can
appropriately uh be uh adopted by this
court in the circumstances of this case
today so we submit that on the proximity
uh sorry on the duty of care part and a
negligence claim um it is plain and
obvious that this cause of action cannot
succeed in the circumstances of this
case based on the facts as alleged in
the amended statement of claim because
there can be no relationship of
proximity between the cbsa and the
plaintiff and there are indeed strong
policy considerations that uh would that
negate a uh the recognition of a duty of
care in this case so this would conclude
my first and uh you know longer point
that I wanted to raise with you um if
that's okay with you subject to your
question I would just move on to uh the
professional fees ahead of
Damages one deal with the the fees issue
yes
okay so as you know the there amended
statement of claim the plaintiff seeks
approximatively $1 million uh in Damages
uh they label it as being for
Professional Services or Prof
professional fee we believe that those
this head of Damages should Al should be
struck because it's not linked to no
reasonable cause of action and also
because it constitutes an abuse of
process you can find those they're
listed in a bit more detail at paragraph
1 C and 6 7B of their amended statement
of claim uh according to uh the
plaintiff they are com those fees are
comprised of legal fees trade consultant
fees fees related to the shy bond that
was uh given to the cbsa and expert
related
fees um also uh according to the
plaintiff at paragraph um 49 of their
memorandum
uh those uh fees so the plaintiff claims
that it is the alleged uh contradictory
procedural positions that were took by
the cbsa or that they received from the
cbsa and the Attorney General of Canada
that caused them to uh bring multiple
proceedings and thus uh causing to
incure those professional
fees and like again this is clearly set
out in paragraph 49 of the
Factor
uh so two points on that issue we think
it should be struck of course I um first
of all we generally submit that um cost
for pursuing appeal Avenues um and for
contesting customs duties and tariff
classification um cannot be compensable
as damages because there's no duty of
care towards importers in that
guard um to protect them from inuring
those
fees um so I we think that this head of
Damages should be struck on that basis
alone and I would just like to uh bring
you again to the case of jco V Canada at
at tab 29 of our book of
authority if you can go to
paragraph 15 to yeah
yes uh so the the facts are a bit more
are set out in more details in the the
paragraphs uh above this but basically
uh jco uh was assessed uh and sought to
appeal with the CRA the assessments of
HST then it s sought to appeal those uh
before the tax Court of Canada and this
is where um and they were in they were
actually uh they were actually granted
what they wanted so they were successful
in their challenge of the tax assessment
in this case so at paragraph 15 the tax
Court upheld jao's position in February
2018 by the time jaob was able to
terminate its letter of credit it had
incured interest charges of uh over 1
million US Dollars and Consulting fees
of uh
$242,000 so jco pleads that uh the
government ought to identify it for
needlessly making it it incure these
costs and so that claim uh was refused
and if you go to paragraph two and three
of the same
decision so there there's a more
informative uh outline of the decision
paragraph two the plaintiff sued the
government for Indemnity and for
negligence and forcing it to incure over
$1 million in interest expense and
professional fees to defend an audit and
an agency assessment that were
undertaken and conducted in bad faith
the plaintiff succeeded in having the
tax assessment set aside in tax court
but the interest expense and
professional fees that it incured to do
so were not recoverable as costs in that
proceedings and then paragraph three the
government argues that it has no duty to
indentify the plaintiff for cost dat
incured in an ancient HST audit and it
has no private law duty of care to
protect plained from incurring costs in
a tax audit under applicable statutory
scheme and then I agree in paragraph
four so this is our main submission on
this that generally they cannot claim
those costs that were a consequences of
them pursuing different appeal avenues
that they did uh both with the cbsa and
then at the CIT and then further before
this court on judicial review or uh on a
section 135 action now my second point
that I want to raise on the professional
fees is that uh they amount we say that
they amount to an abuse of process
because um all those those costs that
that are according to the plaintiff
associated with the pursuing of these uh
proceedings um cannot be recovered as
damages because it is our position that
they should be dealt with more
appropriately as what they are cost in
those
proceedings uh We believe We submit that
the court should use the doctrine of
um of um abuse of process pardon to
strike uh this claim for professional
fee uh mainly because uh by claiming
those the plaintiff is actually trying
to do directly what the law and
Parliament uh didn't want them to in
they're trying to do indirectly what the
law and Parliament didn't want them to
do uh
directly uh and I will Pro I
will provide you with more details on
that position so I would just like to
take every proceedings that were pursued
one by one there there's maybe four and
so if you take the first Appeal on to
the C to um the first appeal was about
you know the five sample transaction so
that was pursued through the cvsa levels
and then it culminated in a CIT appeal
uh so those were on the Tariff
classification issue so on CIT
appeal uh the a plaintiff or an applant
more accurately before the CIT is not um
is not permitted to seek its cost um
actually
uh the the CIT is simply not empowered
to award those cost and this was a
specifically uh this was a specific
Choice made by Parliament and you can uh
easily infer that from um the CIT act
which is found at tab one uh in other
matters uh that can be that are under
the cit's jurisdiction cost can be um
sought for and can be awarded uh an
example of that is uh the procurement uh
complaint proceedings for which CIT has
jurisdiction um and I just refer you for
your reference to section
30.1 and
30.6 of the CIT act in which Parliament
clearly gave the power to the C to uh
award costs in those proceedings by
contrast in appeal proceedings before
the CIT whatever uh the subject of that
appeal is costs are not
recoverable parliament's choice is that
uh each party bear its own cost um and
so we submit that the plaintiff cannot
recover any cost associated with that
Appeal on in indirectly on this action
um it would be improper and an abusive
process of the
cits and this court process as
well um and just in passing on that not
on that note sorry any
uh on that appeal um the the plaintiff
chose to pursue an argument that the um
the goods were actually should be uh
classified under a third tariff item
which was not uh this the in the
verification uh and so any uh any cost
related to that that appeal uh is based
on their own uh choice to pursue uh that
line of argument which was found by the
CIT to be uh
unfounded um so and then um you know
they following the alleged inconsistent
uh information that they received from
the
cbsa uh the plaintiff actually uh
comments three other proceedings um but
first there was the the the appeal of
the notice of penalty and this section
135 appeal then there was a uh judicial
review application before this court in
2020 in August 2020 and then an appeal
to uh of the July 2020 death to the CIT
um also in 2020 I think in October
2020 um so regarding that second appeal
to the CIT the same submissions that
I've just told told you about uh apply
uh in the same matter they a party
cannot claim as damages what uh it was
directly uh precluded to do so before
the
CIT also we submit that the cost of the
Jr should more appropriately dealt with
within that Jr if it ever goes ahead and
also the cost of this current section
135 appeal should also be dealt with
more appropriately as damages
um sorry as cost in that
proceedings now another point that I
wanted to raise which further supports
how this claim of Damages is
inappropriate and an abusive process as
as as I've said already the plaintiff
makes the link between those damages and
the bad advice it received first from an
officer in
2018 and then and then much later on in
August
2020 and then in from another cbsa
official and then in October 2020 advice
that they would have received or
information from Council for the
defendant uh so uh we submit that the
position any positions Advanced by the
defendant Council in the context of
these L this
litigation uh cannot cannot constitute a
breach of Duty of care and cannot give
rise to uh damages in professional
fees uh and this is be and I refer you
to the case of B BMA V mcferson of this
court which is found at Tab 10
nine
um the paragraph uh of interest is
26d where uh the court clearly states
that uh what councils did say or did not
say or the position Council took in the
context of litigation cannot ground a
duty of care because by Nature Council
for the other side owes no duty of care
to the other to the to the other side uh
and in that sense their interest are
plainly adverse so it cannot give rise
to any claim in negligence or any
damages um flowing from
that
um yeah they also the plaintive also
raises in the head in that the
professional fee head of Damages the shy
Bond we just know and passing the sh T
Bond it cannot be an issue of
Damages uh the whole purpose of a shy
bond is to
secure payment so if C the CBS if the
plaintiff was uh successful in
challenging the validity of the July
2020 D then uh the cbsa would have to
remit the sh T Bond and any Mone is
associated with it so it cannot be an
issue of
Damages which brings me to my four my
third main point which uh can be very
short uh regarding uh how the general
claim for the claim for General damages
is pleaded uh we submit that this claim
as pleaded is bound to fail as well
because uh it's not properly
pleaded um
we submit that uh the pl the even
reading the the pleadings generously
trying to understand it the defendant is
left with uh a lot of questions
regarding that 1 million doll in general
damages
um that those damages are all are only
referenced in two paragraphs of the
statement of
claim and those are one B and
a so we don't know what those General
damages are for namely we don't know
what's that what's the injury what's the
loss here this is an important element
that someone has to clean and uh they
also have to uh provide enough material
elements in support um enough material
fact in support of that
element um
now the plaintiffs argues that they
don't have to provide a breakdown of
what ENT what this $1 million damages is
uh they don't have that they don't have
to particularize those damages we don't
necessarily disagree actually uh but I
think this is a misund they conflates
the compensable amount that are that
constitute this $1 million with the loss
or the injury and that that's what the
defendant is missing here to properly
plead against uh this $1
million uh General claim in Damages we
don't know what what caused this we
don't know what it is it for is it for
loss of profit is it for so we submit
that the pleadings are deficient in that
regard and just in passing the lack of
specifics regarding that heading of
Damages uh to to us it signal that um it
should signal to the court we submit
that uh it it also
uh it also shows how um the essential
character of the plaintiff's claim is
based in public CL remedies with only a
private uh pretense to uh with only a
thin pretense to a private wrong and
this this lack of specifics uh supports
that in our submission
so I now I would just like to address
just a few minutes the court on the
estole argument if that's okay with you
justice
gon yes go ahead I'll he you second yeah
so this uh this argument was raised by
the applicant in their submissions in
their written
factum so uh they claimed that the cbsa
is precluded from taking from making the
jurisdictional arguments that we made
today before this court this court
because uh the cbsa allegedly provided
to cbsa contrad and the agc2 provided
contradictory procedural positions to
Ronco in the past namely that uh the
reason to believe issue should be
pursued through uh the the penalty
appeal scheme and then uh the
reassessment policy should be uh
appealed to um through a judicial review
before the federal court so uh B we we
we disagree with the characterization of
the thisinformation that was given by
that that is alleged by uh the plaintiff
but I don't think that uh this court
needs to look into that evidence at all
to dispose of this uh argument of a
stole in this case uh we our submission
is that it's just it just simply doesn't
apply in this case
based solely on on legal
considerations um so for and or or on
how the facts are pleaded in the
pleadings uh so for as you know for the
doctrine of promis reople to apply uh
there are four conditions to uh that you
have to meet we submit that the
plaintiff in this case uh does not meet
the first condition which is that uh an
Authority has to have made a promise or
an undertakings or an assurance
Assurance by words or by conduct that
they will do something and not something
else uh so the purpose of the doctrine
is to um prevent an Public Authority
from deviating from its original uh
undertaking um in the public law context
it has been said that this Doctrine must
yield yield pardon um when uh there's an
overriding public interest
uh at play or when uh it would frustrate
uh the express application of a
legislative
provision um and it Al it has also been
said that the promise or the
undertakings must be lawful or
consistent with a statutory power or
discretion so it it it has it it has to
be not unlawful or inconsistent with
that statutory power said otherwise and
I just refer you to the cases that were
cited by the applicant in that regard
imar vbec at paragraph 20 to 21 tap 10
of their book of
authorities um the this court also in
the case of Samsung has said that the
doctrine is very narrow in the public
law
context this is found that tab uh oops I
forgot I didn't have but it's found in
the plaintiff's book of
authorities so yes again we submit that
there was no promise made uh if you take
the facts as feeded there was no
undertakings made uh and no exercise of
uh
discretion uh I we believe that the what
was provided to the applicant was just
uh recourse information from cbsa
official on what they thought to be uh
accurate at the time or what they
understood from the plaintiff's uh
request
um and so that Doctrine and what was
said by the cbsa official cannot um
cannot even if it was made in error uh
cannot Grant cannot Grant this court
jurisdiction um and cannot uh determine
what is the proper appeal root to what
the plaintiff is is seeking um so we we
say that to conclude otherwise would be
to let the doctrine of promis re estole
dictate uh go against parliament's
intent and dictate this Court's
jurisdictions and the cit's jurisdiction
so um there was no so there was no
promise made or nor undertaking just
information provided and then even if
there was a promise Tak can or made um
it simply cannot uh Define the legal
issues of jurisdiction in this case
um and I would note in passing that um
Ronco may have relied on this
information provided that this provided
by the cbsa to bring a a section 135
action but they did not lose any rights
they still filed a Jr in time they still
filed a CIT appeal in time so their
rights are preserved um and generally
there's no uh consequences on on that
front and there's no we submit there's
no access to justice issue in this case
so those are subm my submissions on the
promisory stop all issue um I would be
ready to conclude subject to any
question from the court
I have no questions on on the stoppable
issue Mr Mayor thank you very much thank
you so just to sum it up I know uh We've
passed over an hour and uh we still have
the other side's argument to go through
but we we submit that the amended
statement of claim is deficient in many
respects and that large portion of it
should be struck without leave to amend
um first of all because it seeks to have
the July 2020 death and it's associated
duties cancelled under the guise of an
award of
Damages uh we submit that this claim is
a collateral attack actually on the cbsa
July 2020 decision with only a thin
pretense to a private
wrong uh and we submit that the amended
statement of claim is precisely what the
Supreme Court of Canada uh warned the
court uh from which is Artful fading
that makes look a claim uh
to to find its sources in private law
where uh it is it Finds Its sources more
appropriately in public law
um the the proper Forum um is to
challenge the D in the validity of the D
is the CIT as the as it was decided in
the jocky case and very recently in the
Sketcher
case um also the claim uh of public law
duties breach of public law duties as
discussed in par honey should also be
struck without uh without uh because it
was just simply rep repudiated by the
Supreme Court and this is pretty clear
from uh the case law we
submitted um the the claim in neg for
negligence should also be struck for the
reasons that I've set out mainly because
there can be no uh relationship of
proximity it would run contrary to the
purpose and of the act in the the
provisions of the act it would also run
Contra it would also
um
uh
it yeah the the the cbsa was acting as a
duty as a auditor and a duty collector
in this case um and so
um even at the second stage there are
two strong policy considerations that
would still negate a duty of care I've
told you what they are and determinate
liability and cir the circumvention of
the regime of the appeal scheme to the
CIT um and the other heads of Damages
are also improper for the reasons that
I've set out I won't repeat them again
so we ask that this court strikes the
portions that are listed in uh paragraph
101 I of uh of our
factum um and in any event uh whatever
the outcome of this motion is we ask uh
for this court to provide um the
defendant with uh 30 days at least to uh
to file an amended statement of defense
and of course uh as we stated we would
ask for our cost in this proceeding
minus uh the um the thrown away cost uh
that the court will
determine just do you not take the
position and correct me if I'm wrong
that the amended statement of claim
actually doesn't Advance a position
on the non-compliance issue pursuant
to section 135 of the Customs Act is is
that not a submission that you
make
um
well than if we if you go into the
amended statement of claim uh there's no
explicit uh the the plaintiff does not
explicitly ask this court to to find
that it did not contravene the act of
course there's portions of the there's
some allegations that actually speak to
uh the reason to believe issue and if uh
so the whole Contra everything so some
of the allegations relate to the
contravention of section
32.2 but um they the plaintiff doesn't
ask anywhere to overturn that uh that uh
the minister decision which should be
the focus of a section 135 action so
maybe I did not respond to your question
but uh please tell me if you no you
you've responded to my question but but
that links back to your position that uh
regardless of what happens here if any
of this is struck your position is it it
be struck without without any leave to
amend does that extend to to this issue
of the of what your position is is the
appropriate matter before of the court
on uh on Section
135 in compliance could B yeah they they
could amend on that so yeah I think so
so you're not opposed to an amendment on
those
grounds uh no we would have to see what
it would be but uh no because and also
because uh yeah it was not an issue
brought to us either
so yeah
all right thank you very much Mr Mayor
thank you very much for your
attentiveness Mr Baxter maybe before we
break for lunch uh are you prepared to
just give me a a brief overview of how
you intend to proceed certainly uh your
honor and and I I was going to rise in
any event because we do have some
concerns on timing uh and um but Mr
trevisano and I have have divided the
argument I intend briefly and and I'll
do this when we come back I will be
addressing the cause of action in
negligence and the Public
maladministration Public Law cause of
action which such as it's been described
I will also uh uh reply or respond to my
friend Mr Myer's arguments about
proximity and duty of care and um we'll
deal briefly with the parody honey um
seeli if if I can call it that that Mr
nosb backin referred to in the city of
Nelson needless to say city of Nelson
and Mary we take a very different view
of what that case says as I'm sure
Justice Stratus would as well if he were
here um Mr triviso will then deal with a
number of other um of the points that
have been raised our initial estimate
had been that we would be about an hour
each uh hopefully uh and and in practice
that was what it was uh working out to
be it may be a little longer than that
and I I my friends have had about three
and a half hours uh and I just I'm I'm
bit concerned so uh I wanted to bring
that to the Court's attention as
well all right um so with that then if
we break until two o'clock is that going
to give everybody enough time to grab a
bite to eat and uh and something to
drink and have a bit of a health break
I'm seeing everybody nodding all right I
and I know your comments with respect to
time Mr bter certainly uh certainly
appreciate uh your position in that
regard
and uh I can assure you we we'll let you
have the time you need to make your
submissions uh if you need if you need
equivalent time you'll certainly get it
thank you it's always just in in the
case of such a complex series of
arguments when we roll around to 4 4:30
and I don't have to tell you this
Justice gleon 4430 it gets hard a to
speak sensibly B it must be hard to
receive sensibly uh so uh so two o'clock
would be excellent thank you we'll break
it to and if you have concerns in that
regard we can certainly look at uh
scheduling some time to uh to finish up
arguments if that becomes necessary if
that concern exists I'm not that
concerned myself at this stage but uh
but there might be Merit to what you say
uh when 4:30 does arrive we'll Endeavor
to get get get you there sir thank you
great all right then with that then
we'll break till uh till two o'clock and
then we'll come back and uh we will hear
from the uh from the
plaintiffs the court is in recess until
two o'clock
the court has now
resumed all right I guess we're ready to
go Mr back are you going are you going
to proceed first yes thank you justice
gleon I'll proceed first followed by Mr
triviso and perhaps uh perhaps just as
uh before we really get going if I could
ask you to have ready to hand the motion
record of the plaintiff so Ron's motion
record have it yes Ron's book of
authorities yes a cop of the pleading
wherever you have it I know it's in
multiple places yes and uh I may um in
in response to Mr um Maher's arguments I
may make reference to in particular the
jco case which is tab 29 of of my
friend's um book of authorities but uh I
may also have to address some of the
others depending on the Court's
questions if you have any and I have all
of that material here it might take me a
little longer to to get into some of it
but uh but it's all here yeah you're
you're better than me if you're doing it
with multiple screens because I find I'm
I I guess I own too many stocks in paper
companies or something but uh I'm using
a mix I've got the I've got the records
in in paper version because I find it
easier but the books of authority are
all electronic so there's a little bit
of bouncing around for sure but well and
I I'll then give you uh unlike my
friends I'm going to concentrate on
three uh cases and I'll tell you which
tabs they are right away if you want to
open them I'll I'll be starting in
Imperial tobacco which is tab 12 I will
then uh proceed to parody honey which is
tab 11 and then I'll go to tesone which
I believe is tab
six uh yes I may make brief reference to
others but I'll I'll direct you there um
when we come great all right thank you
and thank you again for uh for taking a
shorter lunch U uh break let me then uh
just sketch out the division of labor
between myself and Mr trivis Arnell I'm
going to review the particular
allegations of negligence against the
defendant including importantly
pleadings in respect of
proximity the duty of care and the
material facts that are alleged in the
statement of claim to support those
negligence claims I will then sketch the
separate distinct but you know adjacent
claim of public Mal Administration and
relate the pleadings in in respect of
that back to the material facts that are
alleged and indeed in in your
interactions with Mr M nosb and and
Maher it's clear you're you're quite uh
you're quite alert to the pleading so I
I don't think I need to I I won't
belabor them I'll briefly describe the
damages being sought in this action for
in this action in negligence or public
maladministration I will relate I'm
going to address my friend Mr nsb's
Claim about Downstream damages indeed
General damages are are pleaded and
they're properly pleaded lost business
is properly pleaded and I will take you
there uh finally I will deal uh with my
friends uh submissions with respect to
the new Supreme Court of Canada case in
Mary and
Nelson uh and the parody honey obiter in
that case uh in in my respectful view uh
there there's a very different um
reading of that case a much fairer
reading which means that the case before
you today the case at bar must go
through to a trial should go through to
a trial Mr triviso is then going to deal
uh first of all with the issue of
jurisdiction jurisdiction is no longer
an issue he will say because Ronco has
agreed as you've seen uh to eliminate
the prayer for Relief at paragraph 1A
that puts this case on all fours with
the tazone facts uh tazone was a similar
case where the underlying decision uh
was not challenged but the damages were
sought uh Mr triviso will then deal with
the estoppel arguments that um that are
raised he will deal with uh the general
damages pleading and the professional
fees
pleading and with the argument with
respect to an unnecessary multiplicity
of proceedings which importantly would
deprive Ronco of any meaningful redress
for all of these defendants actions and
I'm sure my friend Mr triso will talk to
you also about tazone because that case
in our view is is very material to this
Court's
consideration uh finally the the
centrality of Reason to Believe In in
this whole case uh Mr triviso will will
touch
on so with that overview uh sir and if
there are no questions I think I would
just
start and please go go ahead since this
is a motion to strike and you did invite
my friends comments on the test I will
say there's there's fundamental
agreement and this court is very
familiar with the test for motions to
strike all of the allegations in a
pleading are taken to be true and my
friend didn't mention but I will stress
novelty of a cause of action is not a
reason to strike a claim uh justice
Stratus in the majority decision in
parody honey is very clear on that there
are countless other cases that talk
about the novelty of a cause of action
and part of if you read the subtext of
my friend's plural arguments is uh well
this is novel it's Mr Maher said there's
never been a case where a duty where the
whether a duty of care is owed by cbsa
uh has um has has been found or has been
even considered this if it's novel that
is not a ground to strike in our in our
respectful
submissions but since it is a motion to
strike I'll use my my first observation
what is plain and obvious by now Justice
gleon is that the Attorney General does
not want this claim by Ronco to see the
light of
day that is plain and obvious if nothing
else is it seeks to immunize the conduct
of cbsa in that in its unilateral and
unfair imposition upon Ronco from any
realistic scrutiny by this
court and importantly very importantly
let there be no mistake it also seeks to
limit the materials that any of the
three adjudicators that the defendant
proposed should adjudicate would have
before it it seeks to ensure there will
be no meaningful rights of Discovery
whether oral or written even though
we're here under an action we're here
under an action in the federal court it
it wants to limit uh the rights of
Discovery and it doesn't want uh to
allow the court whoever is deciding any
of the three adjudicators that my friend
is proposing the the federal court on Jr
the federal court on a trial or the
CIT to get to the bottom of the real
issue here and why is Discovery
important Justice gleon well some of the
pleadings make that clear on its face um
my
um why was Ronco submitted to this um
treatment when sumomo had the advanced
ruling certificate in its hand for 13
years what did cbsa say about this
treatment why did Doug band say what he
said when he was asked about it and
about reason to
believe why did the cbsa change its
practice after Ronco made a
fuss all of these things are relevant to
what is before this court and should not
with our in our respectful submission be
stricken on a motion to
strike and you will see uh from the
pleadings and will show you in the in
some of the materials that the
directions that Ronco gave as pardon me
that Ronco received that cbsa gave uh
this is how you vindicate your rights no
actually it's over here you vindicate
your rights it reads like a game of
snakes and ladders I don't know if you
ever played Snakes and Ladders with your
children as or with your family it is
beyond doubt Justice gleon that at the
same time as starting this section 135
action Ronco could have commenced a
separate action in negligence and in
public law
maladministration and we wouldn't be
having this dispute about what you can
and can't do under a section
135 U action now Mr nosb and says well
we weren't opposed to the Amendments
because we thought ronow was going to
pursue the section 135 action uh and and
conclude it why one might ask would
anyone in their right mind pursue an
action the net result of which is to get
$1,000 of penalties
refunded it it's somewhat hard to
believe to hear the Attorney General say
that that's really what they believed
ronow was going to be
doing Ronco was told to go by way of
section 135 and my friend Mr triviso
will take you to those various
directions the only reason in other
words this is Brad under a section
135 um label if you want to call it that
way is it was told to do so but in all
of these uh three adjudicative scenarios
that my friend urge upon urge upon the
court reason to believe is Central
notwithstanding so obviously we take
issue with what Mr NSB and said in this
rearic but the intention of directing
Ron go to three different places is to
frustrate it in its attempts to get any
meaningful redress from from these
actions which in in the course of 13
years singled out one importer in an
industry of eight or nine importers and
it
alone and this is also in the context as
you as you're well aware where it gave
an Express written Assurance to its main
to one of its main competitors sumat
Tomo that tariff 21 importer
importations were appropriate that that
was the just and appropriate one to
use you might be asking yourself at this
stage well he says reason to believe is
important too how can reason to believe
and the assertion that Ronco had a
reason to believe and that's why it
needs to pay four years in back duties
coexist with an Express written
Assurance to a competitor of the exact
opposite and it's also Justice gleon
against the backdrop this whole this
whole motion to strike where um the
defendant through the privy Council and
the Minister of Finance has actually
decided to amend tariff 21 to make it
clear had it not been clear before that
Ron's importation of the steel wheels as
a duty-free item was in fact proper and
appropriate and so the first thing I'd
ask you to turn up if I could is tab
I of the motion record of
Ronco and if you're if you have it in
paper so it's tab I and it's record page
I'll start at record page 108 just for
completion I have it yes yes so that's
the uh the privy Council seal there and
you have the the date of April 23rd I
was I was scratching my head as to why
this wasn't U anyway it's not in the
pleadings but it is before you today if
you turn over now to record page 110
Justice
gleon and the amendment paragraph two
the list of tariff Provisions set out in
the schedule to the ACT is amended as
set out in part one of the schedule to
this order next page record page
111 uh paragraph 1B the description of
goods of tariff item I'll call it tariff
21 that's the language we use in the
pleading is amended by adding forg for
use in the manufacturer production of
Wheel sets as a separate provision after
the provision referred to in paragraph
a well that's precisely what these
wheels as you've seen in the pleadings
are and always have been used for and
that's what that's precisely what
sumomo uh had an Express clearance to do
under tariff 21 for more than a decade
for 13 and a half
years as pleaded and the pleadings are
presumed true no other industry
participants were similarly penalized
and I'm going to deal with Mr Maher's
straw man argument if I may characterize
it so that we're requiring uh cbsa to uh
to verify every importation of every
adjud of every importer I'll come back
to that later but in this very limited
industry of eight participants
sumomo had express provision to do so
and knowingly as it is pleaded um uh was
importing under tariff 21 whereas Ronco
was sub was subjected to this to this
conduct that's pleaded in the in the
statement of claim the Attorney General
now here today says it doesn't matter
you cannot pursue damages whether in
negligence or public law or any other
form and uh you you can't get meaningful
redress for this cont cond and I thought
it was significant for you to understand
where we are today the only the only
importer the only player in this whole
um in this whole picture that has been
subjected to this is
Ronco let me just stop you there quickly
Mr Baxter and one make sure I understand
the significance of of uh of tab I to
your record is is is this amendment now
bring these Wheel sets Within the scope
of the the Tariff 21 item is that is
that what the significance of this is
well our our position was it was
properly done so before indeed cbsa has
had told sumomo that was proper the
entire industry you'll see reference to
the DA statistics Canada data the entire
industry was doing so but for greater
Clarity the governor and Council has
said in case it wasn't clear
before it's now clear and that's what
that sub paragraph B that I that I read
to you was does that does that help is
that answering your question I think so
I think I think it does that's that's
fine and my second question is is really
the question I posed to to your friends
which is the advanced ruling that sumomo
was relying on was Ronco not in a
position to obtain a similar ruling
itself and is that relevant here again I
asked a question uh no no we don't
believe it's relevant to the negligence
claim and the public law claim at all
believe they were in a position to do so
I believe the the evidence at trial if
there is to be a trial justice gleon
inshah as we would say uh would uh would
uh will show that the entire industry
for more than a decade was using tariff
21 with
no absolutely no question that's that is
as is pleaded uh is what FedEx told but
was it open to them yes it was open so
my friend perhaps Mr Maher's argument
should best be and I was going to come
to that in response but should best be
understood as a contributory negligence
argument well if we were negligent in
treating you as we did you were
contributorily negligent for not getting
an arc that's a fair defense at trial
but it's not a defense here to knock it
out of the box to have it be dead in the
water in our respectful view does that
does that help that does thank
you so you've seen the Tariff Amendment
so let's talk about the claim in
negligence that is really the core
Central claim as I say it is it stands
alongside the public law claim but let's
if I could get you to talk about the
essential nature of this claim and to do
so we'll look at the Imperial tobacco
case which is a tab 12 as I told you and
this is of course the leading case of uh
from the Supreme Court of Canada on on
um Public Law negligence claims it's
unanimous Court by the Chief Justice
mlin and I'd also ask you to have open
uh this is where paper helps me it may
it may be harder for you if you got
several screens have opened the specific
pleading at
paragraphs uh 61 to
66 because my friend did take you to
some of these but I think they bear some
more uh some more study if I
could give me a moment
here okay I have all of that material
okay so where I will start then is at
paragraph 39 of the decision of Justice
mcglaughlin in Imperial tobacco so this
is this is sort of the uh the Bible on
claims and negligence against public
authorities paragraph 39 is just setting
out the basic negligence test oh Mr
Maher
oh is he
having you're you're muted if you're
trying to talk to the court
is there an issue on uh on the defendant
side no so we okay we were just looking
for the the papers I thought understood
okay all right okay
sorry sorry I thought my friend had a
comment yeah go ahead Mr if you're with
me uh Justice gleon at paragraph 39
that's where Justice mlin on behalf of
the unanimous Court sets up the
discussion that's about to come and of
course my friends have talked about uh
proximity and a duty of care uh the
two-stage analysis is there and
essentially what my friends uh what my
friends focused on was the first
stage so let's look first with this with
this in mind at the specific pleading of
negligence that's before you today sir
and you have it
paragraph 61 of the statement of
claim cbsa owes a duty of care to Ronco
arising
from a role in administering and
enforcing the Customs act it's a role in
administering and enforcing its own
internal policies including the policies
noted I'm going to skip over C because
my friend uh there was another there was
another straw man if I may say about C
for a second uh D cbsa conduct and allow
other importers to import identical or
substantially similar Goods under tariff
21 e and e will be important cbsa
knowledge that Ronco and the industry as
a whole believe that tariff 21 was
correct and appropriate classification
for these imported
goods and F cbsa is knowledge that
treating Ronco differently from the rest
of the industry would cause significant
harm we say these are the prox these are
the factors of proximity which give rise
to the duty of
care and in paragraph
63 and I won't read them all because I'm
sure you've read them a number of times
we say what the content of that duty of
care
is and when I come back to whether
there's a policy reason to negate the
content of that we may look at these in
Greater
detail so the dis
the discussion by Justice mcglaughlin of
these factors really starts at paragraph
41 and uh but where I think I will uh
and I commend this entire section of uh
Imperial tobacco to your reading and
rereading as I'm sure you've done
already a hundred times but let's go to
paragraph 43 together if we could
because this is where she sketches out
the two types of
negligence um claims
and I'll I'll read from the the third
line two situations may be distinguished
the first is a situation where the
alleged duty of care is said to arise
explicitly or by implication from the
statutory scheme the second is a
situation where the duty of care is
alleged to arise from interactions
between the claimant and the government
and is not negated by the
statute
so uh the next paragraph she talks about
the statutory scheme and of course as I
just showed you Ronco has pleaded that
Ronco has pleaded the statutory scheme
duty of care in 61a and
61b and in our submissions that is
properly
pleaded but paragraph 45 talks about the
second class in category and these are
very important on this motion the second
situation is where the proximity
essential to the private duty of care is
alleged to arise from a series of
specific interactions between the
government and the
claimant the argument in those cases is
that the government has through its
conduct entered into a special
relationship with the plaintiff
sufficient to establish the necessary
proximity for a duty of care in these
cases the governing statutes are still
relevant to the
analysis for instance if a finding of
proximity would conflict with the
state's general public duty no Duty may
arise the court May hold that no
proximity arises well we have and Ronco
has pleaded precisely these types of
interactions and that's why I want to go
back to the pleading now and let's look
at paragraph 61 d e and
f 61d cbsa conduct in allowing other
importers to import identical or
substanti substantially similar Goods
under tariff
21 61e cbsa is knowledge that Ronco and
the industry as a whole believed that
tariff 21 was the correct and
appropriate classification
F cbsa knowledge that treating Ronco
differently would harm it well these are
not just bald pleadings see my friend
did take you to these and In fairness to
him he was under a bit of time pressure
but I want to take you to the the
particulars of these pleadings and to do
so we'll go back to paragraph eight if I
could we'll start back at paragraph
eight paragraph eight is the sumomo
advanced ruling certificate
paragraph nine pleads the uh customs
broker advice but paragraphs 10 through
12 are the specific interactions that
are pleaded and these are taken to be
true your honor Ronco and sumomo and the
Canadian Railway and Customs Brokerage
industry as a whole understood and
reasonably believe that these wheels
were to be imported duty-free under this
tariff item cbsa own con conduct since
2005 confirmed and reinforced this
reasonable
belief this is in the context again
where it has issued an Express thumbs up
to sumomo in this
regard uh paragraph 11 talks about
similarly situated
importers without any importing under
tariff 21 without any Duty penalty or
enforcement
action and paragraph 12 cbsa knew or
ought to have known know that Ronco and
the industry as a whole believed the
Tariff 21 was a correct and appropriate
classification these are that is classic
if you want to put it that way
negligence language but let's turn again
to paragraph 42 because this is also a a
pleading that is true it happens to be
true but it's also presumed to be true
on this
motion industry Behavior also shows that
tariff 21 is not Prima fascia evident
and transparent as from the second part
of this as from 2005 to
2019 it was the cbsa own conduct that
drove importer Behavior rather than the
Tariff items wording which remained
unchanged this is going to come back of
course to the second class of negligence
pleading that Justice mcglaughlin talks
about but lest this court be concerned
that
I'm just
talking in the air about the validity of
the pleading in paragraph
42 my friend Mr nosb and took you to the
CIT notice of appeal and you don't need
to turn it up because it's a very short
but I will I will tell you where it is
it's a tab I as it happen same tab of
the of the defendant the Attorney
General's uh motion record and if you
have it if you have it in paper that's
great we'll go to record page 136
I have it go ahead um and it's just it's
the final four three lines there the
2005 Advanced ruling issue to Ron
foreign based competitor and statistics
Canada data regarding import Behavior
under tariff items 21 and 29 in that
time
period this data exists it was before
the president of the
cbsa it was be I believe it was even
before Mrs Ogie I'm not sure
so there is evidence in the world that
the cbsa knew first of all that it ought
to have known but that it knew that it's
that its own conduct influenced uh
importation of of these steel wheels
under tariff
21 I do this sir simply to situate this
pleading in the Juris Prudence of the
Supreme Court of
Canada so we are
back with me now we've talked talked
about this second class or category of
negligence pleading that Justice
McLaughlin has um has uh talked
about if you and I'll give you a time to
take a
note I'm now going back to paragraph 46
justice gleon of her decision finally it
is possible to Envision a claim where
proximity is based both on interactions
between the parties and a government
statutory duties well this is just such
a claim the one before you sir is just
such a claim and then let's look what
she says at paragraph
47 since this is a motion to strike the
questions before us is simply whether
assuming the facts pleaded to be true
there is any reasonable Prospect of
successfully establishing proximity on
the basis of a statute or otherwise on
the one hand where the sole basis
asserted for proximity is the statute
conflicting public duties May rule at
any possibility of proximity being
established on the other hand where the
asserted basis for proximity is grounded
in specific conduct and interactions
ruling a claim out at the proximity
stage may be difficult and then these
final five or six lines are crucial so
long as there is a reasonable prospect
that the asserted interactions could if
True Result in a finding a sufficient
proximity and the statute does not
exclude that possibility the matter must
be allowed to proceed to trial subject
to any policy considerations that may
negate uh the Prima fascia duty of Care
at the second
stage we submit that there is more than
a reasonable prospect that the asserted
interactions could be made out we assert
that we've there is evidence before you
today that these asserted interactions
happened I've shown you that there is
stats Canada evidence that was relied
upon it before the president will be
relied upon it at trial if if this
matter gets to a
trial the the the test that the Supreme
Court of Canada has enunciated for
whether a motion to Strike should
succeed is more than met by Ronco on
what's before you
today um so uh I've shown you the we can
actually take you to the advanced ruling
certificate but Mr Maher actually said
it's it's not in dispute the evidence
about the Imports it might be of a
assistance to you if you do have Ron's
motion record I'll just take you there
so you have it all it's a tab E Record
page 77 Justice
gleon page 77 did you say yeah 76 and 77
actually if you
want yes uh there at 76 on the leftand
side uh there is the evidence about
other uh
other importers into Canada it's
essentially a group of between eight and
importers okay and at top of page 77
given that so many industry participants
considered real bodies to be properly
classified under tariff item
21 this so this was sorry these are
submissions that were directed have to
remember which level this was directed
to this is probably to the the
ministerial pardon me the president's uh
appeal
um and then below there you have the
reference under subparagraph five on
page 77 to the sumomo Advance ruling and
you see in footnote
29 that that was uh before the
CIT uh so what is what why is this
helpful for you this is helpful for the
court in this uh instance Justice gleon
because the Supreme Court has said if
there's if there's a reasonable prospect
that the specific interactions can be
made out the matter should go to a trial
well in our submission there's more than
a reasonable Prospect you have some of
the evidence here before you
today the matter must be allowed to
proceed to trial of course subject to
any policy considerations that would
negate the duty of care now you in in
our view astutely and correctly ask Mr
Maher don't I need don't I need evidence
on policy consideration in our view of
course you do but it's hard to it's hard
to imagine what these policy
considerations should
be the duty of care that's alleged is to
apply the ACT fairly and consistently
between
importers there's nothing in the
legislative scheme so let's just think
about that apply the ACT fairly and
consistently between
importers there's nothing in the
legislative scheme and indeed there
never would be in legislative scheme
that would that would negate that Duty
so what would the policy consideration
be that would negate that uh to protect
unequal treatment of similarly situated
importers to protect uh to protect
giving an advanced ruling over here and
treating other people differently here
it's very hard to imagine a policy
consideration that would negate it and
with all due respect in an industry of
eight with with a very finite group of
Industry
participants the the Spectre of um
unlimited liability uh is is at best
speculative and of course this is this
is absolutely open to the attorney
general at a trial of this matter so we
say on the test in Imperial
tobacco the duty of care the proximity
required for duty of care the substance
of the duty of care and the breach of
the duty of care are properly pleaded
you have evidence here today
as to why Justice McLaughlin's test is
met both on the statutory and we say on
the specific interaction branch of that
test and it must be allowed to
proceed my friend's arguments if
accepted would immunize any reasonable
scrutiny of of these types of
activities now I do want to are there
any questions on the Imperial tobacco
case because there wasn't a lot more I
had to say on that sir no I think I
think the uh I think I've got the the
submission and the position you're
advancing yeah thank you yeah so just to
sum it up I guess from paragraphs 39 to
47 of the case are the key paragraphs uh
as they relate to the negligence
pleading in this
action uh at this stage I should deal
with my friend Mr
Maher's treatment of a couple of the
cases the main case that was relied upon
by the attorney general against this
duty of care is a case uh by Justice
Fred Meyer is of the Ontario Superior
Court a very experienced judge and it's
the jco case so if you have that it's a
a tab
29 and you'll recall that the argument
here was to
analogize sorry I'm just going to move
my books around a bit
the argument here Justice Leon was to
analogize the cbsa role to the cra's
role in a tax in a tax
matter and the uh the issue before uh
justice Meyers again it was uh it was
her majesty moving to strike a claim
uh it's a favorite activity of her
majesty it seems and um uh the issue
before them was whether in an audit
circumstance uh there's a duty of care
owed and and my friend did take you to
paragraph 26 so let's start there and he
says paragraph 26 of Justice
Meyers um the claim for negligence Fair
no better there's ample case law
rejecting the proximity okay and um he
then uh skipped by notes say right to
paragraph
33 which uh was was interesting because
some of the most important um portions
of Justice Meyers ruling follow
immediately after paragraph 26 if you
look at paragraph 29 of course in
paragraph 29 he's talking about an
outlier case this is called laru versus
Canada Revenue and it's from the BC
court of appeal and I commend this
entire case and particularly this
portion of it to your to your close
study I know you had 46 or 53
authorities from my friends so there's a
lot of reading and I uh but this this
this one really merits it because he's
talking about uh Hill in 27 you see he's
talking about Hill and Hamilton
Wentworth that's the Supreme Court of
Canada case which says essentially that
for an investigation there's a duty of
care that can be owed okay but now we go
and he's talking about this outlier case
laru 29 go over with me to paragraph 30
which where Justice Meyer is is doing as
he should do considering the court of
appeal from
Ontario's um treatment of that and this
is the difference uh between an audit
and an investigation that's the fact
situation that they found themselves in
in jco but here he notes in paragraph 30
the court of appeal from
Ontario's um uh consideration of the
laru case and uh I won't read it all to
you but if we get down to paragraph 62
of the cited MC McCrate case the court
of appeal has said uh whenever McCrate
was uh I don't know the year of
McCrate um it's obviously after 2012
however secondly I can see no relevant
distinction between the above cited case
of Laro and this case so he can see no
IR relevant
distinction between the British columb I
court of appeal which found a duty of
care in an audit
circumstance and uh when the court of
appeals says that uh justice Myers
continues on to paragraph 31 and says
the case involved an investigation and
held like many others that a claim in
negligence is available when the CRA
conducts an
investigation the reference to laru then
was obiter however McCrate certainly
suggests that if an audit case comes
along Laro May well be followed in
Ontario so the court of appeal is saying
this wasn't an audit case it was an
investigation or an enforcement case and
it's clear in that case uh the law that
applies but Justice Meyers notes that
the court of appeal is saying in an
audit uh there may be a duty of care ow
well why is that significant that's
significant because he then goes on to
decide the case and this is the portion
that my friend uh took you to he decides
it not on the basis of uh the court of
appeal he he says and this is it's an
interesting um discussion of um the role
of star decisis if you go with me to
paragraph 42 and following Justice
gleon yes um he says None of the
foregoing matters if I'm Bound by the
court of appeals decision in McCrate
which is of course is saying there is a
duty of care owed in an
audit uh there's a competing principle
and that's a comp principle of star
decisis he then goes on and I won't read
it all to you paragraph 45 he notes the
interesting doctrinal Pro
problem and paragraphs 49 and 50 are the
meat of this the reason this case that
my friends rely on stands for what it
stands on is that he says it stands for
what they say it stands for is that he
says he's Bound by two co-equal Superior
Court
decisions uh he notes at 49 it may well
be that the court of appeal will follow
McCrate and laru on appeal and overturn
this decision if so that would be an
example of the common law developing as
it should were I free to choose which
decision I want to follow judicial
States craft would push me to follow
McCrate but I am not free I have to
follow that my my two brothers who in
the in the case of an audit have found
that an audit by CRA there's no duty of
care but in our respectful
submission it is not at all Beyond doubt
that the Ontario courts are saying that
there's no duty of care even owed by the
CRA now we take a different view about
cbsa um there's some language in one of
the cases the taxman is not your friend
well cbsa is not like a not a tax man
cbsa in my friend's own submission are
responsible for or you know the the free
movement of of people and goods across
across uh uh borders they are not like a
taxing
Authority uh that is adverse in
interest so with all due respect to the
Juris Prudence that my friend cites in
jco it does not say what he says it says
and it does not stand for the
proposition that there cannot be a duty
of
care the salesman case which my friend
also refer too briefly that's at tab 46
we don't need to go there that is not a
a negligence case at all that's a
Judicial pardon me a judicial
review it's uh justice Leon's decision
it was a self-represented
plaintiff he was a divorce he missed
some filings he wanted an extension of
time and he complained that CRA wasn't
acting more like a bank there were no
allegations of negligence the court did
not consider whether it was duty of care
owing and the court made some remarks
about not CRA not owing uh a duty to
taxpayers but that doesn't in the case
of cbsa and and cbsa enforcement of the
Customs act speak at all to whether a
duty of care exists in that
context I can deal with the other cases
uh that my friend uh my friend cites
very briefly the swara case for the
indeterminate liability point that case
is not a case about uh indeterminate
liability in that case the private law
Duty that was alleged comes into direct
conflict with the purpose of the
regulatory scheme and and the judge so
finds so that that doesn't stand for
what my friend say it
says I think the bigger Point here
though to
emphasize is that the case before you as
my friends have admitted is
novel and it should not be this
important issue should not be decided on
a motion to strike the elements are
properly pleaded we've taken you through
paragraph 61 62 63 64 and a motion to
strike blows it out of the water these
also all these cases made it to trial uh
let me just uh let me just be sure of
that uh H humbi the humbi case which my
friends that was after a
trial
uh trying to see if suar made it to
trial anyway the bigger case is a motion
to strike isn't the place to do this to
make um pronouncements of principle
which in our submission would go against
what the Supreme Court of Canada has
said in Imperial tobacco it's properly
pleaded the damages are proper I'm going
to come to the damages in a second about
the the downstream damages of if I can
use my friend's uh wording and it it
needs to get to a trial of course my
friends don't want a trial with all the
all the documentary and oral Discovery
they would like the three summary
proceedings um in resp in response to a
couple other arguments that Mr Maher he
says uh this the Customs act does not
require the cbsa to verify all
importations of importers well with with
the utmost respect Ronco isn't saying it
does Ronco isn't saying that that's a
that's a straw man and we we never said
that and nobody would ever say that
self-reporting is of course a uh a
feature of this act but that doesn't
make this
conduct right it doesn't make it first
of all immune from immune from scrutiny
second of all on our submission it
doesn't make it right and third of all
it doesn't negate any duty of care in
the enforcement of the Customs Act
uh with respect to the advanced ruling I
think I answered your question my friend
Mr Maher may have been uh may have been
making a contributory negligence
argument why didn't FedEx on behalf of
Ronco go and get an advanced ruling that
that's open to them at trial that's
absolutely open to them at trial but
it's not a reason to strike this
pleading and uh the third argument and
I'm coming now to the Doug band the
famous Doug band
representations Ronco does not plead
negligent
misrepresentation it doesn't plead
Reliance and causation that is that's
straw man number two the band fact the
fact of the band meeting and there's
affidavit evidence before before the
various uh lower tribunals is part of
the overall negligent course of conduct
of cbsa that is alleged it is a material
fact it's a material fact that needs to
be pleaded on the rules of pleading and
that will be the subject matter of uh
Discovery and evidence at
trial I think I've made the point on
indeterminate liability and indeed your
question about don't I need some
evidence on that point uh I think that
speaks volume so oh but but my friend
did admit yes the circumstances of this
case are unique I hope they're we
certainly hope they're unique we hope
that there are no such uh there are not
other cases like this
but in in order to find an overriding
policy uh consideration that would
negate uh that would negate this duty of
care you need evidence and in our
respectful view you don't have
it
okay let me just have just a second
[Music]
unless there's other questions on the
negligence pleading I thought I'd move
on if I could to the uh Public Law
pleading Justice
Gleason yes go ahead public law is fine
and uh so in that
regard I'm going to obviously be talking
about the parody honey case which is a
tab 11 Justice Stratus's well-known uh
decision joined by uh justice
Nadal so the claim uh in this regard
relies on many of the same underlying
fact patterns it's a
distinct uh claim from the P from the
negligence claim it sits alongside
negligence and it's pleaded at
paragraphs 46 to 60
of our statement of
claim the gist of it is that there's
significant maladministration which is
both offensive to the public law values
and the terms of the statute but also
which causes real harm which should be
compensable in
Damages paragraphs 49 to 52 if you have
them ready to
hand are the key Public
Law uh
allegations by impo 49 I'll just read by
imposing retroactive duties on Ronco
cbsa treated Ronco differently than
similarly situated competitors who are
importing identical or substantially
similar Goods under the same tariff as
Ronco including sumomo and other
companies in doing so it unfairly
favored certain importers now my friend
says well that's like one speeder saying
there were other people speeding that
would be the case except if you that
would be perhaps analogous except if
you'd given uh the guy in the Camaro uh
an a letter saying it's okay for you to
drive at 160 kilometers an hour but
we're gonna we're going to audit Ronco
speed at
130 um the pleading at paragraph 50 cbsa
did not impose retroactive duties on any
other importer for importing those goods
under tariff 21 it did not conduct trade
compliance verification of any other
importer for conducts similar to ronos
paragraph 51 and 52 I won't read them
you're you're very familiar with them so
this has been styled we call it a parody
honey claim the facts of that case are
well known my friend Mr nosb and
referred to them that was a very similar
case a motion to strike
again uh the the minister had adopted a
blanket prohibition on the importation
of B packages I'm sure we are all
familiar with it uh the if you turn with
me to par paragraph 85 of the decision
which is the page 29 of our report that
we've put in there at tab
11 let me know when you get there
sir yes I'm
there so
um uh there's four bullets uh the
guideline is tan himount to a regulation
that should have passed his regulation
that doesn't apply here so these are the
facts which you'll see later Justice
Stratus keeps referring back to as if
proven could ground a a finding it's the
next three guideline imposes an absolute
prohibition against the importation and
conflicts with the law on the books well
that's very analogous to the case here
with respect to the law and the policy
with respect to reason to believe the
guideline is unreasonable within the
meaning of dunsmir it's not supported by
scientific evidence Etc my friend
reproaches Ronco for pleading un
reasonability and says well that that
unmasks the fact this is just a public
law claim well it was it was a public to
that extent uh parody honey deals with
that and I suppose technically is
binding on on this court coming as it
does from a federal court of appeal
although it is it is oberer the final
bullet is the key one a faction of
commercial beekeepers acting for their
own financial advantage captured the
bureaucracy and induced it to make the
guideline thus the guideline was enacted
for an improper ER purpose then he gives
some cases in
support the gist of these allegations in
parody honey were the actions were
inconsistent with the act and which were
essentially favoring one faction over
the other and the majority in parity
honey as we know held the pleading
should be allowed to stand both in
negligence and on the basis of a broader
right of action to seek R redress for
public
maladministration now this is not I
talked about novelty this is not a novel
idea and if you turn with me to
paragraph 131 of the decision Justice
gleon just be before we go there
um this parody had especially this last
bullet that that you referenced does not
that not suggest some element of bad
faith or improper
conduct and and if so is
that necessary
and is it pled in in this matter not
necessary we haven't pleaded bad faith
or fraud uh it's we haven't had
Discovery Justice gleon we haven't had
Discovery at all but uh I I point out no
it's not necessary for that it's not
necessary for a public law claim to
survive a motion to strike to be
ultimately successful after a trial on
the issues it may be and that's really
for this court and the trial judge to
determine but to survive a motion to
strike you don't have to uh to
allege uh bad faith we have to be
brutally Frank we have no idea uh why
cbsa has acted as it has over the past
14 or 15 years it's it's it's like being
caught in a circle I called it Snakes
and Ladders you can also make analogies
to Dante's level of hell because Ronco
knows Ronco knows not what motivates
these these various actors and these
various
decisions but it's not necessary for the
pleading to stand if that's if that's
the question sir that that is the
question thank you so so given that um
how how pertinent or helpful is is this
final Bullet at uh at paragraph 85 of uh
parody honey it is helpful bear with me
because I'm going to take you down to
paragraph 131 all right I'm with you
you're with me okay so paragraph 131 jce
Stratus is talking about and and you're
familiar with the case so it's this is
in the context of a broader discussion
of integrating if you will remedies
against public uh public officials but
he says this idea is not so novel in the
past on multiple occasions Supreme Court
has suggested public authorities could
be liable when they act quote without
legal justification
unquote a concept that seems to Echo
Public Law principle not private law TS
and that's he gives the con case
and then uh further on he so without
legal justification is is one bullet but
then he he makes reference to the
mcgilvery case of which I'm not familiar
but to Ron Carelli and
dupc Ron Carelli and dupc of course we
all uh we all read it in law school we
know the facts very well it's a
Jehovah's Witness bar owner in Montreal
who uh Premier dup decides to yank his
license um let's let's
consider Justice Stratus's invocation of
that case in this in this motion to
strike and if I if I could let me give
you a hypothetical can you imagine there
are8 to 10 bars on Crescent Street in
Montreal and the two biggest bars one's
called ronos and one's called sumat
Tomos all operate with a license from
the
government All These Bars sell beer
imported from China because that's the
hottest product at the time and you need
an import license to sell that
beer ronos is run by Mr roncarelli
the government suddenly Yanks Mr ronc
carelli's license and worse it goes back
and imposes a penalty for four years of
past importation of Chinese
beer but an additional fact gets to be
added to uh
to um this fact pattern is that 13 years
earlier Mr sumomo was promised that they
could import this Chinese
beer without
duty all the other bars keep on
operating nobody is is um refused the
importation of Chinese beer except Mr
Ron
scarelli
so that's a fact pattern it's analogous
to the fact pattern before you sir and I
say that what the Supreme Court of
Canada did in 1959 with Justice Rand and
others said that Mr Ron Carelli was
entitled to damages based on Mr dup's
treatment we could add the fact that Mr
Ron scarelli in my hypothetical was a
Jehovah's Witness but in our submission
he doesn't need to be that that that was
a key fact in Ron Carelli it it doesn't
need that for this because you've got
the promise to Mr sumomo who operates
sum bar on Crescent Street so here today
in in 2021 doesn't Mr Ron scarelli get a
chance to pursue his case before the
courts we're not saying he's going to
win his case but we're saying you can't
knock it out of the box that's what the
rule of
law is and that's what parody honey is
giving voice to in our submission this
is the this parody honey is saying there
needs to be a when there's a wrong there
needs to be a remedy this is the rule of
law in a society where the state has
more and more influence
in our lives over importers private
citizens clients customers
Etc this is what our action Ron's action
seeks is Meaningful redress like Mr Ron
Carelli got in
1959 and that's what the facts as
pleaded here
today uh require to be determined at the
end of a trial with proper
Discovery
now my friend said this new case of
Nelson and Mary really changes things
because uh because the Supreme Court of
Canada has said parody honey no no no
well if do you have if you're able to
turn that one up sir I'm going to
suggest that that is not the proper
reading at all of that
case let me know if you when you have
it yes I have it I'll just be one
second so this is another it seems like
all the all the Public Authority
negligence cases deal with clearing snow
in BC anyway it's another it's another
one of those and um uh what what my
friend pointed you to besides being if I
may say a bit grat a bit of a gratuitous
slap that the Supreme Court didn't need
to didn't need to do is an argument that
was being made by
abbottford which with all due respect to
the city of abbottsford was a crazy
argument the the the argument that they
make if I could take it to paragraph
40 paragraph 40 of the decision yes I I
I'm they've they've been through uh
they've been through the sort of the
history of negligence actions against
public authorities and then they say
third line some even argue that private
law principles of negligence are wholly
incompatible with the role and nature of
public authorities echoing the obiter
and parody honey uh for example the city
of abbotford intervened to propose the
only public law princip that sorry that
only Public Law principle should govern
Public Authority liability instead of
examining how core policy immunity
operates within negligence law it
suggests that Court should focus on
indefensible in the administrative law
sense and exercise remedial discretion
were appropriate to Grant monetary
relief well with all due respect that
was not a very sensible argument by the
city of abbottford and the Supreme Court
told them
so
um they were arguing essentially that
parody honey should supplant all the
traditional tort analysis for public
authorities the Supreme Court of Canada
rightly says no and it Abbotsford is
going far too far it's saying abandon
the ANS and burrow of Merton Council
soul and Cooper tests and and the
Supreme Court is saying here such an
approach has no basis in this Court's
Juris Prudence it also runs counter to
proed counter the crown proceedings
legislation in Canada that's all this
case is saying this case should be read
in our respectful view as saying the
contrary governments and Public
Authority should be open to private law
causes of action on the developed
negligence test I.E on the Imperial
tobacco negligence test except in cases
of core policy
decisions core policy decisions they say
should be immunized and it gives you a
long discussion about what constitutes a
core policy decision I don't hear my
friends here saying that the decision to
um uh that the decision at bar was a
core policy
decision however so it it does seem a
bit it does seem a bit curious that they
that they saw fit to to um slap
abbottsford if I can put it that way
with reference to Justice Stratus's
decision but I leave it at that I say a
proper reading of Supreme Court of
Canada is parody honey is alive and well
and that and that what they were saying
is abbottford was going far too far but
if parody honey were to be viewed as a
dead letter as my friend seem to suggest
then what this case is saying is there
must be room in a proper tort analog
Anis for uh this kind of public
malfeasance public maladministration
negligence the fact scenario like the
case at bar if parody honey Isn't the
label under which it comes to be
scrutinized because if we live in a
society where there is rule of law it
has to be scrutinized the allegations in
the statement of claim have to be able
to be scrutinized and meaningful redress
has to be
available then it should be under the
the negligence uh the developed
negligence standard that um that has the
Supreme Court of Canada has developed
over 30
years final case
so unless there's questions on the
public law parody honey uh pleadings I
I'll move on does that make sense
Justice Leon yes no that's uh that's
fine you can move on thank you I
referred you U to the of Snakes and
Ladder is directions that Ronco received
my friend Mr travisano is going to take
you through that in Greater difficulty
Sue Ogie from
cbsa um her her advice Miss Ali Muhammad
her advice the Department of Justice
neither of those two pieces of advice
were right do what do as we say go go to
the
CIT um I want to speak a bit about what
the tazone case teaches us about this
approach in tone you have at tab six
that again is a unanimous decision of
the
Court written by Justice
bny uh I'm going to be
starting well I'll just just refresh us
all on this was a 2010 case Justice B
writing for the court um he's he's
facing again a motion to strike the
Attorney General of Canada bringing
motion to strike facing a similar
argument as you face here the Attorney
General was saying you can't bring an
action in Damages because you need to go
to JR this is a thinly veiled attempt to
get a public law remedy uh in our
submission the fact that it was the
Ontario Court in that telone case versus
the federal court trial division here is
of no is of no
matter um and I've pointed out to you
already in our amended statement of
claim we've agreed to strike paragraph
1A um
uh so uh the it is really on all fours
with the tazone
facts this is this RS is now an action
in Damages or public Mal Administration
it's an action in damages caused by the
crown
conduct in applying the Customs act in
an inconsistent and unfair manner in
singling out Ronco for punitive
treatment and in preferring ing its
competitor in a competitive
landscape with respect damages that are
recoverable by Ronco are a matter for
the trial judge to quantify after
hearing all the evidence in this issue
tazone as you'll recall was trying to
fix the problems left by Grenier the
grer decision and Justice bny I'll
direct you to paragraphs 33 to 41 of
this case that's maybe where we can
start uh
the the argument of
the Attorney General in tone was
essentially the same argument as here
you have to stay in what are called
separate silos you you got to get this
kind of relief over here you got to get
this kind of relief over here uh you
have to challenge the penalty in one
proceeding where the where where you can
possibly if you're successful get $1,000
do back you have to challenge the Das
before the CIT which has no power to
award damages you have you can't your
damages for business loss where do we
get those it's not clear where You' get
those um but the Attorney General here
today is saying you can't say the cbsa
was negligent because that's a
collateral attack on these three other
type of administrative decisions and you
can't get Discovery you can't get
damages you got to stick to your
silos well Justice bny talks about this
and he notes at paragraph 37
that the federal court of appeal is
losing its enthusiasm for this kind of
view and in tazone so paragraph 37 you
say uh the type of argument that
basically you're facing here today even
the federal court of appeal back in 2008
n and 10 was losing its enthusiasm for
this separate silos
argument and Justice Binny is saying
this is an access to Justice question
this is really we don't want to
bifurcate or trifurcate the issues into
three separate
proceedings and
um I want to then take you if I
could paragraph 76 and
78 let me know when you get there
okay I'm there paragraph 76 says where a
plaintiff's pleading alleges the
elements of a private cause of action
the provincial Superior
Court I think the provincial Superior
Court should not in general decline
jurisdiction on the basis that the claim
looks like a case that could be pursued
on judicial review if the plaintiff has
a valid cause of action for damages he
or she is normally entitled to pursue it
and then you go uh paragraph 78
and I'll just he he talks about some UK
case law in
77 uh and then paragraph 78 generally
speaking the fundamental issue will
always be whether the claimant has
pleaded a reasonable private cause of
action for damages is the last four
lines if so he or she should generally
be allowed to get on with it
well let's look at what the pleading on
Damages are and my friends obviously
focused on the damages that happened to
have the same numbers as uh the duties
but let's look at paragraphs 14 to 17 of
the pleading if we could Justice
gleon 14 to is business damages lost
there's a million dollars pleaded it
could be amended tomorrow to10 million
and and there's nothing offensive about
such an amendment and that would easily
cover the pleadings which my friends say
are offensive so the number this is
really a question about measure of
Damages and that's up for the trial
judge to decide at the end of a trial
but let's look there General damages are
pleaded paragraphs 14 and 15 talk about
the industry paragraphs 16 and 17
expressly talk about Ron's plans to
expand its operation in western Canada
by opening a wheel shop and why western
Canada was a relevant market for it why
it would have been profitable how much
it would have
invested these plans says paragraph 16
which is presumed to be true were
upended due to the imposition of a 99.5%
duty on the
wheels paragraph 17 as a result Ronco
has been unable to expand its operation
as planned and Canadian customers many
of whom do not have their own wheel
shops continue to be serviced from the
American companies these are damages
these are lost profits this is lost
business opportunity and they're pleaded
they aren't my friends wanted
particulars of the million dollars and
we said case law says we give that to
you at a later stage and my friend
acknowledged that I think Mr Maher
actually acknowledged that so um we say
it is properly pleaded and to come back
to Justice
Benny's uh uh to come back to Justice
Ben's admonition if so he or she should
generally be allowed to get on with it
well let's get on with it this has been
more than a year a year and a half in
this motion to strike
limbo and my my other friend Mr nosb and
says it's a collateral attack he says
well look you've you've expressly
enumerated the dollar values of of the
um of the uh duties and so by
eliminating paragraph 1A you're just
sort of it's just window dressing it's a
collateral attack well of course Justice
bny deals with that as well and I'll
point you to that that's paragraph 6 63
to 65 of this decision and he notes that
uh justice borens very senior judge of
the court of appeal had noted properly
in tone that that that that collateral
attack defense is available at trial
that's not a that's not a defense for a
motion to strike that doesn't knock us
out of the box if if if the trial judge
after hearing all the evidence is
persuaded that uh that this really is
just a public law claimed dressed up as
a private law WR wrong uh he or she will
so
decide if additional damages should not
be awarded to Ronco that decision should
be made by this court in light of all
the evidence with proper Discovery and
proper testing of the
witnesses let's let Ronco get on with
its case as justice bny has uh has
urged uh where there's a wrong like
there like we say there's been a
wrong there need to be a meaningful
remedy so so your submissions are are
referring specifically to your general
damages claim at paragraph 1 a or 1B
sorry yes General damages are pleaded at
a million dollars I've taken you some of
Bings about lost business lost profits
they could be more you know a lot of
these things a lot of these things could
could be more or less particularized the
problem is a a deficiency in pleading
and if there is a deficiency in pleading
it's entirely my fault Justice B that
doesn't knock the cause of action and
Ronco out of the box it we told my
friends no particulars are required at
this time they don't disagree they agree
that's the law but they say well you
know that million dollars which could be
10 million I think I just said it could
be amended tomorrow to 10 million that
million dollars that's really not
properly a negligence claim or a public
law claim I say to you it is properly
and the trial judge at the end of
trial could will could and shall
determine this and as I said at the
outset right alongside this section 135
action Ronco could have commenced a
separate proceeding in negligence and
public
maladministration and my friends would
have nothing to say about that uh
proceeding I'm sure they would say
exactly what they're saying today but in
our respectful view uh the this Court's
jurist prudence and the court of appeal
in break would say look let's get on
with it as Justice bny's told us to do
let's uh let's consolidate these matters
we'll issue two decisions if we have to
let's get on with it all right so so
given that um given that uh there's
you've taken a position that one
paragraph 1A should be
struck why is one what what purpose does
1B
serve pardon me I'm just getting to it
so that's that's the 2.5 million claim
for penalties and tariffs and duties Etc
one a goes how does One D survive we say
those are Dam those are damages damages
that are caused by this this improper
maladministration this is this is a
measure of Damages
pleading my friends say you can't do it
because it's indirectly a collateral
attack that's may be available to them
at the end of the evidence but you can
imagine a situation not unlike let's
imagine it's a roncarelli situation
where Mr roncarelli is a Jehovah's
Witness it of course that wasn't the
reason but if it were these would be
part of the damages this is an issue let
let me then ask you this
question if this if this action is
allowed to
proceed it's certainly you you currently
have a matter that's being held in OB
bance before the
CIT an appeal before the CIT if that
appeal were to go ahead and you were
successful
and had been awarded damages here under
a head of damage but you were also
successful later on before the CIT
aren't you double indemnified then for
these duties and tariffs issues there's
no damages here there's there's a
payment as a result of an administrative
decision um that administrative decision
is is going to be dealt with other
elsewhere um the 1A pleading is coming
out as a result of what I understand to
be your position that you agree with
that how does the 1 D survive if if
that's a position you have with one with
one
a may I just have a minute I don't want
to trench also on what my friend is
gonna say so if I yeah absolutely yes
thank you thank you justice gon I I
don't want to trench too much on what my
friend is going to be talking to you
about but in essence these parallel
proceedings which you were quite right
to point out the possibility of
discordant uh results one is going to be
held in OB if the CIT proceeding is held
in abeyance until this action is
finished there's there's no chance of
double recovery is that there and it's
not the attempt of Ronco to seek double
recovery we were told first of all to
come to the federal court we did that
then we were told to go to judicial
review we've done that and asked to be
held in the bance then we were told to
go to the CIT we've done that and asked
to be held in OB bance the the intent
isn't to isn't to multiply recovery the
intent is to get these matters get on
with it as Justice Benny said but I
think I think my friend Mr triviso is
also going to be talking about this in
terms of in terms of his
arguments and and so so link to that and
perhaps this is something that uh that
uh that your colleague is going to to
address but but tone is tazone not
distinguished on the basis that there is
not a
legisla process that that's engaged in
tone here it's here your friend's
argument is that with respect to the to
the
assessment
decision there's a there's a process
prescribed in the act that requires you
to go through the through the president
to the CIT and ultimately to the court
of appeal and my understanding is that
you don't necessarily disagree with that
and that's why we're seeing paragraph 1A
come out of the pleading uh or you're
proposing to take it out and perhaps I'm
putting words in your mouse so if I am
please let me
know so is a legisla process um given
what the Supreme Court has said in
tazone I don't read anything in there
and perhaps you can point me to
somewhere where this issue is addressed
I see nothing in there that suggests
this whole notion of letting a party get
on with it allows the court to ignore
parliament's Direction with respect to
how appeals or or reviews or be
undertaken with respect to
administrative
decisions you're correct sir the the the
facts are are not analogous in that
regard there is not a there is not a
customs act kind of um Customs act kind
of um legislative scheme such as there
is in this case what we are saying
though is tazone is about access to
justice tazone is about doing away with
the separate silos
and and when my friend talks about the
estole argument and talks about uh
General damages more generally I think
it'll be clear why this is the most
efficient way this is what um Justice
Stratus talks about in the break
decision like there's all kinds of ways
that this can be heard but it needs to
be heard on a proper record with proper
Witnesses
Etc and again uh I'll I'll wait to hear
from your friend but but but but that's
certainly one of the challenges as I
look this at this matter is is
Parliament has described and prescribed
a mechanism
1 a seems to be part of that
mechanism um and I don't see how 1 D
doesn't fall within the scope of that as
well if you accept 1A how do you how do
you not take the position that 1D should
be struck from the amended statement of
claim and um and the notion of getting
on with it and and removing silos again
uh not something that's inconsistent
with with what I read in the jurist
Prudence but I haven't seen any jurist
Prudence that allows you to take that
approach to to to allow a court to
ignore the fact that Parliament has
prescribed the process if Parliament
decides there shall be multiple silad
processes certainly I'm I don't see
anything telone that allows the court to
ignore that if the court may not agree
with it the court may not like it the
parties may not like like it but if if
that's what this if that's the scheme
that's been enacted by Parliament I'm
not sure how those types of arguments
give the court the authority to override
the jurisdiction that's been been given
to these bodies by by Parliament and uh
so so again if you can help me out with
that or make it clear I've misunderstood
where things are going here then then
that would be helpful either you or uh
or Mr TR trono on his uh on his
submissions well we we take your point
and and and we we frankly in in trying
to obviate the need for this hearing we
wanted to get to my friends something
quickly if if if the court is of the
view that that paragraph 1D is equally
offensive we would there are ways to do
that without blowing this out of the
water um but I I take your point about
the the the legisla scheme and and I
think I will just defer the rest of
these comments to to my friend
submissions and that's fine thank you
thank you if I could just conclude
though and I will say tone is also about
access to Justice and it's not every
client it's not every litigant that that
has the resolve of Ronco you know Ronco
has has this this it is rare to hold the
Attorney General to account in the in
the manner in which Ronco has done so
and frankly I'm I'm proud that somebody
is trying to do so because most
litigants don't have the means and don't
have the you know the wherewithal to do
that and and that leads sort of to my
concluding remarks this this claim
should not be struck here today would
send a terrible terrible message it
would say that this court will not
review and if necessary correct the type
of behavior that is pleaded it would be
signaling to these government actors to
the cbsa to Mr ban to all of the cbsa
officials that are named that that there
the these actions will not be
meaningfully scrutinized and held to
account now in the past of course this
court the federal court trial division
has has that's been their role it has to
stand up to the attorney general of
Canada when the Attorney General Canada
has taken positions that don't Accord
with the rule of law that don't Accord
with the government's duty to the public
or to its statutory duties or to
principles of fairness and access to
Justice this tazone again is an access
to Justice case above
all I I know you're familiar with it so
I'll mention it the National Security
context it's not analogous but that's a
perfect example where this court has has
said to the attorney general of Canada
no you you got to stop you gotta you
have to uh you have to be held
accountable for your actions that that
is what this Court's Duty is and that is
the best feature of this court and it
also goes without saying Justice gleon
that by dismissing this motion my friend
the Attorney General's motion you aren't
saying that Ronco or the cbsa is right
or wrong what you are you're saying to
cbsa get ready to explain yourselves you
may have a very good explanation or you
may not and you're saying to Ronco get
ready to put your best foot forward they
Ronco has been ready for a while to do
that um tell this court how and why cbsa
actions have harmed you and harmed you
unfairly that's what this court does and
is the only person to do it because my
friends are trying to send Ronco with
due respect to three different places
none of which can do all of that so if
there aren't any more uh questions
Justice gleon I would turn that turn it
over to Mr triviso at this
point thank you very much Mr Baxter now
I've got no questions thank you Mr TR
[Music]
I I've taken a minute unmuting myself
because Mr bter and I are in the same
room and we didn't want to create an
echo for you which is always a danger in
these
proceedings I'm going to start by
briefly dealing with some of the
arguments around General damages and
damages for professional fees uh then
I'll move on to what seems to be the hot
button issue today which is questions of
jurisdiction the statutory process and
the section 1D that uh you've pointed
out um attached to that issue I will
also walk you through the estole
argument for why we say that the
Attorney General cannot make the
jurisdiction arguments that it attempts
to make today given the clear and
unambiguous representations previously
made by the cbsa
I then want to speak to the dangers of
multiple proceedings and uh lastly I
will come back to the interpretation of
reason to believe and briefly touch on
what its significance is although uh
that should not be determinative on a
motion to strike and I think Mr nosac is
in agreement with that as
well so briefly on General damages Mr
Baxter just took you to the paragraphs
of our statement of claim in paragraphs
14 to 17 that articulate some of the
particulars of the effect on Ron's
business as a result of the conduct uh
that we allege in our statement of claim
uh importantly though for um
uh topic of a motion to strike the
defendants have not cited a single case
where a plaintiff's claim has been
struck for a failure to plead General
damages or a single case where a general
damage is claimed has been has been
struck for for a failure to plead those
damages and as such there's there's no
legal basis to strike Ronco General
damages claims here and and that's
because General damages are of a general
nature they do not need to be
particularized at the pleading stage uh
it is a matter for Discovery I know I
know Mr Mayor said earlier today that he
has a lot of questions about our general
damages claim and and those are
questions that he can Fair rais in
Discovery and I I do think that uh the
Attorney General accepts that uh we
don't have to particularize at this
stage um we've cited the uh governor and
Company of Adventures case at tab eight
of our book of authorities I won't take
you there but that was in the context of
a motion for particulars where the judge
made very clear that at the pleading
stage it is not necessary to
particularize a general damages claim
and to be very clear as as I understand
it there's there's no argument before
you today that the defendants um uh uh
or that General damages are not
available to the defendants as a matter
of law there's no suggestion that
General damages can't result from a
negligence claim or the general damages
cannot result from a parody honey style
Public Law claim uh it's just an issue
of how close mostly we have
particularized those General damages and
I think as Mr Baxter showed you earlier
we have fled General damages properly
and there's no legal basis to strike the
general damages
claim I I'll deal briefly as well with
the question of the damages that Ronco
seeks for uh certain professional fees
incurred and Ronco seeks those damages
on the basis that those professional uh
fees which were occurred throughout this
entire process of appeals um with
cbsa um our position is that those fees
result from the conduct of the cbsa that
we say is negligent and that we say
constitutes a maladministration under a
public law claim and courts have
regularly awarded professional fees
incurred as a result of a defendant's
negligence or other tortous conduct uh
We've cited a number of cases where that
uh where those kinds of Damages have
been awarded I I won't take you to them
all I'll just reference them for you but
there's the Granville savings case
Supreme Court case at tab n of our book
of authorities there's the tesy case at
tab 15 of our book of authorities and
the Beckstead case at Tab four of our
book of
authorities these are simply pecuniary
damages that that we say were caused by
the defendant's conduct but for the
defendant's conduct Ronco would not have
incurred these fees and therefore they
should be reimbursed as damages now I I
heard Mr may this morning expressed some
concerns about whether these
professional fees were actually caused
by cbsa conduct or not and again that is
a that is a fair defense for the
defendants to raise a trial questions of
cause
but it is not an issue to be decided
without any evidence at the pleading
stage on a motion to
strike um similarly there may be
questions about whether these were
Quantified properly but again that's a
defense to be raised at trial on the
evidence again like with the uh
arguments around General damages the
defendants have not cited a single case
where a claim for professional fees Was
Defeated on a motion to strike
specifically because of the nature of
the professional fees claim the the one
decision that Mr May uh mayor pointed
you to this morning was the jco case and
that jco case was decided on the basis
of Duty of care right that there was a
finding by Justice Meyers that he was
bound by star decisis of um uh uh other
Superior Courts in Ontario that he could
not recognize a duty of care and that's
why the damages claimed there could not
move forward but it wasn't because of
the nature of a damages claim for
professional
fees um so our submission is that there
is no legal basis for you to strike that
part of Ron's
claim moving on to um jurisdiction and
as as Mr Baxter said to earlier we we
don't think jurisdiction should be an
issue any longer and uh We've made very
clear that section 1A is no longer an
issue we've been through that a few
times I do want to um clarify what it is
I understand the defendants are arguing
with respect to jurisdiction and what I
don't think they are arguing
there's no argument by the defendants
that this court doesn't have
jurisdiction to hear Ron's negligence
claim there's no argument that this
court doesn't have jurisdiction to hear
a parody honey claim and there's no
argument that damages cannot normally be
sought uh uh for those kinds of claims
no no no argument that that's not within
the jurisdiction of this court and
there's no argument that the Customs act
has ousted this Court's Jurisdiction to
hear any of those sorts of claims it
really is a question that relates to
damages and as as justice gleon as you
pointed out how those damages are
Quantified and let me take you through
all of that uh there was some reference
to the fritz and Sketchers uh cases this
morning but neither of those cases speak
to the federal Court's Jurisdiction to
Grant damages in a negligence case or to
Grant to award damages in a parody honey
style
claim now the arguments that the
defendants raise around
jurisdiction and
damages um they they have not cited a
single case that stands for the
proposition that this court doesn't have
jurisdiction to award the kinds of
Damages that Ronco that Ronco seeks in
my view and I think their argument in
expressing this as a jurisdiction
argument I believe that it
misunderstands the underlying case law
and the the case that they cite too is
the same case that Mr Baxter and I have
been relying on quite a bit in this
hearing and that's the tesone case and
obviously we see the case quite
differently and I will take you to um uh
paragraph 78 of tazone Tone's at tab six
of our book of authority
but this is the paragraph they site for
the proposition that this court doesn't
have
jurisdiction and this is a paragraph
about residual discretion it says there
is always a residual discretion in the
inherent jurisdiction of the superior
court and the federal court to stay the
damages claimed because in its essential
character is a claim for judicial review
with only a thin pretense to a private
wrong so again this is about residual
discretion it's not about there being no
jurisdiction to hear a damages claim in
the federal
court um and then it the the the the
same sentence in the same breath uh Jus
as B emphasized that really the question
is whether there's a reasonable private
cause of action for damages which has
been pled and our submission is of
course that that private cause of action
has been pled just as it was in tazone
and as such we should be allowed to get
on with
it and and that's where our claim is
similar to tone in that the damages that
we're seeking the general damages the
professional fees and the amount
Quantified in the amount of the um uh of
the duties all of those flow from the
conduct of cbsa and we should be able to
pursue them and I'm I'm going to come to
your question Justice Gleason about the
statutory process I think before we do
that it would be instructive to review
two of the cases that my friend cite to
this morning that apply this paragraph
in tone and that's the Leon case and the
Stewart case Leon is at volume two tab
34 of um uh of the defendant's book of
authorities again neither of these cases
are dealing with questions of
jurisdiction over damag
claims that's that's not what these
courts are doing when they ex when they
exercise their residual discretion under
tesone so in the um the Leon case this
is a case where a federal inmate had
brought an action on the basis of a a
sech charge that was charged against
their pum
allowance uh the plaintiff um uh alleged
that this was a breach of the
corrections and conditional release act
and in paragraph 22 this is where the
court applies its residual discretion in
pelone and the court says I find that a
breach of section
76 of the corrections in conditional
release Act is not a reasonable cause of
action so this is the court saying you
you can't just claim the breach of a
statute and and make that a cause of
action that's how tesone is being
applied in this case it's not looking at
at the negligence claim it's not looking
at the damages sought it's just saying
you you can't make up a cause of action
that's just grounded in statutory breach
that is the kind of um Public Law claim
dressed up as a private law claim that
can be struck under tesone
and Leon is quite instructive because
the plaintiff actually had pled a
negligence claim in that case and the
negligence claim is not struck on the
basis of Tel
the negligence claim was struck on the
basis that the plaintiff had not
properly pled the material facts
underlying a claim and negligence this
is at paragraph
35 uh just just so you can see it but
the court found that the pleadings
around negligence were merely bald
assertions and I think Mr Baxter has
made very clear that our pleadings
around negligence are not merely bald
assertions and I don't think there is
any argument being Advanced by the
defend today that we failed to plead
material facts that ground a negligence
claim there's some discussion about
whether there's a duty of care here
today and Mr Baxter has addressed why
that's uh why why why there should be uh
or why a duty of care or why we should
be found to have properly pled a duty of
care and that's not a basis to strike a
claim but what this case is illustrative
of is this this whole question of
exercising the residual discretion in
tesone the way it's been applied in the
courts has not been to strike a damages
claim like the one that Ronco
seeks the the other um uh case that the
Attorney General cites where this tesone
residual discretion has been exercised
is the Stewart and Canada case at toab
50 of the uh uh defendants book of
authorities and that's a that's a very
strange case the the plaintiff had
alleged in that case that the crown and
the Attorney General of the United
States had conspired together to limit
the plaintiff's um presence in Canada
there were Charter breaches alleged
alleged there was a Mis fance in public
office claim there was a defamation
claim but again this case is not about
jurisdiction over damages claims the
plaintiff sought a uh quite novel
order uh at section or at paragraph 7 C
it's described in the case the plaintiff
was looking for an order to be allowed
to remain in Canada for the duration of
these
proceedings right it's this portion of
the claim that the judge used the
residual discretion from tesone to
strike and that's clear at the
paragraphs that the Attorney General
cites which are down at paragraph 59 and
60 you'll see paragraph 59 as the
reference to that language and tone that
I took you to earlier and then in
section or in paragraph 60 the court
says well in so far as the plaintiff
complains about the period of time for
which he was granted permission to stay
in Canada I agree with the arguments of
the defendants that the complainant may
be able or may be the subject of an
application for judicial review pursuant
to the provisions of the immigration and
Refugee protections act and then the
court strikes that portion of the claim
on the basis of telone
those are the cases that the attorney
general has put before you today on
exercising the residual discretion under
tesone to strike a portion of a claim
because it's merely a private law cause
of action or a public law a public law
claim that's dressed up as a private law
cause of
action none of those cases are on point
and none of those cases deal with a
damages claim like Ron
Ronco this case is much more like tazone
um as Mr Baxter explained to you before
tazone was about um uh uh uh was about
um the uh
um it was about the various silos that
the uh government said that the uh
claims should be in judicial review
should be pursued before seeking damages
in the superior court and um uh uh Mr
Baxter emphasized the importance of that
case as a case about access to Justice
and I I would just commend paragraph 18
of that decision as well which you you
may already be familiar with but this is
where Justice bnie says this is
fundamentally about access to Justice
people who claim to be injured by
government action should have whatever
redress the legal system permits through
the procedures that minimize unnecessary
cost and complexity the Court's approach
should be practical and preg Matic with
that objective in mind and that's the
approach that we're trying to take today
and that's the approach that we're
trying to take in this action um our
view is that the defendants jurisdiction
arguments are a way of over complicating
the necessary proceedings suggesting
that this court does not have
jurisdiction and on the basis of tone
taking that pragmatic and practical
approach uh the court should reject um
uh that argument and I I don't want to
create a a moment of suspense but I
wonder Justice gleon I'm about to get
into um uh the question that I think is
on your mind around a statutory process
and what can be done in the CIT I wonder
if now would be a natural point for a
short
break I think that's a a good idea we've
been going for over an hour and a half
now so so let's break um is uh 10
minutes enough just given the time of
the day everybody's noding yes okay so
we'll break for 10 minutes we'll come
back at uh at uh at 350 thank
you okay uh this uh special sitting of
the federal court is now in recess until
350 all
right the court is now
resumed all right I think we're probably
ready to go again Mr trano I can
actually see you you were you were uh I
thought it was my perhaps my camera my
screen but you were quite uh quite foggy
there earlier but the the picture seems
to have improved so I don't know what
happened on the break but but you're
you're up you're up and clear go ahead I
hope I hope you're just speaking about
my appearance not my arguments Justice
appearance only yes not the argument go
ahead please um so so let me take on
what I think is uh the essence of the
jurisdiction question here and and this
has to do with um the statutory process
under the Customs act and and that
statutory process in our submission is
quite Limited in the issues and in the
remedies um uh that can be considered by
the CIT and I think Mr NSB in made this
very clear this morning when he cited to
section 60 of the Customs Act which
limits that statutory process to
questions of
origin tariff
classification value for Duty or
marking nothing in the Customs act
grants the CIT a broader jurisdiction to
consider other factors and the factors
that are in issue in this case this is
not a case about tariff classification
value for Duty or Market the CIT cannot
consider the essence of the wrong that
Ronco alleges in this case which you
know there's a whole course of conduct
that we base our allegations on but I
think at the heart of it as Mr uh Baxter
explained in his Ron scarelli argument
um
hypothetical this is a case about cbsa
unequal treatment of Ronco as compared
to simil similarly situated importers
without any
justification and is no suggestion
before you today Justice gleon that the
CIT can reckon with that issue that that
question can go before the CIT and I I
know that Mr NOS bachin tried to point
to the fritz case for example to suggest
that the cit's jurisdiction is is
broader than questions of origin tariff
classification or value for Duty or
marking but as I've seen in the cases
the the only other thing that can come
with within uh the cit's jurisdiction as
these cases suggest is the question of
whether the original decision was valid
to begin with right and that's not
something we're challenging here this
question of validity now Fritz the fritz
case was specifically um this is this is
where the court found that there was no
jurisdiction to set aside detailed
adjustment statements which is the very
reason that we've taken Section 1 a out
of our
pleading but when the court looked at
the case in in Fritz and I think it's
instructive um uh to turn to and this is
that the fritz case is at I believe tab
20 of uh the defendants
um book of authorities and specifically
at paragraph
36 yeah I'm
there here the the court was saying this
matter can go to the
CIT because the CIT does have
jurisdiction to exclude evidence on
Charter grounds because remember that
that's that was the issue in Fritz was
whether certain evidence had been
gathered should be excluded or not and
importantly in in the second sentence no
one no one appearing that Day suggested
that the C JT lacks jur jurisdiction to
exclude evidence on Charter grounds so
of course with that being the core issue
the federal court has no problem sending
um the litigant back to the CIT to deal
with that issue because no one was
contesting whether the CIT had
jurisdiction to deal with that issue or
not but here Ron's concern is that the
CIT does not have well it certainly
doesn't have jurisdiction to adjudicate
our damages claims doesn't have
jurisdiction to adjudicate a negligence
claim doesn't have jurisdiction to
adjudicate a claim under parody honey
and it doesn't it is not able to deal
with the key issue the wrong that we say
was done here which is treating Ronco
differently than the other similarly
situated
importers and I think it's instructive
to look at the CIT decision on tariff
classification that was issued in this
very
case and that's in the um defendants
motion record at exhibit
D I'm at page 75 of the defendants
motion record and it's paragraph 63 of
the CIT
decision yes I there
and I'm at the last sentence the CIT
made very clear to
Ronco that its mandate and its
jurisdiction on this kind of appeal is
quite limited it's simply to determine
tariff classification of the goods at
issue it has no power to determine how
the Tariff classification should
ultimately impact the appellant with
respect to the duties imposed nor how
the Reliance of Ronco upon an advanced
ruling should INF inuence the cbsa
decisions on these
matters so there's a comment there about
the um limited jurisdiction in terms of
relief the CIT can't decide how um how
the Tariff classification or you know in
our case now it' be the question of
being treated differently how that
affects the duties that were imposed
citd saying we we can't decide that we
can't give you the relief you're looking
for and then the second part of the
sentence is a limit on jurisdiction uh
as far as subject matter goes saying
that the CIT can't consider how the
Reliance of ronow upon an advanced
ruling should influence the csa's
decisions on these matters these are
issues that need to be brought up in a
federal court action they're issues that
need to be brought in the context of
Ron's negligence claim and its parody
honey claim because those causes of
action are actually broad enough to um
evaluate these issues our Reliance on on
on the fact of Industry practice as
reflected in that Sumitomo decision and
the unequal treatment of Ronco as
compared to the other um similarly
situated
importance and quite quite frankly you
know we've spoken Mr Baxter has spoken
quite a bit about uh how we see this
motion as an attempt by the defendants
to stop this casee from seeing the light
of day I I think that's why they want to
be in the
CIT right it's somewhere where the full
breadth of this case cannot be
considered not only will we not get
Discovery but in fact the full merits of
the case whether there's evidence or not
is not going to be decided and I think
the two jockey candidate cases are quite
illustrative of this kind of um uh
procedural strategy uh having been taken
by um uh the attorney general in the
context of the Customs act and I turn
first to the federal court decision
which is at tab 30 of the um uh
defendant's motion
[Music]
record yes and I think I think Mr nosb
backin took us here this morning at
paragraphs 29 and 30 right um the court
the court is looking at the case and of
course the the applicants here were
making an argument that they didn't have
uh reason to believe uh at the time of
import and the court says the issue here
is that this question of reason and
belief and in section 30 following or in
paragraph 30 following the fritz
marketing case the court says I'm of the
view that this is a matter for the
president of the C cbsa and if
unresolved for appeal to the CIT now
what's interesting is this finding is
contrary to the representations that
were made to Ronco which I'll show you
in a
minute um but that's the result here
right this this issue this is what
happens the federal court says we we
can't deal with reason to believe
because it comes within the context it
comes within the scope of the statutory
process and sends it to the CIT on the
arguments of the um uh uh cbsa in this
case and then at paragraph
31 sorry not paragraph 31 this is tab 31
the CIT
decision
and the CIT decision in Jockey
Canada um and I will take you to
paragraph 260
and the CIT here granted the CIT is
talking about reason to believe in the
context of section 135 of the ACT but
then that last sentence is instructive
in these circumstances the cbsa argued
that it would be for the federal court
not the tribunal to decide when the
Importer had reason to believe that its
declarations were
incorrect so before the federal court
the federal court finds reason to
believe is outside of our
jurisdiction then the same argument is
made to the CIT reason to believe is
outside of your jurisdiction and I take
Mr NOS Bin's point from this morning and
this was this was a confusion that I
think Justice gleon you you asked about
this morning your questions and it's
something that took me quite some time
to understand about this case but reason
to believe is relevant both in the
context of the section 60 to 67
proceedings and it's also relevant in
the statutory framework for section 129
and section 135 which is where we come
before you
today and I acknowledge that distinction
and I acknowledge that that's Mr nosb
and's explanation for why uh uh cbsa got
in front of the federal court and said
no jurisdiction to decide reason to
believe and then got in front of the CIT
and said no jurisdiction to decide
reason to
believe but the effect of that in this
case right in par or in Jockey Canada as
it comes before the CIT
is that reason to believe is not dealt
with on its merits the CIT in this case
doesn't make a decision about whether
jockey Canada had reason to believe or
not and and Mr Nas backin likes that
aspect of the case because he relies on
C the CIT decision to say well reason to
believe
isn't isn't relevant to how much uh uh
to to the duties that should be paid
right and how that should be
reassessed but the point is the CIT
decision maker after receiving
submissions uh by the cbsa that reason
to believe is not within its
jurisdiction avoids making a decision on
reason to believe and I think this comes
back to the question of the multiplicity
of proceedings and something again
Justice GL that you asked about this
morning which is the uh danger of
inconsistent decisions on reason to
believe the flip side the flip side of
that danger of too many decisions about
reason to believe is not enough no
decisions made about reason to believe
just just let me jump in there and just
just make sure I
clearly understand uh your submissions
and allow you to understand at least
what I understand the situation to be
and
if a party
brings an action under Section
135 in this type of scenario the very
issue before the court would be the
reason to believe finding it's it's it's
whether there's been a contravention and
as I understand the facts here the
contravention is based solely and
strictly upon the reason to believe
finding and the failure to them file the
the voluntary adjustments or the the
self- declared
adjustments in if I'm correct in that
understanding there seems to be no doubt
that the reason to believe issue uh can
be put before an external decision
maker so so again I'm getting lost by
this notion of how somehow this this
matter can be somehow lost in the
multitude of potential proceedings
there's there's a Express clear
proceeding prescribed by Parliament that
puts this very issue in this case before
the federal
court where there may well be some
ambiguity is with respect to what the
citd does with with this reason to
believe scenario but again as I
understand the facts in this particular
case at least from your friend's
perspective it's unclear to me whether
you agree with that with with those that
position or not but reason to believe is
of no consequence V the
CIT aspect of this on the unique facts
of this case so so again so this
argument that somehow the reason to
believe issue is runs across all
proceedings and somehow gets lost just
doesn't seem to be consistent with my
understanding of of the process again
which may be multiple it may be siloed
um but it doesn't seem to allow this
issue to get
lost as I understand you to be
arguing that and that is my argument
that it will get lost because if it gets
decided solely in the context of a
section 135 action without the
negligence claim without the parody
honey claim without the ability to seek
damages as they are Quantified in our
statement of claim then reason to
believe is being decided in a silo where
the only thing on the line is a
$1,000 and I think Mr nosp backen said
this morning we could raise reason to
believe in the uh proceedings in the
CIT he just says that um uh that they
wouldn't have any effect and we disagree
with that we vehemently disagree with
that and I'll show you in a moment why
those that position taken by Mr nosb in
today is inconsistent with the position
that the cbsa has taken in the past and
I think that's significant as well but
but the point is reason to believe would
be decided in a small small Silo only
dealing with the question of the
Thousand
penalty I'm not sure if the CIT would
decide reason to believe I'm not sure if
they would make a factual finding about
reason to believe because the CIT didn't
injy Canada they specifically avoided it
because they were told that reason to
believe is properly dealt with only in a
section 135 action before the federal
court so we would be arguing if we went
back to the CIT like Mr nosb and is
asking us we' be there and that's that's
where he says that the True priz Lies if
you want to have the Das overturned
you've got to go to the CIT and he says
well you you can have reason to believe
uh uh dealt with there but the CIT is
just going to tell you it doesn't mean
anything for your
case I'm not sure that the CIT would
even I I don't know that the CIT would
address reason to believe on its
merits just in the same way that it
wasn't addressed on its merits in Jockey
Canada and and then the other point I
need to make about reason to believe is
as Central as that is to Ron's claim
it's a very important piece of the
puzzle in our negligence claim and our
parody honey claim but it is only one
piece of the
puzzle the broader context is the
allegation that Ronco was treated
differently than other situate similarly
situated importers and those those two
things feed on each other because of
course part of our lack of reason to
believe at the time of import was
because everyone else was allowed to
import the goods uh at issue under
tariff 21 so those things feed on each
other but even if even if reason to
believe uh uh can be dealt with in the
CIT there's no jurisdiction to deal with
the true question of the wrong which is
Ronco being treated differently than
others and I think the point of the
Jockey Canada case and the point of uh
the multiplicity of proceedings is also
that not only do you risk multiple
decision makers making uh uh decisions
about the same issue but you also risk a
hesitancy on the part of a decision
maker to make a decision on the issue
just like the CIT and jockey Canada uh
because there's there's an awareness
that in fact it is something that's
going to be treated in multiple
proceedings um I I I I hope that I hope
that I've made myself clear on on those
points I I would like to move on to deal
with um our argument that uh cbsa is a
stopped from making its jurisdiction
argument today and just to show you some
of the representations that Ronco relied
on in the course of this appeals
process and and just
to before you move on I just wanted to
be clear that you're going to address my
question my very specific question
around uh paragraph 1D and how that how
that claim for damages fits within the
context of the CIT process in light of
your position on paragraph 1A so um so
if you're doing that later fine but if
you're not I'd like to hear that before
you go to the the stop discussion no I I
think I I think I would deal with that
now I I had understood I had understood
that um uh that question to be in the
context of the St
process um uh taking over that kind of
relief was I I think what I heard um
heard you saying and and the point I was
I was making was that in fact that
statutory process is not wide enough to
consider the merits of Ron's claim right
and that's why we should be able to seek
damages resulting from cbsa conduct in
this federal court proceeding because
other otherwise we are not not going to
have that fundamental question the wrong
that we say was done to Ronco
adjudicated will be before the CIT where
we can't deal with that issue and I I'm
I'm not even sure that the CIT could
grant us the duties based on the
paragraph that I showed uh that I showed
you a moment ago from the CIT decision
the last time Ronco was there on tariff
classification where the CIT told us um
that they couldn't make a decision about
how the Importer was uh ultimately
affected with respect to duties so I
don't I don't know and I don't think
that that statutory process is actually
one where Ronco can get um uh those
amounts that it seeks and and and that's
why we've Quantified our damages that
way because we say that that is the
result of the conduct of
cbsa I I think that addresses my
question I I think I still struggle with
this notion that that
somehow within within the structure of
this argument there seems to be at least
an implication that somehow the
statutory process can be avoided and uh
and I I haven't really heard either you
or Mr Baxter specifically address that
to my satisfaction to say Parliament has
described this process uh your friends
argue that the amount that you're
seeking in Damages at at paragraph 1D is
ESS entially an effort
to adopt a different approach than that
prescribed by Parliament to deal with
the imposition of Duties and uh and
interest and and as I say perhaps I'm
I'm just not getting it from the
perspective the argument you're
advancing uh I hear the point you're
making with respect to the broader
aspect of the claim uh but I'm not quite
sure how that then allows you to avoid
the process with respect to the specific
issue
of Duties and the
classification of the uh the proper
tariff uh by by by using a different
label with respect to that Duty and and
and and interest order um in a damages
claim in an action to say I'm I'm I'm
not there yet in understanding exactly
how you're advancing that view and as I
say my my confusion becomes uh even
greater given your position on paragraph
1A uh if you were somehow maintaining
the view that 1A can advance Then I then
I would feel there was some consistency
I'm not quite sure I'm following the
consistency between your position on 1 a
and
1D having said that I understand
generally the argument you're advancing
I'm just not sure how it fits together
with respect to that particular
paragraph of the amended statement of
claims I confer with Mr Mr Baxter for
one second and then and then we'll we'll
continue certainly absolutely
I I I I get the sense that you do
understand our submissions on this and I
I would refer you back to our written
submissions as well to to ensure that uh
that you understand them in detail and I
I hope they will alleviate uh your
concerns and I I I guess the last the
last point I'd make and I I think I
think you you do
understand this but if if we were
advancing an
action um uh where we were claiming
these
damages and it was on the basis of uh
determinations of origin tariff
classification value for Duty or marking
which which are which are the issues in
that statutory process then then I could
understand why the statutory process
usurps the the the Juris or out the
jurisdiction of the federal court and
our submission is that because our uh
because the wrong that we claim because
our claim is not anchored in those
issues then we should be able to seek
those damages and in fact we're not we
are not circumventing the statutory
process we're taking the only Avenue
that is open to us in a way uh in a way
to recover the damages that we allege I
I'm not going to belabor the point I I
think I think it's worth moving on um
and I want to deal with the uh uh the
estole issues here um You' you've heard
a bit about uh Mr Baxter has referred to
the game of snakes and La ladders that
Ronco has been through and all of this
has been in the context of a complex um
uh appeals proceeding where Ronco has
been down many different Avenues and had
many different representations made to
it about uh the proceedings and the
appropriate venue uh to proceed in and
our submission is that those
those representations made to Ronco have
been in a state of constant
Evolution um it there's no debate that
aole applies in the public law context
and Mr Mayor referred you to the am Jac
robit Tai Supreme Court case this
morning and I think he he put it quite
well when he said a Public Authority
cannot deviate from its previous
representations that is the essence of a
stole and the specific um uh elements of
of a of public law EST stopple there has
to be a clear and unambiguous promise
made to a citizen by a Public
Authority it has to be made in order to
induce a certain
act and then the citizen must rely on
that promise and act on it by changing
their conduct I I would just note
quickly that the concept of Promise in
the promisor estole context especially
on the part of a prise
a public law Authority is quite wide um
I and I think it's akin to
representation so if you read the the
other case that we have uh uh cited I
don't think we need to go there but I'll
I'll just give you the reference and
this is the Samsung Electronics case at
tab 13 of our book of authorities there
was an access to information request
Health Canada released two
decisions um they argued that only the
second decision stood
and the court found that Health Canada
was a stop from going back on that first
decision and there the decision of
Health Canada on an access to
information request fit the criteria for
a a promise so I take that notion of
promise to be quite wide in terms of
representations and I want to take you
through the um the representations that
were made to Ronco here and the first
representation made by Miss Ogie and
this needs to be looked it in the
context of uh Mr nosac and submissions
this morning that reason to believe can
be dealt with in the
CIT because this runs directly contrary
to what Ronco was told by an appeals
officer of the cbsa at the beginning of
these proceedings and I'd take you to
Exhibit C of our motion record
and um just to start at the bottom of
the email chain which is at page 54 of
our motion
record
yes so Ronco had initiated the statutory
process under Section 60 to section 6 7
of the Customs Act made their
submissions to the cbsa and Ronco had
made submissions on tariff
classification and they' made
submissions or we've made submissions on
reason to believe and then miss Ogie the
appeals officer for the cbsa emails
Ron's representative on her own accord
responding to our uh our submission
saying I've been reviewing your appeal
letter concerning tariff classification
you also discuss reason to believe
have you appealed the penalty I will
only be dealing with tariff
classification so this is the cbsa
spontaneously telling us we're not going
to deal with reason to believe and these
representations become much clearer
higher up in the chain that's that's the
beginning of the unambiguous
representations but M Mr Clark uh who is
a representative of Ronco responds and
this is if you scroll up to page 15 53
or turn to page 5 turn back to page
53 Mr Clark clarifies Ron's position
which is uh reason to believe is
included as a part of this appeal to
address the requirement to correct these
import transactions Ronco has been very
clear with the cbsa since the beginning
of this case that we believe that reason
to believe is tied to the uh the issue
of whether Ronco should be required to
pay duties or not that relates to the
reassessment policy which we will get to
in a minute and Mr Clark asked Miss Ogie
to confirm you do not have jurisdiction
to hear an appeal of reason to
believe and Miss Clark responds turning
back to page
52 yes you are correct I do not have
jurisdiction under a section 60 appeal
to deal with reason to
believe and this runs directly contrary
to what Mr nosb was saying today the
suggestion that we could bring reason to
believe before the CIT Miss oovi does
not tell us reason to believe doesn't
matter she doesn't say reason to believe
is not a basis on which to challenge
duties that's not what we're told we're
told there is no jurisdiction within the
Customs act process under Section 60 to
deal with reason to believe and I I
think these are clear these are as clear
and unambiguous as representations from
a public La Authority can get they were
meant to induce Ronco not to pursue
reason to believe within that section 60
to section 67 process and Ronco in fact
relied on those uh uh
representations and waited to challenge
reason to believe until it brought the
section 129 appeal to the minister
and then uh the section 135 action which
is which is why this issue of reason to
believe comes to this court in this um
uh in this form because we were told
that's the only place that you can deal
with reason to
believe um it's also a very clear and
unambiguous representation about the
limitations on the jurisdiction uh under
Section 60 to 67 and I I I think I think
J as as you reckon with the question of
how wide a jurisdiction the CIT has
under the process outlined in those
Provisions I think it's important to
take these representations into
consideration as well as the
representations on the CIT decision
which I I took you to
earlier there are further
representations made to Ronco that um
are in some ways consistent with what
Miss Ogie said and in some ways
inconsistent in that they direct us
towards a judicial review procedure and
those are at exhibit F of our motion
record and this
is uh at page
82 and it's it's quite a a technical
Email exchange so rather than read
through all of it I I will just give you
the context um uh Ronco at this point
had made its um appeal under Section 29
to the minister um and there was a
discussion between Ronco and Miss Ali
Muhammad of the cbsa as to whether Ronco
would be required to pay duties before
exhausting the appeals mechanism uh Mrs
Miss Ali Muhammad was aware that Ronco
had raised reason to believe in its
appeal to the section 12 uh uh to the
minister under section
129 and and the reason that Ronco had
raised reason to believe um uh what was
not just as it relates to the Penalty it
was also as it relates to the
reassessment policy which we say is the
reason why Ronco should not have had to
have paid duties
and Miss Ali Muhammad says very clearly
there is no review mechanism provided
within the Customs act that allows for
an appeal or review of the application
of the reassessment
policy and then directs us uh directs
Ronco um uh to commence a judicial
review so initially we're told reason to
believe needs to be dealt with under
section 129 and section 135 that's the
only place but now that you're talking
about reason to believe in the context
of a reassessment policy okay now now
you actually have to go over to this
door and commence a judicial
review and that's that's the only reason
that Ronco commenced that judicial
review was was to preserve its rights
we relied on the clear and unambiguous
representations of Miss Al Muhammad and
and commen that proceeding to preserve
our
rights so that judicial review
application
actually seeks judicial review of the
Das so does it
not I I believe it does in the context
of the reassessment policy
and
well so what was what's the issue on
that judicial review
the the application of the an
interpretation of the assessment policy
or the
Das
again does my question is does the
judicial review application actually
line up with the representation that
that you just pointed me to well I I
believe that it is reviewing the dask in
light of the reassessment
[Music]
policy yeah so it it is it is viewing
the detailed adjustment
statements on Ron's theory that they
were issued on the basis that Ronco had
reason to believe that its original
tariff Declaration was incorrect at the
time and and that that relates back to
the reassessment policy right which we
we say that the in the judicial review
that the the Das should be quashed um uh
because um the reassessment policy
requires that Ronco be excused from
those d ities right on the basis that it
did not have reason to believe at the
time of
import and it it's you know it was it
was unclear in those Communications as
to what what what uh decision we should
be challenging the only decision that
comes to Ronco is the decision of the
detailed adjustment statements it's not
as though someone you know sends a
letter to Ronco that says we're not
applying the reassessment policy
right or we're not applying section 27
of the reassessment policy
here
um so it's in it's in the context of
these multiple representations about
where re re reason to believe can be
dealt with and where it cannot be dealt
with that we say that cbsa is now a
stopped from taking the position that uh
this court doesn't have jurisdiction to
hear the issue and that the issue should
be before the CIT as a part of
um a challenge to the duties
there I will quickly touch on the issue
of multiplicity of proceedings which I I
think Justice gleon you you you've
you've asked about a few times but um
we're talking about a section 135 action
in federal court to challenge The
Minister's
decision um uh the and say that we would
need to bring a separate judicial review
on the basis of the legislation if we
wanted to challenge the amount of the
notice of penalty
assessment and and then they say that we
should be bringing an appeal to the CIT
of the July 2020 detailed adjustment
statements and of
course we're not able to seek damages in
any of those proceedings so they would
have us argue these matters in three
separate proceedings without Ronco being
able to seek the relief that uh uh that
it seeks in this
claim there's no proposal from the
defendants as to how to coordinate these
multiple proceedings I which one goes
first how to proceed with them
efficiently uh and there's no proposal
as to how to ensure that there are no
conflicting decisions uh on issues like
reason to believe which we say would
need to be dealt with in the context of
I mean it would need to be dealt with in
the context of the section 135 action it
would need to be dealt with to some
extent in the context of the negligence
claim and parody honey claim and
similarly we would also be dealing with
it in the CIT in query whether the CIT
would want to hear that issue or
not but I think this goes back to the
point about access to Justice in tazone
because this kind of three-headed
procedure only makes sense for a
defendant that has practically unlimited
resources and that wants to avoid having
this case heard on its merits and I I
took you through some of the process
that we went through uh Mr Baxter's
already made the point to that most
litigants would have abandoned this case
by now given the procedural obstacles
that have been created by the defendants
and and we and we think that the reason
for that is to avoid having the issues
in this case and that fundamental
question of whether Ronco was treated
unequally and whether that constitutes
negligence from having that heard on its
merits
and that we say is a serious access to
Justice concern just like in tazone and
the government should not be allowed to
rely on the technical and ill-founded
procedural arguments that they're making
to avoid having this her on its
merits I will touch on um touch on it
very briefly which is just the the uh
interpretation of reason to believe I I
think Mr nspac said this morning that um
it's not an issue that needs to be
finally dealt with on this motion what
the significance of Reason to Believe
within the reassessment policy is and
how it should be interpreted I agree
with him that it's not an issue for this
motion to strike because um it it it's
it's not a basis to strike Ron Go's
claim even if even if the defendants are
right about um uh what the significance
of reason to believe is um our claims
and negligence and imperity honey as
I've said are are broader based on the
conduct of cbsa and not anchored solely
and reason to believe which is only one
piece of that
puzzle and we disagree with uh cbsa
interpretation of um of reason to
believe we've referred to the uh
reassess policy which we say uh makes
very clear and has mandatory language
that Ronco is to be relieved or that a a
party that did not have reason to
believe that its declarations were
incorrect at the time of import um uh uh
uh is only required to correct for the
period of
verification and for the period going
forward following the amendment and I
think that's where we have our
fundamental disagreement is about what
going forward means and how to interpret
that but that's that's not a question to
be dealt with on this motion to strike I
don't think the defendants submit that
it's a question to be dealt with on this
Mo uh um on a motion to strike so I I
I'm not going to get into it in any more
detail just to say
that the the provisions of the
reassessment policy and and and just so
you know the reassessment policy
specifically
ties the um uh correction period to
reason to believe I mean that is section
one of the reassessment policy ties
those Concepts together and then section
27 is the section that we say has that
mandatory language and this is set out
in our written submissions but just at a
high level I mean it makes good sense
that the duties imposed on an importer
that didn't know that its declarations
were incorrect correct that didn't have
reason to believe that its declarations
were incorrect it makes good sense that
that importer should not be charged the
same retroactive duties as someone who
did have reason to believe at the time
of import and that's especially true
here where Ronco received advice that
its declarations were
correct Ronco was led to believe as we
allege that it uh could import rough
boore wheels under tariff 21 um uh
because cbsa had allowed them to do so
for years and it also allowed other
industry participants to do so for years
including Sumit Tomo under that advanced
ruling and despite all this um our view
is that the defendants are now saying to
Ronco that reason to believe has no
effect on Ron Go's obligation to pay
retroactive duties uh and we say that
must be wrong based on our our uh
interpretation of the reassessment
policy that that's dealt with in further
detail in our written missions but I
think I'll I'll I'll leave it at that um
uh uh for today um I I did want to go
back to the question of Duty of care
just very briefly and that is a that is
a matter whether whether a duty of care
can be imposed on cbsa in these kinds of
circumstances is absolutely a matter
that needs to be heard on its merits
because as all the parties have made
clear to you today there are are no
cases dealing with that issue there are
no cases that say that there is no duty
of care owed by um
cbsa uh uh to an importer in general and
also in circumstances such as these now
no case has been put forward before you
for that proposition so that that
absolutely should not be struck um we've
properly pled our negligence claim we've
properly pled our mer parody honey claim
we've pled private law causes of action
and just like in telone we should be
able to get on with them those are my
submissions thank you very much uh Mr
triso
um back to the uh to the defendants a
reply uh we do have a brief reply I
wonder if we could have just five
minutes just to uh to briefly make sure
that we have everything in order
certainly yeah so um so we'll adjourn
then till uh
4:45 okay the court is in recess until
4:40 the court is
received all right looks like we've got
everybody back so uh Mr
nospam uh thank you justice gleon I'll
be very brief um most of the submissions
of my friends uh we address in our in
our main submissions I'll just go
through a number of points um first my
friend both of my friends uh mentioned
the novelty aspect and suggested that
this claim should not be struck because
of novelty and I just wanted to make it
clear
that we are not asking that it be struck
because of novelty uh that is not one of
our grounds um
it novelty was raised in the context of
uh the negligence uh duty of care
exercise which was just to say that no
previous case has dealt with with duty
of care in this scenario and all that
means means is that the full test has to
be looked at um my friend Mr Baer says
well these are arguments you can make at
trial uh all of the arguments that one
could make on a motion to strike could
also be made at trial by definition um
that doesn't mean that a motion to
strike is not appropriate uh and in the
context of the duty of care analysis my
friend Mr Baxter says that all of these
duty of care cases went to trial uh well
I would point out that the Almon case at
uh tab eight of our book did not go to
trial it was struck on the duty of care
issue on a motion to strike as was the
swarth case uh which is at tab 51 of our
book and as was what my friend I'm sure
will agree is one of the big cases
Imperial tobacco itself was about a
motion to strike which was struck on the
basis of lack of Duty of care including
on the second stage of that
test um I also want to clarify uh that
we are not suggesting that the
plaintiffs can pursue their Claim by way
of a judicial review just in case there
was any confusion in that
respect um I'd like to just brief my
friend said that uh surrounding the
notion of a uh Advanced ruling and the
sumomo situation that it
was a question of of contributory
negligence that the plaintiff did not
Avail themselves of an advanced rule
we would submit that uh it is not a
matter of negligence at all it is we
just said that it was open to the
plaintiff to seek an advanced ruling
what it is about is the application of
the
legislation which is both the Customs
Act and the regulations pertaining to
Advanced
rulings the any any um differential
treatment coming out of that is as a
result of the application of the
legislation as it's written and and as
it and as it is this is in no way
comparable to Ron Kelli versus D dup C
where the whole point of that case was
uh the bad faith and
arbitrariness of the premier of Quebec
and intervening to to to personally
remove the license from from the plti
there
um my friend referred to referred
several times that the case is on all
fours factually with tazone and we just
say that there's three ways in which it
isn't in particular one is the one that
you mentioned Justice gleon that it that
case didn't involve statutory scheme
second it did not involve damages that
that are in the nature of of of taxes
seeking reimbursement of taxes as
damages and third the the the plaintiffs
in that case did not seek to nullify the
effect of the decision that issue
plaintiffs are in this case uh they're
trying to undo what was
done um the next point I had is on uh
jurisdiction uh I just want to make it
clear that uh my my friend Mr traso said
that we are not making an argument that
the negligence claim or the parody honey
claim are outside of this Court's
Jurisdiction we certainly say they are
outside of this jurisdiction with
respect to the damages related to duties
and
interest we've already made our
submissions on parody honey as a whole
um uh but in that context of that
discussion my friend said that there
we've shown given no cases uh to say the
court cannot Grant the sorts of Damages
here regarding the duties and I would
just take the remind the court again
that we took uh us to the the flar case
which is at tab 18 of our book
and the veridico case which is at 53
both of those cases involves um money
well verich was taxes Flo was seized
funds which rather than following the
the appropriate scheme were sought as
damages and the
court struck those
claims
um just in terms of I I just have to
reiterate that in terms of uh the cit's
jurisdiction my friend's assertion again
that that the the CIT on a section 67
appeal is limited to the issues of
tariff classification value for Duty uh
and
origin that statement can only be made
if one ignores all of the federal court
of appeal federal court and cic CIT
decisions that we took you to today my
friend says the only thing outside of
that so there is something outside of
that is is challenging the validity of a
Das it says they're not trying to do
that
here we disagree they're saying that the
the D is not valid because they didn't
actually have reason to believe and
because the policies of the cbsa were
misapplied basically as my friend
described in relation to the the
judicial review application that they
have held in OB
bance uh and of course jockey dealt with
the issue with the
CIT as I noted um I won't go into again
to our disagreements with uh my friend
on the jockey cases and how they are to
be interpreted I I tried to address that
in my submissions in Chief um I I I just
urge you to read the jockey cases
particularly the CIT one carefully uh to
see that the CIT did in fact deal with
the issues that it had to and did not
shy away from
it um finally I would just say that my
friend
uh questioned whether the CIT could even
award the duties
uh if they were successful and I would
just say that if the Das is if they are
successful at the CIT that means that
the D is
overturned and that means that the cbsa
returns the duties or cancels the duties
as
owing and of course the CIT proceeding
is a
denovo hearing at which evidence can be
uh can can be adduced uh so when my
friend says that we are trying to
prevent this case from seeing light of
day that is in fact not the case at
all uh those subject questions those are
my reply
submissions no I have no no further
questions thank
you all right I think that wraps up then
the submissions for this afternoon uh I
would like to hear very briefly um on
the issue of costs as I indicated this
morning and specifically cost thrown
away I have your written submissions
I've been through them um certainly uh
the the defendants do address this whole
issue of the timing and whether or not
uh costs in the amounts and in the uh
the volume of work that's reflected in
the uh in the plan of submissions are
really thrown away given uh given where
we are from a Time perspective and uh
again I'll leave you the opportunity Mr
backer if you'd like to make any
submissions on that aspect of things
otherwise I'll deal with this in the in
the context of uh of the order that
issues in the uh in the motion itself
but uh but I just wanted to give you the
opportunity if you want to speak to the
issue and obviously give the defendants
the opportunity to respond if if there's
anything to respond to so thank you
justice gleon and I'll be extremely
brief and uh I am going to invite my
friend Mr triviso to talk to speak to
the case law which was submitted in our
three page uh in our three-page item
just three remarks first of all Ronco is
thankful to the court for rescheduling
this matter so quickly uh we heard I
think it's three weeks and a day from
the time that we were initially supposed
to be heard um just a remark that is
three weeks is still a very long time um
particularly for all of us when we have
intervening cases my second General
remark is that the as I understand the
jur Prudence costs thrown away are very
real cost paid by real clients and
that's what happened in this case not
once but twice and at the instance of a
party on its own motion uh we don't take
we don't uh it cost there's not blame uh
affiliated with cost thrown away and my
friend will speak to that uh but it
happened not once but twice and third uh
and this probably speaks more to my old
and fuzzy brain compared what uh the
others other Council but there was a
great deal of time in getting back up to
speed this past week I will tell you my
friends the Attorney General um have you
know ably relied upon 47 different
pieces of jurist prudence cases um six
or seven statutory regimes that took a
great deal of time and none of it came
back easily but I would like now to ask
Mr trevisano if he would um just speak
to the the the legal tests in the case
thank you thank
you so just just briefly um the case law
that we've cited in our cost submissions
makes clear that costs thrown away
should be treated on a lumsum basis on
the basis of the actual costs incurred
and not on the basis of the tariffs
we've cited to the Abdul razic case the
Packers plus case and the Eli Lily case
uh all all three in the federal court
and they're cited in our cost
submissions and I understand in Abdul
razik and Packers plus those are both
cases dealing with trials and I I
understand that and I understand that
the amount of preparation that goes into
a trial is very significant but I think
that the principle of treating this from
a lumpsum basis should be the same in
the context of a though maybe the amount
of preparation involved in a motion is
less and that can be reflected in how
you exercise your discretion to give us
a portion of those costs thrown away it
is the very same principle in that we
prepared we got ramped up twice for this
proceeding uh and have had to do so now
a third time uh which involves as Mr Mr
bter uh reference and it's it's it's not
his brain not just his brain but my
brain to and trying to get back into
these 53 cases um I would just speak
quickly to the Eli Lily case which makes
clear that the standard here in
assessing whether um or or whether cost
thrown away should be assessed on a
lumpsum basis it's not a matter of
reprehensible scandalous or outrageous
conduct as my friend suggest in in Eli
Lily OD issue was a an examination that
was adjourn due to a last minute illness
um uh these costs rewarding costs thrown
away on a lumsum basis is not meant to
be punitive it's just meant to
compensate for the real the real costs
incurred and the way we've Quant
Quantified our total costs in the
submissions i i i acknowledge that it's
significant and there was significant
preparation involved for both of those
hearings we've presented you with the
total lumpsum amount uh that was
incurred in preparing for the ing twice
and I would submit Justice gleon that
you you of course now have uh the
discretion to determine uh what what the
appropriate uh percentage of that is um
given given your views of the
circumstances the amount of time between
each of the adjournments I I would just
make one one last submission and that's
on the preparation for the September
hearing I I recognize that we we agreed
to that adjournment and we agreed to
that adjournment assuming that you know
the case wouldn't be the motion wouldn't
be adjourned again um but I I think some
portion of those September costs needs
to be included because those really are
costs thrown away at this point when
we're talking about preparation that Mr
baxer and I did uh a number of months
ago we're not just talking about three
weeks we're talking about um I I I I
guess it's uh I guess it's about three
months now so that's those those are my
submissions uh on costs thrown away can
I just ask you to to either yourself or
Mr Baxter I'm looking at your Annex H
your
submissions and I'm looking at the uh at
the hours I just want to make sure that
I understand or haven't misapprehended
what's happened here um the September
27th hearing
hours uh are roughly half of in fact
exactly half uh with respect to uh in
one case and and almost exactly half in
the other with respect to yourself and
Mr Baxter uh as they relate to the no
November
25 preparation
time is there is that is is are we
double counting here by by mistake or or
is that uh is that in fact uh what's
occurred here that the the prep time is
is double for the November 25 hearing as
it was for the September 27 hearing and
again I'm not asking to explain the
hours I just want to make sure
understand what's what's occurred there
that that is that is actual yes um and
it was significantly more time in
preparation for November 25th there
there's a few reasons uh one in
September uh we hadn't gotten as far in
terms of our preparation because there
was a weekend between when the hearing
was adjourned on a Friday and when the
hearing was scheduled for a Monday so we
anticipated significant prep time over
that weekend uh and I think the other
the other issue is there have been a
number of cases raised in the interim uh
the um the decision in the Supreme Court
the Tellis decision in the federal court
um uh I can't remember if Sketchers was
raised before or after the September
hearing but I and that's fine as I say
it was just just given given the the way
the hours were set up I just wanted to
make sure that uh that there wasn't a
clerical error there or a Mis
misstatement clerically all right thank
you very much uh Mr trano um Mr noban or
Mr Mayor I don't know if who's going to
speak to the issue on your side uh sure
thank you justice gleon I mean we don't
we don't have a lot to add to our
written submissions and I don't intend
to go through them all I don't think
unless you want me to no there's no
need I would just say that one case that
deals with that timeline issue that you
asked about is the TAA case and in that
case um the argument was made that well
some of the some of the preparation
isn't really thrown away it can it can
go forward and uh the court found that
it understood that argument but given
the seven months in that case that went
between the uh the adjourned hearing and
the actual hearing uh that that it was
going to order costs thrown away and it
did so in accordance with column four of
tariff and so we do think that three
weeks uh is brief enough time that we
can't say that the costs have fully been
thrown away and that as we say in our
submissions
they should be awarded in accordance
with ter thank you thank you very
much all right I don't have any further
questions um just before we wrap up just
make sure there's no last minute matters
on on either
side I'm seen everybody shake their head
so with that then uh we'll uh we'll
adour for the day I'll reserve on the
matter thank you for your both your
written submissions and your or
submissions today you've given me uh
lots to think about have a good weekend
and uh all the best over
holidays thank
you the special sitting of the federal
court is now concluded thank you
everyone